ANNAJANSKA,

THE BOLSHEVIK EMPRESS

By George Bernard Shaw

ANNAJANSKA is frankly a bravura piece. The modern variety theatre demands for its "turns" little plays called sketches, to last twenty minutes or so, and to enable some favorite performer to make a brief but dazzling appearance on some barely passable dramatic pretext. Miss Lillah McCarthy and I, as author and actress, have helped to make one another famous on many serious occasions, from Man and Superman to Androcles; and Mr Charles Ricketts has not disdained to snatch moments from his painting and sculpture to design some wonderful dresses for us. We three unbent as Mrs Siddons, Sir Joshua Reynolds and Dr Johnson might have unbent, to devise a turn for the Coliseum variety theatre. Not that we would set down the art of the variety theatre as something to be condescended to, or our own art as elephantine. We should rather crave indulgence as three novices fresh from the awful legitimacy of the highbrow theatre.

Well, Miss McCarthy and Mr Ricketts justified themselves easily in the glamor of the footlights, to the strains of Tchaikovsky's 1812. I fear I did not. I have received only one compliment on my share; and that was from a friend who said, "It is the only one of your works that is not too long." So I have made it a page or two longer, according to my own precept: EMBRACE YOUR REPROACHES: THEY ARE OFTEN GLORIES IN DISGUISE.

Annajanska was first performed at the Coliseum Theatre in London on the 21st January, 1918, with Lillah McCarthy as the Grand Duchess, Henry Miller as Schneidekind, and Randle Ayrton as General Strammfest.

ANNAJANSKA, THE BOLSHEVIK EMPRESS

The General's office in a military station on the east front in Beotia. An office table with a telephone, writing materials, official papers, etc., is set across the room. At the end of the table, a comfortable chair for the General. Behind the chair, a window. Facing it at the other end of the table, a plain wooden bench. At the side of the table, with its back to the door, a common chair, with a typewriter before it. Beside the door, which is opposite the end of the bench, a rack for caps and coats. There is nobody in the room.

General Strammfest enters, followed by Lieutenant Schneidekind. They hang up their cloaks and caps. Schneidekind takes a little longer than Strammfest, who comes to the table.

STRAMMFEST. Schneidekind.

SCHNEIDEKIND. Yes, sir.

STRAMMFEST. Have you sent my report yet to the government? [He sits down.]

SCHNEIDEKIND [coming to the table]. Not yet, sir. Which government do you wish it sent to? [He sits down.]

STRAMMFEST. That depends. What's the latest? Which of them do you think is most likely to be in power tomorrow morning?

SCHNEIDEKIND. Well, the provisional government was going strong yesterday. But today they say that the Prime Minister has shot himself, and that the extreme left fellow has shot all the others.

STRAMMFEST. Yes: that's all very well; but these fellows always shoot themselves with blank cartridge.

SCHNEIDEKIND. Still, even the blank cartridge means backing down. I should send the report to the Maximilianists.

STRAMMFEST. They're no stronger than the Oppidoshavians; and in my own opinion the Moderate Red Revolutionaries are as likely to come out on top as either of them.

SCHNEIDEKIND. I can easily put a few carbon sheets in the typewriter and send a copy each to the lot.

STRAMMFEST. Waste of paper. You might as well send reports to an infant school. [He throws his head on the table with a groan.]

SCHNEIDEKIND. Tired out, Sir?

STRAMMFEST. O Schneidekind, Schneidekind, how can you bear to live?

SCHNEIDEKIND. At my age, sir, I ask myself how can I bear to die?

STRAMMFEST. You are young, young and heartless. You are excited by the revolution: you are attached to abstract things like liberty. But my family has served the Panjandrums of Beotia faithfully for seven centuries. The Panjandrums have kept our place for us at their courts, honored us, promoted us, shed their glory on us, made us what we are. When I hear you young men declaring that you are fighting for civilization, for democracy, for the overthrow of militarism, I ask myself how can a man shed his blood for empty words used by vulgar tradesmen and common laborers: mere wind and stink. [He rises, exalted by his theme.] A king is a splendid reality, a man raised above us like a god. You can see him; you can kiss his hand; you can be cheered by his smile and terrified by his frown. I would have died for my Panjandrum as my father died for his father. Your toiling millions were only too honored to receive the toes of our boots in the proper spot for them when they displeased their betters. And now what is left in life for me? [He relapses into his chair discouraged.] My Panjandrum is deposed and transported to herd with convicts. The army, his pride and glory, is paraded to hear seditious speeches from penniless rebels, with the colonel actually forced to take the chair and introduce the speaker. I myself am made Commander-in-Chief by my own solicitor: a Jew, Schneidekind! a Hebrew Jew! It seems only yesterday that these things would have been the ravings of a madman: today they are the commonplaces of the gutter press. I live now for three objects only: to defeat the enemy, to restore the Panjandrum, and to hang my solicitor.

SCHNEIDEKIND. Be careful, sir: these are dangerous views to utter nowadays. What if I were to betray you?

STRAMMFEST. What!

SCHNEIDEKIND. I won't, of course: my own father goes on just like that; but suppose I did?

STRAMMFEST [chuckling]. I should accuse you of treason to the Revolution, my lad; and they would immediately shoot you, unless you cried and asked to see your mother before you died, when they would probably change their minds and make you a brigadier. Enough. [He rises and expands his chest.] I feel the better for letting myself go. To business. [He takes up a telegram: opens it: and is thunderstruck by its contents.] Great heaven! [He collapses into his chair.] This is the worst blow of all.

SCHNEIDEKIND. What has happened? Are we beaten?

STRAMMFEST. Man, do you think that a mere defeat could strike me down as this news does: I, who have been defeated thirteen times since the war began? O, my master, my master, my Panjandrum! [he is convulsed with sobs.]

SCHNEIDEKIND. They have killed him?

STRAMMFEST. A dagger has been struck through his heart—

SCHNEIDEKIND. Good God!

STRAMMFEST. —and through mine, through mine.

SCHNEIDEKIND [relieved]. Oh, a metaphorical dagger! I thought you meant a real one. What has happened?

STRAMMFEST. His daughter the Grand Duchess Annajanska, she whom the Panjandrina loved beyond all her other children, has—has— [he cannot finish.]

SCHNEIDEKIND. Committed suicide?

STRAMMFEST. No. Better if she had. Oh, far far better.

SCHNEIDEKIND [in hushed tones]. Left the Church?

STRAMMFEST [shocked]. Certainly not. Do not blaspheme, young man.

SCHNEIDEKIND. Asked for the vote?

STRAMMFEST. I would have given it to her with both hands to save her from this.

SCHNEIDEKIND. Save her from what? Dash it, sir, out with it.

STRAMMFEST. She has joined the Revolution.

SCHNEIDEKIND. But so have you, sir. We've all joined the Revolution. She doesn't mean it any more than we do.

STRAMMFEST. Heaven grant you may be right! But that is not the worst. She had eloped with a young officer. Eloped, Schneidekind, eloped!

SCHNEIDEKIND [not particularly impressed]. Yes, Sir.

STRAMMFEST. Annajanska, the beautiful, the innocent, my master's daughter! [He buries his face in his hands.]

The telephone rings.

SCHNEIDEKIND [taking the receiver]. Yes: G.H.Q. Yes... Don't bawl: I'm not a general. Who is it speaking?... Why didn't you say so? don't you know your duty? Next time you will lose your stripe... Oh, they've made you a colonel, have they? Well, they've made me a field-marshal: now what have you to say?... Look here: what did you ring up for? I can't spend the day here listening to your cheek... What! the Grand Duchess [Strammfest starts.] Where did you catch her?

STRAMMFEST [snatching the telephone and listening for the answer]. Speak louder, will you: I am a General I know that, you dolt. Have you captured the officer that was with her?... Damnation! You shall answer for this: you let him go: he bribed you. You must have seen him: the fellow is in the full dress court uniform of the Panderobajensky Hussars. I give you twelve hours to catch him or... what's that you say about the devil? Are you swearing at me, you... Thousand thunders! [To Schneidekind.] The swine says that the Grand Duchess is a devil incarnate. [Into the telephone.] Filthy traitor: is that the way you dare speak of the daughter of our anointed Panjandrum? I'll—

SCHNEIDEKIND [pulling the telephone from his lips]. Take care, sir.

STRAMMFEST. I won't take care: I'll have him shot. Let go that telephone.

SCHNEIDEKIND. But for her own sake, sir—

STRAMMFEST. Eh?—

SCHNEIDEKIND. For her own sake they had better send her here. She will be safe in your hands.

STRAMMFEST [yielding the receiver]. You are right. Be civil to him. I should choke [he sits down].

SCHNEIDEKIND [into the telephone]. Hullo. Never mind all that: it's only a fellow here who has been fooling with the telephone. I had to leave the room for a moment. Wash out: and send the girl along. We'll jolly soon teach her to behave herself here... Oh, you've sent her already. Then why the devil didn't you say so, you—[he hangs up the telephone angrily]. Just fancy: they started her off this morning: and all this is because the fellow likes to get on the telephone and hear himself talk now that he is a colonel. [The telephone rings again. He snatches the receiver furiously.] What's the matter now?... [To the General.] It's our own people downstairs. [Into the receiver.] Here! do you suppose I've nothing else to do than to hang on to the telephone all day?... What's that? Not men enough to hold her! What do you mean? [To the General.] She is there, sir.

STRAMMFEST. Tell them to send her up. I shall have to receive her without even rising, without kissing her hand, to keep up appearances before the escort. It will break my heart.

SCHNEIDEKIND [into the receiver]. Send her up... Tcha! [He hangs up the receiver.] He says she is halfway up already: they couldn't hold her.

The Grand Duchess bursts into the room, dragging with her two exhausted soldiers hanging on desperately to her arms. She is enveloped from head to foot by a fur-lined cloak, and wears a fur cap.

SCHNEIDEKIND [pointing to the bench]. At the word Go, place your prisoner on the bench in a sitting posture; and take your seats right and left of her. Go.

The two soldiers make a supreme effort to force her to sit down. She flings them back so that they are forced to sit on the bench to save themselves from falling backwards over it, and is herself dragged into sitting between them. The second soldier, holding on tight to the Grand Duchess with one hand, produces papers with the other, and waves them towards Schneidekind, who takes them from him and passes them on to the General. He opens them and reads them with a grave expression.

SCHNEIDEKIND. Be good enough to wait, prisoner, until the General has read the papers on your case.

THE GRAND DUCHESS [to the soldiers]. Let go. [To Strammfest]. Tell them to let go, or I'll upset the bench backwards and bash our three heads on the floor.

FIRST SOLDIER. No, little mother. Have mercy on the poor.

STRAMMFEST [growling over the edge of the paper he is reading]. Hold your tongue.

THE GRAND DUCHESS [blazing]. Me, or the soldier?

STRAMMFEST [horrified]. The soldier, madam.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Tell him to let go.

STRAMMFEST. Release the lady.

The soldiers take their hands off her. One of them wipes his fevered brow. The other sucks his wrist.

SCHNEIDKIND [fiercely]. 'ttention!

The two soldiers sit up stiffly.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Oh, let the poor man suck his wrist. It may be poisoned. I bit it.

STRAMMFEST [shocked]. You bit a common soldier!

GRAND DUCHESS. Well, I offered to cauterize it with the poker in the office stove. But he was afraid. What more could I do?

SCHNEIDEKIND. Why did you bite him, prisoner?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. He would not let go.

STRAMMFEST. Did he let go when you bit him?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. No. [Patting the soldier on the back]. You should give the man a cross for his devotion. I could not go on eating him; so I brought him along with me.

STRAMMFEST. Prisoner—

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Don't call me prisoner, General Strammfest. My grandmother dandled you on her knee.

STRAMMFEST [bursting into tears]. O God, yes. Believe me, my heart is what it was then.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Your brain also is what it was then. I will not be addressed by you as prisoner.

STRAMMFEST. I may not, for your own sake, call you by your rightful and most sacred titles. What am I to call you?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. The Revolution has made us comrades. Call me comrade.

STRAMMFEST. I had rather die.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Then call me Annajanska; and I will call you Peter Piper, as grandmamma did.

STRAMMFEST [painfully agitated]. Schneidekind, you must speak to her: I cannot—[he breaks down.]

SCHNEIDEKIND [officially]. The Republic of Beotia has been compelled to confine the Panjandrum and his family, for their own safety, within certain bounds. You have broken those bounds.

STRAMMFEST [taking the word from him]. You are I must say it—a prisoner. What am I to do with you?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. You should have thought of that before you arrested me.

STRAMMFEST. Come, come, prisoner! do you know what will happen to you if you compel me to take a sterner tone with you?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. No. But I know what will happen to you.

STRAMAIFEST. Pray what, prisoner?

THE GLAND DUCHESS. Clergyman's sore throat.

Schneidekind splutters; drops a paper: and conceals his laughter under the table.

STRAMMFEST [thunderously]. Lieutenant Schneidekind.

SCHNEIDEKIND [in a stifled voice]. Yes, Sir. [The table vibrates visibly.]

STRAMMFEST. Come out of it, you fool: you're upsetting the ink.

Schneidekind emerges, red in the face with suppressed mirth.

STRAMMFEST. Why don't you laugh? Don't you appreciate Her Imperial Highness's joke?

SCHNEIDEKIND [suddenly becoming solemn]. I don't want to, sir.

STRAMMFEST. Laugh at once, sir. I order you to laugh.

SCHNEIDEKIND [with a touch of temper]. I really can't, sir. [He sits down decisively.]

STRAMMFEST [growling at him]. Yah! [He turns impressively to the Grand Duchess.] Your Imperial Highness desires me to address you as comrade?

THE GRAND DUCHESS [rising and waving a red handkerchief]. Long live the Revolution, comrade!

STRAMMFEST [rising and saluting]. Proletarians of all lands, unite. Lieutenant Schneidekind, you will rise and sing the Marseillaise.

SCHNEIDEKIND [rising]. But I cannot, sir. I have no voice, no ear.

STRAMMFEST. Then sit down; and bury your shame in your typewriter. [Schneidekind sits down.] Comrade Annajanska, you have eloped with a young officer.

THE GRAND DUCHESS [astounded]. General Strammfest, you lie.

STRAMMFEST. Denial, comrade, is useless. It is through that officer that your movements have been traced. [The Grand Duchess is suddenly enlightened, and seems amused. Strammfest continues an a forensic manner.] He joined you at the Golden Anchor in Hakonsburg. You gave us the slip there; but the officer was traced to Potterdam, where you rejoined him and went alone to Premsylople. What have you done with that unhappy young man? Where is he?

THE GRAND DUCHESS [pretending to whisper an important secret]. Where he has always been.

STRAMMFEST [eagerly]. Where is that?

THE GRAND DUCHESS [impetuously]. In your imagination. I came alone. I am alone. Hundreds of officers travel every day from Hakonsburg to Potterdam. What do I know about them?

STRAMMFEST. They travel in khaki. They do not travel in full dress court uniform as this man did.

SCHNEIDEKIND. Only officers who are eloping with grand duchesses wear court uniform: otherwise the grand duchesses could not be seen with them.

STRAMMFEST. Hold your tongue. [Schneidekind, in high dudgeon, folds his arms and retires from the conversation. The General returns to his paper and to his examination of the Grand Duchess.] This officer travelled with your passport. What have you to say to that?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Bosh! How could a man travel with a woman's passport?

STRAMMFEST. It is quite simple, as you very well know. A dozen travellers arrive at the boundary. The official collects their passports. He counts twelve persons; then counts the passports. If there are twelve, he is satisfied.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Then how do you know that one of the passports was mine?

STRAMMFEST. A waiter at the Potterdam Hotel looked at the officer's passport when he was in his bath. It was your passport.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Stuff! Why did he not have me arrested?

STRAMMFEST. When the waiter returned to the hotel with the police the officer had vanished; and you were there with your own passport. They knouted him.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Oh! Strammfest, send these men away. I must speak to you alone.

STRAMMFEST [rising in horror]. No: this is the last straw: I cannot consent. It is impossible, utterly, eternally impossible, that a daughter of the Imperial House should speak to any one alone, were it even her own husband.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. You forget that there is an exception. She may speak to a child alone. [She rises.] Strammfest, you have been dandled on my grandmother's knee. By that gracious action the dowager Panjandrina made you a child forever. So did Nature, by the way. I order you to speak to me alone. Do you hear? I order you. For seven hundred years no member of your family has ever disobeyed an order from a member of mine. Will you disobey me?

STRAMMFEST. There is an alternative to obedience. The dead cannot disobey. [He takes out his pistol and places the muzzle against his temple.]

SCHNEIDEKIND [snatching the pistol from him]. For God's sake, General—

STRAMMFEST [attacking him furiously to recover the weapon]. Dog of a subaltern, restore that pistol and my honor.

SCHNEIDEKIND [reaching out with the pistol to the Grand Duchess]. Take it: quick: he is as strong as a bull.

THE GRAND DUCHESS [snatching it]. Aha! Leave the room, all of you except the General. At the double! lightning! electricity! [She fires shot after shot, spattering the bullets about the ankles of the soldiers. They fly precipitately. She turns to Schneidekind, who has by this time been flung on the floor by the General.] You too. [He scrambles up.] March. [He flies to the door.]

SCHNEIDEKIND [turning at the door]. For your own sake, comrade—

THE GRAND DUCHESS [indignantly]. Comrade! You!!! Go. [She fires two more shots. He vanishes.]

STRAMMFEST [making an impulsive movement towards her]. My Imperial Mistress—

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Stop. I have one bullet left, if you attempt to take this from me [putting the pistol to her temple].

STRAMMFEST [recoiling, and covering his eyes with his hands]. No no: put it down: put it down. I promise everything: I swear anything; but put it down, I implore you.

THE GRAND DUCHESS [throwing it on the table]. There!

STRAMMFEST [uncovering his eyes]. Thank God!

THE GRAND DUCHESS [gently]. Strammfest: I am your comrade. Am I nothing more to you?

STRAMMFEST [falling on his knee]. You are, God help me, all that is left to me of the only power I recognize on earth [he kisses her hand].

THE GRAND DUCHESS [indulgently]. Idolater! When will you learn that our strength has never been in ourselves, but in your illusions about us? [She shakes off her kindliness, and sits down in his chair.] Now tell me, what are your orders? And do you mean to obey them?

STRAMMFEST [starting like a goaded ox, and blundering fretfully about the room]. How can I obey six different dictators, and not one gentleman among the lot of them? One of them orders me to make peace with the foreign enemy. Another orders me to offer all the neutral countries 48 hours to choose between adopting his views on the single tax and being instantly invaded and annihilated. A third orders me to go to a damned Socialist Conference and explain that Beotia will allow no annexations and no indemnities, and merely wishes to establish the Kingdom of Heaven on Earth throughout the universe. [He finishes behind Schneidekind's chair.]

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Damn their trifling!

STRAMMFEST. I thank Your Imperial Highness from the bottom of my heart for that expression. Europe thanks you.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. M'yes; but—[rising]. Strammfest, you know that your cause—the cause of the dynasty—is lost.

STRAMMFEST. You must not say so. It is treason, even from you. [He sinks, discouraged, into the chair, and covers his face with his hand.]

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Do not deceive yourself, General: never again will a Panjandrum reign in Beotia. [She walks slowly across the room, brooding bitterly, and thinking aloud.] We are so decayed, so out of date, so feeble, so wicked in our own despite, that we have come at last to will our own destruction.

STRAMMFEST. You are uttering blasphemy.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. All great truths begin as blasphemies. All the king's horses and all the king's men cannot set up my father's throne again. If they could, you would have done it, would you not?

STRAMMFEST. God knows I would!

THE GRAND DUCHESS. You really mean that? You would keep the people in their hopeless squalid misery? you would fill those infamous prisons again with the noblest spirits in the land? you would thrust the rising sun of liberty back into the sea of blood from which it has risen? And all because there was in the middle of the dirt and ugliness and horror a little patch of court splendor in which you could stand with a few orders on your uniform, and yawn day after day and night after night in unspeakable boredom until your grave yawned wider still, and you fell into it because you had nothing better to do. How can you be so stupid, so heartless?

STRAMMFEST. You must be mad to think of royalty in such a way. I never yawned at court. The dogs yawned; but that was because they were dogs: they had no imagination, no ideals, no sense of honor and dignity to sustain them.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. My poor Strammfest: you were not often enough at court to tire of it. You were mostly soldiering; and when you came home to have a new order pinned on your breast, your happiness came through looking at my father and mother and at me, and adoring us. Was that not so?

STRAMMFEST. Do YOU reproach me with it? I am not ashamed of it.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Oh, it was all very well for you, Strammfest. But think of me, of me! standing there for you to gape at, and knowing that I was no goddess, but only a girl like any other girl! It was cruelty to animals: you could have stuck up a wax doll or a golden calf to worship; it would not have been bored.

STRAMMFEST. Stop; or I shall renounce my allegiance to you. I have had women flogged for such seditious chatter as this.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Do not provoke me to send a bullet through your head for reminding me of it.

STRAMMFEST. You always had low tastes. You are no true daughter of the Panjandrums: you are a changeling, thrust into the Panjandrina's bed by some profligate nurse. I have heard stories of your childhood: of how—

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Ha, ha! Yes: they took me to the circus when I was a child. It was my first moment of happiness, my first glimpse of heaven. I ran away and joined the troupe. They caught me and dragged me back to my gilded cage; but I had tasted freedom; and they never could make me forget it.

STRAMMFEST. Freedom! To be the slave of an acrobat! to be exhibited to the public! to—

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Oh, I was trained to that. I had learnt that part of the business at court.

STRAMMFEST. You had not been taught to strip yourself half naked and turn head over heels—

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Man, I WANTED to get rid of my swaddling clothes and turn head over heels. I wanted to, I wanted to, I wanted to. I can do it still. Shall I do it now?

STRAMMFEST. If you do, I swear I will throw myself from the window so that I may meet your parents in heaven without having my medals torn from my breast by them.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Oh, you are incorrigible. You are mad, infatuated. You will not believe that we royal divinities are mere common flesh and blood even when we step down from our pedestals and tell you ourselves what a fool you are. I will argue no more with you: I will use my power. At a word from me your men will turn against you: already half of them do not salute you; and you dare not punish them: you have to pretend not to notice it.

STRAMMFEST. It is not for you to taunt me with that if it is so.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. [haughtily]. Taunt! I condescend to taunt! To taunt a common General! You forget yourself, sir.

STRAMMFEST [dropping on his knee submissively]. Now at last you speak like your royal self.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Oh, Strammfest, Strammfest, they have driven your slavery into your very bones. Why did you not spit in my face?

STRAMMFEST [rising with a shudder]. God forbid!

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Well, since you will be my slave, take your orders from me. I have not come here to save our wretched family and our bloodstained crown. I am come to save the Revolution.

STRAMMFEST. Stupid as I am, I have come to think that I had better save that than save nothing. But what will the Revolution do for the people? Do not be deceived by the fine speeches of the revolutionary leaders and the pamphlets of the revolutionary writers. How much liberty is there where they have gained the upper hand? Are they not hanging, shooting, imprisoning as much as ever we did? Do they ever tell the people the truth? No: if the truth does not suit them they spread lies instead, and make it a crime to tell the truth.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Of course they do. Why should they not?

STRAMMFEST [hardly able to believe his ears]. Why should they not?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Yes: why should they not? We did it. You did it, whip in hand: you flogged women for teaching children to read.

STRAMMFEST. To read sedition. To read Karl Marx.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Pshaw! How could they learn to read the Bible without learning to read Karl Marx? Why do you not stand to your guns and justify what you did, instead of making silly excuses? Do you suppose I think flogging a woman worse than flogging a man? I, who am a woman myself!

STRAMMFEST. I am at a loss to understand your Imperial Highness. You seem to me to contradict yourself.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Nonsense! I say that if the people cannot govern themselves, they must be governed by somebody. If they will not do their duty without being half forced and half humbugged, somebody must force them and humbug them. Some energetic and capable minority must always be in power. Well, I am on the side of the energetic minority whose principles I agree with. The Revolution is as cruel as we were; but its aims are my aims. Therefore I stand for the Revolution.

STRAMMFEST. You do not know what you are saying. This is pure Bolshevism. Are you, the daughter of a Panjandrum, a Bolshevist?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. I am anything that will make the world less like a prison and more like a circus.

STRAMMFEST. Ah! You still want to be a circus star.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Yes, and be billed as the Bolshevik Empress. Nothing shall stop me. You have your orders, General Strammfest: save the Revolution.

STRAMMFEST. What Revolution? Which Revolution? No two of your rabble of revolutionists mean the same thing by the Revolution What can save a mob in which every man is rushing in a different direction?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. I will tell you. The war can save it.

STRAMMFEST. The war?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Yes, the war. Only a great common danger and a great common duty can unite us and weld these wrangling factions into a solid commonwealth.

STRAMMFEST. Bravo! War sets everything right: I have always said so. But what is a united people without a united army? And what can I do? I am only a soldier. I cannot make speeches: I have won no victories: they will not rally to my call [again he sinks into his chair with his former gesture of discouragement].

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Are you sure they will not rally to mine?

STRAMMFEST. Oh, if only you were a man and a soldier!

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Suppose I find you a man and a soldier?

STRAMMFEST [rising in a fury]. Ah! the scoundrel you eloped with! You think you will shove this fellow into an army command, over my head. Never.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. You promised everything. You swore anything. [She marches as if in front of a regiment.] I know that this man alone can rouse the army to enthusiasm.

STRAMMFEST. Delusion! Folly! He is some circus acrobat; and you are in love with him.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. I swear I am not in love with him. I swear I will never marry him.

STRAMMFEST. Then who is he?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Anybody in the world but you would have guessed long ago. He is under your very eyes.

STRAMMFEST [staring past her right and left]. Where?

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Look out of the window.

He rushes to the window, looking for the officer. The Grand Duchess takes off her cloak and appears in the uniform of the Panderobajensky Hussars.

STRAMMFEST [peering through the window]. Where is he? I can see no one.

THE GRAND DUCHESS. Here, silly.

STRAMMFEST [turning]. You! Great Heavens! The Bolshevik Empress!

Augustus Does His Bit

A True-to-Life Farce

Preface

I wish to express my gratitude for certain good offices which “Augustus” secured for me in January, 1917. I had been invited to visit the theatre of war in Flanders by the Commander-in-Chief: an invitation which was, under the circumstances, a summons to duty. Thus I had occasion to spend some days in procuring the necessary passport and other official facilities for my journey. It happened just then that the Stage Society gave a performance of this little play. It opened the heart of every official to me. I have always been treated with distinguished consideration in my contracts with bureaucracy during the war; but on this occasion I found myself persona grata in the highest degree. There was only one word when the formalities were disposed of; and that was “We are up against Augustus all day.” The showing-up of Augustus scandalized one or two innocent and patriotic critics who regarded the prowess of the British army as inextricably bound up with Highcastle prestige. But our Government departments knew better: their problem was how to win the war with Augustus on their backs, well-meaning, brave, patriotic, but obstructively fussy, self-important, imbecile, and disastrous.

Save for the satisfaction of being able to laugh at Augustus in the theatre, nothing, as far as I know, came of my dramatic reduction of him to absurdity. Generals, admirals, Prime Ministers and Controllers, not to mention Emperors, Kaisers and Tsars, were scrapped remorselessly at home and abroad, for their sins or services, as the case might be. But Augustus stood like the Eddystone in a storm, and stands so to this day. He gave us his word that he was indispensable and we took it.

“Augustus Does His Bit” was performed for the first time at the Court Theatre in London by the Stage Society on the 21st January, 1917, with Lalla Vandervelde as The Lady, F. B. J. Sharp as Lord Augustus Highcastle, and Charles Rock as Horatio Floyd Beamish.

Dramatis Personae

Lord Augustus Highcastle

Horatio Floyd Beamish

The Lady

Augustus Does His Bit

The Mayor’s parlor in the Town Hall of Little Pifflington. Lord Augustus Highcastle, a distinguished member of the governing class, in the uniform of a colonel, and very well preserved at forty-five, is comfortably seated at a writing table with his heels on it, reading The Morning Post. The door faces him, a little to his left, at the other side of the room. The window is behind him. In the fireplace, a gas stove. On the table a bell button and a telephone. Portraits of past Mayors, in robes and gold chains, adorn the walls. An elderly Clerk with a short white beard and whiskers, and a very red nose, shuffles in.

Augustus | Hastily putting aside his paper and replacing his feet on the floor. Hullo! Who are you?
The Clerk | The staff. A slight impediment in his speech adds to the impression of incompetence produced by his age and appearance.
Augustus | You the staff! What do you mean, man?
The Clerk | What I say. There ain’t anybody else.
Augustus | Tush! Where are the others?
The Clerk | At the front.
Augustus | Quite right. Most proper. Why aren’t you at the front?
The Clerk | Over age. Fifty-seven.
Augustus | But you can still do your bit. Many an older man is in the G.R.’s, or volunteering for home defence.
The Clerk | I have volunteered.
Augustus | Then why are you not in uniform?
The Clerk | They said they wouldn’t have me if I was given away with a pound of tea. Told me to go home and not be an old silly. A sense of unbearable wrong, till now only smouldering in him, bursts into flame. Young Bill Knight, that I took with me, got two and sevenpence. I got nothing. Is it justice? This country is going to the dogs, if you ask me.
Augustus | Rising indignantly. I do not ask you, sir; and I will not allow you to say such things in my presence. Our statesmen are the greatest known to history. Our generals are invincible. Our army is the admiration of the world. Furiously. How dare you tell me that the country is going to the dogs!
The Clerk | Why did they give young Bill Knight two and sevenpence, and not give me even my tram fare? Do you call that being great statesmen? As good as robbing me, I call it.
Augustus | That’s enough. Leave the room. He sits down and takes up his pen, settling himself to work. The Clerk shuffles to the door. Augustus adds, with cold politeness: Send me the Secretary.
The Clerk | I’m the Secretary. I can’t leave the room and send myself to you at the same time, can I?
Augustus | Don’t be insolent. Where is the gentleman I have been corresponding with: Mr. Horatio Floyd Beamish?
The Clerk | Returning and bowing. Here. Me.
Augustus | You! Ridiculous. What right have you to call yourself by a pretentious name of that sort?
The Clerk | You may drop the Horatio Floyd. Beamish is good enough for me.
Augustus | Is there nobody else to take my instructions?
The Clerk | It’s me or nobody. And for two pins I’d chuck it. Don’t you drive me too far. Old ’uns like me is up in the world now.
Augustus | If we were not at war, I should discharge you on the spot for disrespectful behavior. But England is in danger; and I cannot think of my personal dignity at such a moment. Shouting at him. Don’t you think of yours, either, worm that you are; or I’ll have you arrested under the Defence of the Realm Act, double quick.
The Clerk | What do I care about the realm? They done me out of two and seven—
Augustus | Oh, damn your two and seven! Did you receive my letters?
The Clerk | Yes.
Augustus | I addressed a meeting here last night—went straight to the platform from the train. I wrote to you that I should expect you to be present and report yourself. Why did you not do so?
The Clerk | The police wouldn’t let me on the platform.
Augustus | Did you tell them who you were?
The Clerk | They knew who I was. That’s why they wouldn’t let me up.
Augustus | This is too silly for anything. This town wants waking up. I made the best recruiting speech I ever made in my life; and not a man joined.
The Clerk | What did you expect? You told them our gallant fellows is falling at the rate of a thousand a day in the big push. Dying for Little Pifflington, you says. Come and take their places, you says. That ain’t the way to recruit.
Augustus | But I expressly told them their widows would have pensions.
The Clerk | I heard you. Would have been all right if it had been the widows you wanted to get round.
Augustus | Rising angrily. This town is inhabited by dastards. I say it with a full sense of responsibility, dastards! They call themselves Englishmen; and they are afraid to fight.
The Clerk | Afraid to fight! You should see them on a Saturday night.
Augustus | Yes, they fight one another; but they won’t fight the Germans.
The Clerk | They got grudges again one another: how can they have grudges again the Huns that they never saw? They’ve no imagination: that’s what it is. Bring the Huns here; and they’ll quarrel with them fast enough.
Augustus | Returning to his seat with a grunt of disgust. Mf! They’ll have them here if they’re not careful. Seated. Have you carried out my orders about the war saving?
The Clerk | Yes.
Augustus | The allowance of petrol has been reduced by three quarters?
The Clerk | It has.
Augustus | And you have told the motorcar people to come here and arrange to start munition work now that their motor business is stopped?
The Clerk | It ain’t stopped. They’re busier than ever.
Augustus | Busy at what?
The Clerk | Making small cars.
Augustus | New cars!
The Clerk | The old cars only do twelve miles to the gallon. Everybody has to have a car that will do thirty-five now.
Augustus | Can’t they take the train?
The Clerk | There ain’t no trains now. They’ve tore up the rails and sent them to the front.
Augustus | Psha!
The Clerk | Well, we have to get about somehow.
Augustus | This is perfectly monstrous. Not in the least what I intended.
The Clerk | Hell—
Augustus | Sir!
The Clerk | Explaining. Hell, they says, is paved with good intentions.
Augustus | Springing to his feet. Do you mean to insinuate that hell is paved with my good intentions—with the good intentions of His Majesty’s Government?
The Clerk | I don’t mean to insinuate anything until the Defence of the Realm Act is repealed. It ain’t safe.
Augustus | They told me that this town had set an example to all England in the matter of economy. I came down here to promise the Mayor a knighthood for his exertions.
The Clerk | The Mayor! Where do I come in?
Augustus | You don’t come in. You go out. This is a fool of a place. I’m greatly disappointed. Deeply disappointed. Flinging himself back into his chair. Disgusted.
The Clerk | What more can we do? We’ve shut up everything. The picture gallery is shut. The museum is shut. The theatres and picture shows is shut: I haven’t seen a movie picture for six months.
Augustus | Man, man: do you want to see picture shows when the Hun is at the gate?
The Clerk | Mournfully. I don’t now, though it drove me melancholy mad at first. I was on the point of taking a pennorth of rat poison—
Augustus | Why didn’t you?
The Clerk | Because a friend advised me to take to drink instead. That saved my life, though it makes me very poor company in the mornings, as hiccuping perhaps you’ve noticed.
Augustus | Well, upon my soul! You are not ashamed to stand there and confess yourself a disgusting drunkard.
The Clerk | Well, what of it? We’re at war now; and everything’s changed. Besides, I should lose my job here if I stood drinking at the bar. I’m a respectable man and must buy my drink and take it home with me. And they won’t serve me with less than a quart. If you’d told me before the war that I could get through a quart of whisky in a day, I shouldn’t have believed you. That’s the good of war: it brings out powers in a man that he never suspected himself capable of. You said so yourself in your speech last night.
Augustus | I did not know that I was talking to an imbecile. You ought to be ashamed of yourself. There must be an end of this drunken slacking. I’m going to establish a new order of things here. I shall come down every morning before breakfast until things are properly in train. Have a cup of coffee and two rolls for me here every morning at half-past ten.
The Clerk | You can’t have no rolls. The only baker that baked rolls was a Hun; and he’s been interned.
Augustus | Quite right, too. And was there no Englishman to take his place?
The Clerk | There was. But he was caught spying; and they took him up to London and shot him.
Augustus | Shot an Englishman!
The Clerk | Well, it stands to reason if the Germans wanted to spy they wouldn’t employ a German that everybody would suspect, don’t it?
Augustus | Rising again. Do you mean to say, you scoundrel, that an Englishman is capable of selling his country to the enemy for gold?
The Clerk | Not as a general thing I wouldn’t say it; but there’s men here would sell their own mothers for two coppers if they got the chance.
Augustus | Beamish, it’s an ill bird that fouls its own nest.
The Clerk | It wasn’t me that let Little Pifflington get foul. I don’t belong to the governing classes. I only tell you why you can’t have no rolls.
Augustus | Intensely irritated. Can you tell me where I can find an intelligent being to take my orders?
The Clerk | One of the street sweepers used to teach in the school until it was shut up for the sake of economy. Will he do?
Augustus | What! You mean to tell me that when the lives of the gallant fellows in our trenches, and the fate of the British Empire, depend on our keeping up the supply of shells, you are wasting money on sweeping the streets?
The Clerk | We have to. We dropped it for a while; but the infant death rate went up something frightful.
Augustus | What matters the death rate of Little Pifflington in a moment like this? Think of our gallant soldiers, not of your squalling infants.
The Clerk | If you want soldiers you must have children. You can’t buy ’em in boxes, like toy soldiers.
Augustus | Beamish, the long and the short of it is, you are no patriot. Go downstairs to your office; and have that gas stove taken away and replaced by an ordinary grate. The Board of Trade has urged on me the necessity for economizing gas.
The Clerk | Our orders from the Minister of Munitions is to use gas instead of coal, because it saves material. Which is it to be?
Augustus | Bawling furiously at him. Both! Don’t criticize your orders: obey them. Yours not to reason why: yours but to do and die. That’s war. Cooling down. Have you anything else to say?
The Clerk | Yes: I want a rise.
Augustus | Reeling against the table in his horror. A rise! Horatio Floyd Beamish, do you know that we are at war?
The Clerk | Feebly ironical. I have noticed something about it in the papers. Heard you mention it once or twice, now I come to think of it.
Augustus | Our gallant fellows are dying in the trenches; and you want a rise!
The Clerk | What are they dying for? To keep me alive, ain’t it? Well, what’s the good of that if I’m dead of hunger by the time they come back?
Augustus | Everybody else is making sacrifices without a thought of self; and you—
The Clerk | Not half, they ain’t. Where’s the baker’s sacrifice? Where’s the coal merchant’s? Where’s the butcher’s? Charging me double: that’s how they sacrifice themselves. Well, I want to sacrifice myself that way too. Just double next Saturday: double and not a penny less; or no secretary for you. He stiffens himself shakily, and makes resolutely for the door.
Augustus | Looking after him contemptuously. Go: miserable pro-German.
The Clerk | Rushing back and facing him. Who are you calling a pro-German?
Augustus | Another word, and I charge you under the Act with discouraging me. Go.
The clerk blenches and goes out, cowed.
The telephone rings.
Augustus | Taking up the telephone receiver. Hallo. Yes: who are you? … oh, Blueloo, is it? … Yes: there’s nobody in the room: fire away. What? … A spy! … A woman! … Yes: brought it down with me. Do you suppose I’m such a fool as to let it out of my hands? Why, it gives a list of all our antiaircraft emplacements from Ramsgate to Skegness. The Germans would give a million for it—what? … But how could she possibly know about it? I haven’t mentioned it to a soul, except, of course, dear Lucy … Oh, Toto and Lady Popham and that lot: they don’t count: they’re all right. I mean that I haven’t mentioned it to any Germans. … Pooh! Don’t you be nervous, old chap. I know you think me a fool; but I’m not such a fool as all that. If she tries to get it out of me I’ll have her in the Tower before you ring up again. The clerk returns. Sh‑sh! Somebody’s just come in: ring off. Goodbye. He hangs up the receiver.
The Clerk | Are you engaged? His manner is strangely softened.
Augustus | What business is that of yours? However, if you will take the trouble to read the society papers for this week, you will see that I am engaged to the Honorable Lucy Popham, youngest daughter of—
The Clerk | That ain’t what I mean. Can you see a female?
Augustus | Of course I can see a female as easily as a male. Do you suppose I’m blind?
The Clerk | You don’t seem to follow me, somehow. There’s a female downstairs: what you might call a lady. She wants to know can you see her if I let her up.
Augustus | Oh, you mean am I disengaged. Tell the lady I have just received news of the greatest importance which will occupy my entire attention for the rest of the day, and that she must write for an appointment.
The Clerk | I’ll ask her to explain her business to me. I ain’t above talking to a handsome young female when I get the chance. Going.
Augustus | Stop. Does she seem to be a person of consequence?
The Clerk | A regular marchioness, if you ask me.
Augustus | Hm! Beautiful, did you say?
The Clerk | A human chrysanthemum, sir, believe me.
Augustus | It will be extremely inconvenient for me to see her; but the country is in danger; and we must not consider our own comfort. Think how our gallant fellows are suffering in the trenches! Show her up. The Clerk makes for the door, whistling the latest popular ballad. Stop whistling instantly, sir. This is not a casino.
The Clerk | Ain’t it? You just wait till you see her. He goes out.
Augustus produces a mirror, a comb, and a pot of moustache pomade from the drawer of the writing table, and sits down before the mirror to put some touches to his toilet.
The Clerk returns, devotedly ushering a very attractive Lady, brilliantly dressed. She has a dainty wallet hanging from her wrist. Augustus hastily covers up his toilet apparatus with The Morning Post, and rises in an attitude of pompous condescension.
The Clerk | To Augustus. Here she is. To the Lady. May I offer you a chair, lady? He places a chair at the writing table opposite Augustus, and steals out on tiptoe.
Augustus | Be seated, madam.
The Lady | Sitting down. Are you Lord Augustus Highcastle?
Augustus | Sitting also. Madam, I am.
The Lady | With awe. The great Lord Augustus?
Augustus | I should not dream of describing myself so, Madam; but no doubt I have impressed my countrymen—and bowing gallantly may I say my countrywomen—as having some exceptional claims to their consideration.
The Lady | Emotionally. What a beautiful voice you have!
Augustus | What you hear, madam, is the voice of my country, which now takes a sweet and noble tone even in the harsh mouth of high officialism.
The Lady | Please go on. You express yourself so wonderfully!
Augustus | It would be strange indeed if, after sitting on thirty-seven Royal Commissions, mostly as chairman, I had not mastered the art of public expression. Even the Radical papers have paid me the high compliment of declaring that I am never more impressive than when I have nothing to say.
The Lady | I never read the Radical papers. All I can tell you is that what we women admire in you is not the politician, but the man of action, the heroic warrior, the beau sabreur.
Augustus | Gloomily. Madam, I beg! Please! My military exploits are not a pleasant subject, unhappily.
The Lady | Oh, I know, I know. How shamefully you have been treated! what ingratitude! But the country is with you. The women are with you. Oh, do you think all our hearts did not throb and all our nerves thrill when we heard how, when you were ordered to occupy that terrible quarry in Hulluch, and you swept into it at the head of your men like a sea-god riding on a tidal wave, you suddenly sprang over the top shouting “To Berlin! Forward!”; dashed at the German army single-handed; and were cut off and made prisoner by the Huns.
Augustus | Yes, madam; and what was my reward? They said I had disobeyed orders, and sent me home. Have they forgotten Nelson in the Baltic? Has any British battle ever been won except by a bold initiative? I say nothing of professional jealousy: it exists in the army as elsewhere; but it is a bitter thought to me that the recognition denied me by my country—or rather by the Radical cabal in the Cabinet which pursues my family with rancorous class hatred—that this recognition, I say, came to me at the hands of an enemy—of a rank Prussian.
The Lady | You don’t say so!
Augustus | How else should I be here instead of starving to death in Ruhleben? Yes, madam: the Colonel of the Pomeranian regiment which captured me, after learning what I had done, and conversing for an hour with me on European politics and military strategy, declared that nothing would induce him to deprive my country of my services, and set me free. I offered, of course, to procure the release in exchange of a German officer of equal quality; but he would not hear of it. He was kind enough to say he could not believe that a German officer answering to that description existed. With emotion. I had my first taste of the ingratitude of my own country as I made my way back to our lines. A shot from our front trench struck me in the head. I still carry the flattened projectile as a trophy. He throws it on the table; the noise it makes testifies to its weight. Had it penetrated to the brain I might never have sat on another Royal Commission. Fortunately we have strong heads, we Highcastles. Nothing has ever penetrated to our brains.
The Lady | How thrilling! How simple! And how tragic! But you will forgive England? Remember: England! Forgive her.
Augustus | With gloomy magnanimity. It will make no difference whatever to my services to my country. Though she slay me, yet will I, if not exactly trust in her, at least take my part in her government. I am ever at my country’s call. Whether it be the embassy in a leading European capital, a governor-generalship in the tropics, or my humble mission here to make Little Pifflington do its bit, I am always ready for the sacrifice. Whilst England remains England, wherever there is a public job to be done you will find a Highcastle sticking to it. And now, madam, enough of my tragic personal history. You have called on business. What can I do for you?
The Lady | You have relatives at the Foreign Office, have you not?
Augustus | Haughtily. Madam, the Foreign Office is staffed by my relatives exclusively.
The Lady | Has the Foreign Office warned you that you are being pursued by a female spy who is determined to obtain possession of a certain list of gun emplacements—
Augustus | Interrupting her somewhat loftily. All that is perfectly well known to this department, madam.
The Lady | Surprised and rather indignant. Is it? Who told you? Was it one of your German brothers-in-law?
Augustus | Injured, remonstrating. I have only three German brothers-in-law, madam. Really, from your tone, one would suppose that I had several. Pardon my sensitiveness on that subject; but reports are continually being circulated that I have been shot as a traitor in the courtyard of the Ritz Hotel simply because I have German brothers-in-law. With feeling. If you had a German brother-in-law, madam, you would know that nothing else in the world produces so strong an anti-German feeling. Life affords no keener pleasure than finding a brother-in-law’s name in the German casualty list.
The Lady | Nobody knows that better than I. Wait until you hear what I have come to tell you: you will understand me as no one else could. Listen. This spy, this woman—
Augustus | All attention. Yes?
The Lady | She is a German. A Hun.
Augustus | Yes, yes. She would be. Continue.
The Lady | She is my sister-in-law.
Augustus | Deferentially. I see you are well connected, madam. Proceed.
The Lady | Need I add that she is my bitterest enemy?
Augustus | May I—He proffers his hand. They shake, fervently. From this moment onward Augustus becomes more and more confidential, gallant, and charming.
The Lady | Quite so. Well, she is an intimate friend of your brother at the War Office, Hungerford Highcastle, Blueloo as you call him, I don’t know why.
Augustus | Explaining. He was originally called The Singing Oyster, because he sang drawing-room ballads with such an extraordinary absence of expression. He was then called the Blue Point for a season or two. Finally he became Blueloo.
The Lady | Oh, indeed: I didn’t know. Well, Blueloo is simply infatuated with my sister-in-law; and he has rashly let out to her that this list is in your possession. He forgot himself because he was in a towering rage at its being entrusted to you: his language was terrible. He ordered all the guns to be shifted at once.
Augustus | What on earth did he do that for?
The Lady | I can’t imagine. But this I know. She made a bet with him that she would come down here and obtain possession of that list and get clean away into the street with it. He took the bet on condition that she brought it straight back to him at the War Office.
Augustus | Good heavens! And you mean to tell me that Blueloo was such a dolt as to believe that she could succeed? Does he take me for a fool?
The Lady | Oh, impossible! He is jealous of your intellect. The bet is an insult to you: don’t you feel that? After what you have done for our country—
Augustus | Oh, never mind that. It is the idiocy of the thing I look at. He’ll lose his bet; and serve him right!
The Lady | You feel sure you will be able to resist the siren? I warn you, she is very fascinating.
Augustus | You need have no fear, madam. I hope she will come and try it on. Fascination is a game that two can play at. For centuries the younger sons of the Highcastles have had nothing to do but fascinate attractive females when they were not sitting on Royal Commissions or on duty at Knightsbridge barracks. By Gad, madam, if the siren comes here she will meet her match.
The Lady | I feel that. But if she fails to seduce you—
Augustus | Blushing. Madam!
The Lady | Continuing.—from your allegiance—
Augustus | Oh, that!
The Lady | —she will resort to fraud, to force, to anything. She will burgle your office: she will have you attacked and garotted at night in the street.
Augustus | Pooh! I’m not afraid.
The Lady | Oh, your courage will only tempt you into danger. She may get the list after all. It is true that the guns are moved. But she would win her bet.
Augustus | Cautiously. You did not say that the guns were moved. You said that Blueloo had ordered them to be moved.
The Lady | Well, that is the same thing, isn’t it?
Augustus | Not quite—at the War Office. No doubt those guns will be moved: possibly even before the end of the war.
The Lady | Then you think they are there still! But if the German War Office gets the list—and she will copy it before she gives it back to Blueloo, you may depend on it—all is lost.
Augustus | Lazily. Well, I should not go as far as that. Lowering his voice. Will you swear to me not to repeat what I am going to say to you; for if the British public knew that I had said it, I should be at once hounded down as a pro-German.
The Lady | I will be silent as the grave. I swear it.
Augustus | Again taking it easily. Well, our people have for some reason made up their minds that the German War Office is everything that our War Office is not—that it carries promptitude, efficiency, and organization to a pitch of completeness and perfection that must be, in my opinion, destructive to the happiness of the staff. My own view—which you are pledged, remember, not to betray—is that the German War Office is no better than any other War Office. I found that opinion on my observation of the characters of my brothers-in-law: one of whom, by the way, is on the German general staff. I am not at all sure that this list of gun emplacements would receive the smallest attention. You see, there are always so many more important things to be attended to. Family matters, and so on, you understand.
The Lady | Still, if a question were asked in the House of Commons—
Augustus | The great advantage of being at war, madam, is that nobody takes the slightest notice of the House of Commons. No doubt it is sometimes necessary for a Minister to soothe the more seditious members of that assembly by giving a pledge or two; but the War Office takes no notice of such things.
The Lady | Staring at him. Then you think this list of gun emplacements doesn’t matter!!
Augustus | By no means, madam. It matters very much indeed. If this spy were to obtain possession of the list, Blueloo would tell the story at every dinner-table in London; and—
The Lady | And you might lose your post. Of course.
Augustus | Amazed and indignant. I lose my post! What are you dreaming about, madam? How could I possibly be spared? There are hardly Highcastles enough at present to fill half the posts created by this war. No: Blueloo would not go that far. He is at least a gentleman. But I should be chaffed; and, frankly, I don’t like being chaffed.
The Lady | Of course not. Who does? It would never do. Oh never, never.
Augustus | I’m glad you see it in that light. And now, as a measure of security, I shall put that list in my pocket. He begins searching vainly from drawer to drawer in the writing table. Where on earth—? What the dickens did I—? That’s very odd: I—Where the deuce—? I thought I had put it in the— Oh, here it is! No: this is Lucy’s last letter.
The Lady | Elegiacally. Lucy’s Last Letter! What a title for a picture play!
Augustus | Delighted. Yes: it is, isn’t it? Lucy appeals to the imagination like no other woman. By the way handing over the letter I wonder could you read it for me? Lucy is a darling girl; but I really can’t read her writing. In London I get the office typist to decipher it and make me a typed copy; but here there is nobody.
The Lady | Puzzling over it. It is really almost illegible. I think the beginning is meant for “Dearest Gus.”
Augustus | Eagerly. Yes: that is what she usually calls me. Please go on.
The Lady | Trying to decipher it. “What a”—“what a”—oh yes: “what a forgetful old”—something—“you are!” I can’t make out the word.
Augustus | Greatly interested. Is it blighter? That is a favorite expression of hers.
The Lady | I think so. At all events it begins with a B. Reading. “What a forgetful old”— She is interrupted by a knock at the door.
Augustus | Impatiently. Come in. The Clerk enters, clean shaven and in khaki, with an official paper and an envelope in his hand. What is this ridiculous mummery, sir?
The Clerk | Coming to the table and exhibiting his uniform to both. They’ve passed me. The recruiting officer come for me. I’ve had my two and seven.
Augustus | Rising wrathfully. I shall not permit it. What do they mean by taking my office staff? Good God! they will be taking our hunt servants next. Confronting the Clerk. What did the man mean? What did he say?
The Clerk | He said that now you was on the job we’d want another million men, and he was going to take the old-age pensioners or anyone he could get.
Augustus | And did you dare to knock at my door and interrupt my business with this lady to repeat this man’s ineptitudes?
The Clerk | No. I come because the waiter from the hotel brought this paper. You left it on the coffee room breakfast table this morning.
The Lady | Intercepting it. It is the list. Good heavens!
The Clerk | Proffering the envelope. He says he thinks this is the envelope belonging to it.
The Lady | Snatching the envelope also. Yes! Addressed to you, Lord Augustus! Augustus comes back to the table to look at it. Oh, how imprudent! Everybody would guess its importance with your name on it. Fortunately I have some letters of my own here. Opening her wallet. Why not hide it in one of my envelopes? then no one will dream that the enclosure is of any political value. Taking out a letter, she crosses the room towards the window, whispering to Augustus as she passes him. Get rid of that man.
Augustus | Haughtily approaching the Clerk, who humorously makes a paralytic attempt to stand at attention. Have you any further business here, pray?
The Clerk | Am I to give the waiter anything; or will you do it yourself?
Augustus | Which waiter is it? The English one?
The Clerk | No: the one that calls hisself a Swiss. Shouldn’t wonder if he’d made a copy of that paper.
Augustus | Keep your impertinent surmises to yourself, sir. Remember that you are in the army now; and let me have no more of your civilian insubordination. Attention! Left turn! Quick march!
The Clerk | Stolidly. I dunno what you mean.
Augustus | Go to the guardroom and report yourself for disobeying orders. Now do you know what I mean?
The Clerk | Now look here. I ain’t going to argue with you—
Augustus | Nor I with you. Out with you.
He seizes the Clerk: and rushes him through the door. The moment the Lady is left alone, she snatches a sheet of official paper from the stationery rack: folds it so that it resembles the list; compares the two to see that they look exactly alike: whips the list into her wallet: and substitutes the facsimile for it. Then she listens for the return of Augustus. A crash is heard, as of the Clerk falling downstairs.
Augustus returns and is about to close the door when the voice of the Clerk is heard from below.
The Clerk | I’ll have the law of you for this, I will.
Augustus | Shouting down to him. There’s no more law for you, you scoundrel. You’re a soldier now. He shuts the door and comes to the Lady. Thank heaven, the war has given us the upper hand of these fellows at last. Excuse my violence; but discipline is absolutely necessary in dealing with the lower middle classes.
The Lady | Serve the insolent creature right! Look! I have found you a beautiful envelope for the list, an unmistakable lady’s envelope. She puts the sham list into her envelope and hands it to him.
Augustus | Excellent. Really very clever of you. Slyly. Come: would you like to have a peep at the list? Beginning to take the blank paper from the envelope.
The Lady | On the brink of detection. No no. Oh, please, no.
Augustus | Why? It won’t bite you. Drawing it out further.
The Lady | Snatching at his hand. Stop. Remember: if there should be an inquiry, you must be able to swear that you never showed that list to a mortal soul.
Augustus | Oh, that is a mere form. If you are really curious—
The Lady | I am not. I couldn’t bear to look at it. One of my dearest friends was blown to pieces by an aircraft gun; and since then I have never been able to think of one without horror.
Augustus | You mean it was a real gun, and actually went off. How sad! how sad! He pushes the sham list back into the envelope, and pockets it.
The Lady | Ah! Great sigh of relief. And now, Lord Augustus, I have taken up too much of your valuable time. Goodbye.
Augustus | What! Must you go?
The Lady | You are so busy.
Augustus | Yes; but not before lunch, you know. I never can do much before lunch. And I’m no good at all in the afternoon. From five to six is my real working time. Must you really go?
The Lady | I must, really. I have done my business very satisfactorily. Thank you ever so much. She proffers her hand.
Augustus | Shaking it affectionately as he leads her to the door, but first pressing the bell button with his left hand. Goodbye. Goodbye. So sorry to lose you. Kind of you to come; but there was no real danger. You see, my dear little lady, all this talk about war saving, and secrecy, and keeping the blinds down at night, and so forth, is all very well; but unless it’s carried out with intelligence, believe me, you may waste a pound to save a penny; you may let out all sorts of secrets to the enemy; you may guide the Zeppelins right on to your own chimneys. That’s where the ability of the governing class comes in. Shall the fellow call a taxi for you?
The Lady | No, thanks: I prefer walking. Goodbye. Again, many, many thanks.
She goes out. Augustus returns to the writing table smiling, and takes another look at himself in the mirror. The Clerk returns, with his head bandaged, carrying a poker.
The Clerk | What did you ring for? Augustus hastily drops the mirror. Don’t you come nigh me or I’ll split your head with this poker, thick as it is.
Augustus | It does not seem to me an exceptionally thick poker. I rang for you to show the lady out.
The Clerk | She’s gone. She run out like a rabbit. I ask myself why was she in such a hurry?
The Lady’s Voice | From the street. Lord Augustus. Lord Augustus.
The Clerk | She’s calling you.
Augustus | Running to the window and throwing it up. What is it? Won’t you come up?
The Lady | Is the clerk there?
Augustus | Yes. Do you want him?
The Lady | Yes.
Augustus | The lady wants you at the window.
The Clerk | Rushing to the window and putting down the poker. Yes, ma’am? Here I am, ma’am. What is it, ma’am?
The Lady | I want you to witness that I got clean away into the street. I am coming up now.
The two men stare at one another.
The Clerk | Wants me to witness that she got clean away into the street!
Augustus | What on earth does she mean?
The lady returns.
The Lady | May I use your telephone?
Augustus | Certainly. Certainly. Taking the receiver down. What number shall I get you?
The Lady | The War Office, please.
Augustus | The War Office!?
The Lady | If you will be so good.
Augustus | But—Oh, very well. Into the receiver. Hallo. This is the Town Hall Recruiting Office. Give me Colonel Bogey, sharp.
A pause.
The Clerk | Breaking the painful silence. I don’t think I’m awake. This is a dream of a movie picture, this is.
Augustus | His ear at the receiver. Shut up, will you? Into the telephone. What? … To the Lady. Whom do you want to get on to?
The Lady | Blueloo.
Augustus | Into the telephone. Put me through to Lord Hungerford Highcastle … I’m his brother, idiot … That you, Blueloo? Lady here at Little Pifflington wants to speak to you. Hold the line. To the Lady. Now, madam. He hands her the receiver.
The Lady | Sitting down in Augustus’s chair to speak into the telephone. Is that Blueloo? … Do you recognize my voice? … I’ve won our bet. …
Augustus | Your bet!
The Lady | Into the telephone. Yes: I have the list in my wallet. …
Augustus | Nothing of the kind, madam. I have it here in my pocket. He takes the envelope from his pocket: draws out the paper: and unfolds it.
The Lady | Continuing. Yes: I got clean into the street with it. I have a witness. I could have got to London with it. Augustus won’t deny it. …
Augustus | Contemplating the blank paper. There’s nothing written on this. Where is the list of guns?
The Lady | Continuing. Oh, it was quite easy. I said I was my sister-in-law and that I was a Hun. He lapped it up like a kitten. …
Augustus | You don’t mean to say that—
The Lady | Continuing. I got hold of the list for a moment and changed it for a piece of paper out of his stationery rack: it was quite easy. She laughs; and it is clear that Blueloo is laughing too.
Augustus | What!
The Clerk | Laughing slowly and laboriously, with intense enjoyment. Ha ha! Ha ha ha! Ha! Augustus rushes at him; he snatches up the poker and stands on guard. No you don’t.
The Lady | Still at the telephone, waving her disengaged hand behind her impatiently at them to stop making a noise. Sh‑sh‑sh‑sh‑sh!!! Augustus, with a shrug, goes up the middle of the room. The Lady resumes her conversation with the telephone. What? … Oh yes: I’m coming up by the 12.35: why not have tea with me at Rumpelmeister’s? … Rum-pel-meister’s. You know: they call it Robinson’s now … Right. Ta ta. She hangs up the receiver, and is passing round the table on her way towards the door when she is confronted by Augustus.
Augustus | Madam, I consider your conduct most unpatriotic. You make bets and abuse the confidence of the hardworked officials who are doing their bit for their country whilst our gallant fellows are perishing in the trenches—
The Lady | Oh, the gallant fellows are not all in the trenches, Augustus. Some of them have come home for a few days’ hard-earned leave; and I am sure you won’t grudge them a little fun at your expense.
The Clerk | Hear! hear!
Augustus | Amiably. Ah, well! For my country’s sake—!

Great Catherine

“In Catherine’s reign, whom Glory still adores”

Byron

The Author’s Apology for “Great Catherine”

Exception has been taken to the title of this seeming tomfoolery on the ground that the Catherine it represents is not Great Catherine, but the Catherine whose gallantries provide some of the lightest pages of modern history. Great Catherine, it is said, was the Catherine whose diplomacy, whose campaigns and conquests, whose plans of Liberal reform, whose correspondence with Grimm and Voltaire enabled her to cut such a magnificent figure in the eighteenth century. In reply, I can only confess that Catherine’s diplomacy and her conquests do not interest me. It is clear to me that neither she nor the statesmen with whom she played this mischievous kind of political chess had any notion of the real history of their own times, or of the real forces that were moulding Europe. The French Revolution, which made such short work of Catherine’s Voltairean principles, surprised and scandalized her as much as it surprised and scandalized any provincial governess in the French châteaux.

The main difference between her and our modern Liberal Governments was that whereas she talked and wrote quite intelligently about Liberal principles before she was frightened into making such talking and writing a flogging matter, our Liberal ministers take the name of Liberalism in vain without knowing or caring enough about its meaning even to talk and scribble about it, and pass their flogging Bills, and institute their prosecutions for sedition and blasphemy and so forth, without the faintest suspicion that such proceedings need any apology from the Liberal point of view.

It was quite easy for Patiomkin to humbug Catherine as to the condition of Russia by conducting her through sham cities run up for the occasion by scenic artists; but in the little world of European court intrigue and dynastic diplomacy which was the only world she knew she was more than a match for him and for all the rest of her contemporaries. In such intrigue and diplomacy, however, there was no romance, no scientific political interest, nothing that a sane mind can now retain even if it can be persuaded to waste time in reading it up. But Catherine as a woman with plenty of character and (as we should say) no morals, still fascinates and amuses us as she fascinated and amused her contemporaries. They were great sentimental comedians, these Peters, Elizabeths, and Catherines who played their Tsarships as eccentric character parts, and produced scene after scene of furious harlequinade with the monarch as clown, and of tragic relief in the torture chamber with the monarch as pantomime demon committing real atrocities, not forgetting the indispensable love interest on an enormous and utterly indecorous scale. Catherine kept this vast Guignol Theatre open for nearly half a century, not as a Russian, but as a highly domesticated German lady whose household routine was not at all so unlike that of Queen Victoria as might be expected from the difference in their notions of propriety in sexual relations.

In short, if Byron leaves you with an impression that he said very little about Catherine, and that little not what was best worth saying, I beg to correct your impression by assuring you that what Byron said was all there really is to say that is worth saying. His Catherine is my Catherine and everybody’s Catherine. The young man who gains her favor is a Spanish nobleman in his version. I have made him an English country gentleman, who gets out of his rather dangerous scrape by simplicity, sincerity, and the courage of these qualities. By this I have given some offence to the many Britons who see themselves as heroes: what they mean by heroes being theatrical snobs of superhuman pretensions which, though quite groundless, are admitted with awe by the rest of the human race. They say I think an Englishman a fool. When I do, they have themselves to thank.

I must not, however, pretend that historical portraiture was the motive of a play that will leave the reader as ignorant of Russian history as he may be now before he has turned the page. Nor is the sketch of Catherine complete even idiosyncratically, leaving her politics out of the question. For example, she wrote bushels of plays. I confess I have not yet read any of them. The truth is, this play grew out of the relations which inevitably exist in the theatre between authors and actors. If the actors have sometimes to use their skill as the author’s puppets rather than in full self-expression, the author has sometimes to use his skill as the actors’ tailor, fitting them with parts written to display the virtuosity of the performer rather than to solve problems of life, character, or history. Feats of this kind may tickle an author’s technical vanity; but he is bound on such occasions to admit that the performer for whom he writes is “the onlie begetter” of his work, which must be regarded critically as an addition to the debt dramatic literature owes to the art of acting and its exponents. Those who have seen Miss Gertrude Kingston play the part of Catherine will have no difficulty in believing that it was her talent rather than mine that brought the play into existence. I once recommended Miss Kingston professionally to play queens. Now in the modern drama there were no queens for her to play; and as to the older literature of our stage, did it not provoke the veteran actress in Sir Arthur Pinero’s Trelawny of the Wells to declare that, as parts, queens are not worth a tinker’s oath? Miss Kingston’s comment on my suggestion, though more elegantly worded, was to the same effect; and it ended in my having to make good my advice by writing “Great Catherine.” History provided no other queen capable of standing up to our joint talents.

In composing such bravura pieces, the author limits himself only by the range of the virtuoso, which by definition far transcends the modesty of nature. If my Russians seem more Muscovite than any Russian, and my English people more insular than any Briton, I will not plead, as I honestly might, that the fiction has yet to be written that can exaggerate the reality of such subjects; that the apparently outrageous Patiomkin is but a timidly bowdlerized ghost of the original; and that Captain Edstaston is no more than a miniature that might hang appropriately on the walls of nineteen out of twenty English country houses to this day. An artistic presentment must not condescend to justify itself by a comparison with crude nature; and I prefer to admit that in this kind my dramatis personae are, as they should be, of the stage stagey, challenging the actor to act up to them or beyond them, if he can. The more heroic the overcharging, the better for the performance.

In dragging the reader thus for a moment behind the scenes, I am departing from a rule which I have hitherto imposed on myself so rigidly that I never permit myself, even in a stage direction, to let slip a word that could bludgeon the imagination of the reader by reminding him of the boards and the footlights and the sky borders and the rest of the theatrical scaffolding, for which nevertheless I have to plan as carefully as if I were the head carpenter as well as the author. But even at the risk of talking shop, an honest playwright should take at least one opportunity of acknowledging that his art is not only limited by the art of the actor, but often stimulated and developed by it. No sane and skilled author writes plays that present impossibilities to the actor or to the stage engineer. If, as occasionally happens, he asks them to do things that they have never done before and cannot conceive as presentable or possible (as Wagner and Thomas Hardy have done, for example), it is always found that the difficulties are not really insuperable, the author having foreseen unsuspected possibilities both in the actor and in the audience, whose will-to-make-believe can perform the quaintest miracles. Thus may authors advance the arts of acting and of staging plays. But the actor also may enlarge the scope of the drama by displaying powers not previously discovered by the author. If the best available actors are only Horatios, the authors will have to leave Hamlet out, and be content with Horatios for heroes. Some of the difference between Shakespeare’s Orlandos and Bassanios and Bertrams and his Hamlets and Macbeths must have been due not only to his development as a dramatic poet, but to the development of Burbage as an actor. Playwrights do not write for ideal actors when their livelihood is at stake: if they did, they would write parts for heroes with twenty arms like an Indian god. Indeed the actor often influences the author too much; for I can remember a time (I am not implying that it is yet wholly past) when the art of writing a fashionable play had become very largely the art of writing it “round” the personalities of a group of fashionable performers of whom Burbage would certainly have said that their parts needed no acting. Everything has its abuse as well as its use.

It is also to be considered that great plays live longer than great actors, though little plays do not live nearly so long as the worst of their exponents. The consequence is that the great actor, instead of putting pressure on contemporary authors to supply him with heroic parts, falls back on the Shakespearean repertory, and takes what he needs from a dead hand. In the nineteenth century, the careers of Kean, Macready, Barry Sullivan, and Irving, ought to have produced a group of heroic plays comparable in intensity to those of Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripides; but nothing of the kind happened: these actors played the works of dead authors, or, very occasionally, of live poets who were hardly regular professional playwrights. Sheridan Knowles, Bulwer Lytton, Wills, and Tennyson produced a few glaringly artificial high horses for the great actors of their time; but the playwrights proper, who really kept the theatre going, and were kept going by the theatre, did not cater for the great actors: they could not afford to compete with a bard who was not for an age but for all time, and who had, moreover, the overwhelming attraction for the actor-managers of not charging author’s fees. The result was that the playwrights and the great actors ceased to think of themselves as having any concern with one another: Tom Robertson, Ibsen, Pinero, and Barrie might as well have belonged to a different solar system as far as Irving was concerned; and the same was true of their respective predecessors.

Thus was established an evil tradition; but I at least can plead that it does not always hold good. If Forbes Robertson had not been there to play Caesar, I should not have written Caesar and Cleopatra. If Ellen Terry had never been born, Captain Brassbound’s Conversion would never have been effected. The Devil’s Disciple, with which I won my cordon bleu in America as a potboiler, would have had a different sort of hero if Richard Mansfield had been a different sort of actor, though the actual commission to write it came from an English actor, William Terriss, who was assassinated before he recovered from the dismay into which the result of his rash proposal threw him. For it must be said that the actor or actress who inspires or commissions a play as often as not regards it as a Frankenstein’s monster, and will have none of it. That does not make him or her any the less parental in the fecundity of the playwright.

To an author who has any feeling of his business there is a keen and whimsical joy in divining and revealing a side of an actor’s genius overlooked before, and unsuspected even by the actor himself. When I snatched Mr. Louis Calvert from Shakespeare, and made him wear a frock coat and silk hat on the stage for perhaps the first time in his life, I do not think he expected in the least that his performance would enable me to boast of his Tom Broadbent as a genuine stage classic. Mrs. Patrick Campbell was famous before I wrote for her, but not for playing illiterate cockney flower-maidens. And in the case which is provoking me to all these impertinences, I am quite sure that Miss Gertrude Kingston, who first made her reputation as an impersonator of the most delightfully feather-headed and inconsequent ingenues, thought me more than usually mad when I persuaded her to play the Helen of Euripides, and then launched her on a queenly career as Catherine of Russia.

It is not the whole truth that if we take care of the actors the plays will take care of themselves; nor is it any truer that if we take care of the plays the actors will take care of themselves. There is both give and take in the business. I have seen plays written for actors that made me exclaim, “How oft the sight of means to do ill deeds makes deeds ill done!” But Burbage may have flourished the prompt copy of Hamlet under Shakespeare’s nose at the tenth rehearsal and cried, “How oft the sight of means to do great deeds makes playwrights great!” I say the tenth because I am convinced that at the first he denounced his part as a rotten one; thought the ghost’s speech ridiculously long; and wanted to play the king. Anyhow, whether he had the wit to utter it or not, the boast would have been a valid one. The best conclusion is that every actor should say, “If I create the hero in myself, God will send an author to write his part.” For in the long run the actors will get the authors, and the authors the actors, they deserve.

“Great Catherine” was performed for the first time at the Vaudeville Theatre in London on the 18th November 1913, with Gertrude Kingston as Catherine, Miriam Lewes as Varinka, Dorothy Massingham as Claire, Norman McKinnell as Patiomkin, Edmond Breon as Edstaston, Annie Hill as the Princess Dashkoff, and Eugene Mayeur and F. Cooke Beresford as Naryshkin and the Sergeant.

Dramatis Personae

Character, a character

Scene: A scene.

The First Scene

1776. Patiomkin in his bureau in the Winter Palace, St. Petersburg. Huge palatial apartment: style, Russia in the eighteenth century imitating the Versailles du Roi Soleil. Extravagant luxury. Also dirt and disorder.

Patiomkin, gigantic in stature and build, his face marred by the loss of one eye and a marked squint in the other, sits at the end of a table littered with papers and the remains of three or four successive breakfasts. He has supplies of coffee and brandy at hand sufficient for a party of ten. His coat, encrusted with diamonds, is on the floor. It has fallen off a chair placed near the other end of the table for the convenience of visitors. His court sword, with its attachments, is on the chair. His three-cornered hat, also bejewelled, is on the table. He himself is half dressed in an unfastened shirt and an immense dressing gown, once gorgeous, now food-splashed and dirty, as it serves him for towel, handkerchief, duster, and every other use to which a textile fabric can be put by a slovenly man. It does not conceal his huge hairy chest, nor his half-buttoned knee breeches, nor his legs. These are partly clad in silk stockings, which he occasionally hitches up to his knees, and presently shakes down to his shins, by his restless movement. His feet are thrust into enormous slippers, worth, with their crust of jewels, several thousand roubles apiece.

Superficially Patiomkin is a violent, brutal barbarian, an upstart despot of the most intolerable and dangerous type, ugly, lazy, and disgusting in his personal habits. Yet ambassadors report him the ablest man in Russia, and the one who can do most with the still abler Empress Catherine II, who is not a Russian but a German, by no means barbarous or intemperate in her personal habits. She not only disputes with Frederick the Great the reputation of being the cleverest monarch in Europe, but may even put in a very plausible claim to be the cleverest and most attractive individual alive. Now she not only tolerates Patiomkin long after she has got over her first romantic attachment to him, but esteems him highly as a counsellor and a good friend. His love letters are among the best on record. He has a wild sense of humor, which enables him to laugh at himself as well as at everybody else. In the eyes of the English visitor now about to be admitted to his presence he may be an outrageous ruffian. In fact he actually is an outrageous ruffian, in no matter whose eyes; but the visitor will find out, as everyone else sooner or later fends out, that he is a man to be reckoned with even by those who are not intimidated by his temper, bodily strength, and exalted rank.

A pretty young lady, Varinka, his favorite niece, is lounging on an ottoman between his end of the table and the door, very sulky and dissatisfied, perhaps because he is preoccupied with his papers and his brandy bottle, and she can see nothing of him but his broad back.

There is a screen behind the ottoman.

An old soldier, a Cossack sergeant, enters.

The Sergeant | Softly to the lady, holding the door handle. Little darling honey: is his Highness the prince very busy?
Varinka | His Highness the prince is very busy. He is singing out of tune; he is biting his nails; he is scratching his head; he is hitching up his untidy stockings; he is making himself disgusting and odious to everybody; and he is pretending to read state papers that he does not understand because he is too lazy and selfish to talk and be companionable.
Patiomkin | Growls; then wipes his nose with his dressing gown.!!
Varinka | Pig. Ugh! She curls herself up with a shiver of disgust and retires from the conversation.
The Sergeant | Stealing across to the coat, and picking it up to replace it on the back of the chair. Little Father, the English captain, so highly recommended to you by old Fritz of Prussia, by the English ambassador, and by Monsieur Voltaire (whom crossing himself may God in his infinite mercy damn eternally!), is in the antechamber and desires audience.
Patiomkin | Deliberately. To hell with the English captain; and to hell with old Fritz of Prussia; and to hell with the English ambassador; and to hell with Monsieur Voltaire; and to hell with you too!
The Sergeant | Have mercy on me, Little Father. Your head is bad this morning. You drink too much French brandy and too little good Russian kvass.
Patiomkin | With sudden fury. Why are visitors of consequence announced by a sergeant? Springing at him and seizing him by the throat. What do you mean by this, you hound? Do you want five thousand blows of the stick? Where is General Volkonsky?
The Sergeant | On his knees. Little Father, you kicked his Highness downstairs.
Patiomkin | Flinging him down and kicking him. You lie, you dog. You lie.
The Sergeant | Little Father: life is hard for the poor. If you say it is a lie, it is a lie. He fell downstairs. I picked him up; and he kicked me. They all kick me when you kick them. God knows that is not just, Little Father!
Patiomkin | Laughs ogreishly; then returns to his place at the table, chuckling.!!!
Varinka | Savage! Boor! It is a disgrace. No wonder the French sneer at us as barbarians.
The Sergeant | Who has crept round the table to the screen, and insinuated himself between Patiomkin’s back and Varinka. Do you think the Prince will see the Captain, little darling?
Patiomkin | He will not see any captain. Go to the devil!
The Sergeant | Be merciful, Little Father. God knows it is your duty to see him! To Varinka. Intercede for him and for me, beautiful little darling. He has given me a rouble.
Patiomkin | Oh, send him in, send him in; and stop pestering me. Am I never to have a moment’s peace?
The Sergeant salutes joyfully and hurries out, divining that Patiomkin has intended to see the English captain all along, and has played this comedy of fury and exhausted impatience to conceal his interest in the visitor.
Varinka | Have you no shame? You refuse to see the most exalted persons. You kick princes and generals downstairs. And then you see an English captain merely because he has given a rouble to that common soldier. It is scandalous.
Patiomkin | Darling beloved, I am drunk; but I know what I am doing. I wish to stand well with the English.
Varinka | And you think you will impress an Englishman by receiving him as you are now, half drunk?
Patiomkin | Gravely. It is true: the English despise men who cannot drink. I must make myself wholly drunk. He takes a huge draught of brandy.
Varinka | Sot!
The Sergeant returns ushering a handsome strongly built young English officer in the uniform of a Light Dragoon. He is evidently on fairly good terms with himself, and very sure of his social position. He crosses the room to the end of the table opposite Patiomkin’s, and awaits the civilities of that statesman with confidence. The Sergeant remains prudently at the door.
The Sergeant | Paternally. Little Father: this is the English captain, so well recommended to her sacred Majesty the Empress. God knows, he needs your countenance and protec—He vanishes precipitately, seeing that Patiomkin is about to throw a bottle at him. The Captain contemplates these preliminaries with astonishment, and with some displeasure, which is not allayed when Patiomkin, hardly condescending to look at his visitor, of whom he nevertheless takes stock with the corner of his one eye, says gruffly. Well?
Edstaston | My name is Edstaston: Captain Edstaston of the Light Dragoons. I have the honor to present to your Highness this letter from the British ambassador, which will give you all necessary particulars. He hands Patiomkin the letter.
Patiomkin | Tearing it open and glancing at it for about a second. What do you want?
Edstaston | The letter will explain to your Highness who I am.
Patiomkin | I don’t want to know who you are. What do you want?
Edstaston | An audience of the Empress. Patiomkin contemptuously throws the letter aside. Edstaston adds hotly. Also some civility, if you please.
Patiomkin | With derision. Ho!
Varinka | My uncle is receiving you with unusual civility, Captain. He has just kicked a general downstairs.
Edstaston | A Russian general, madam?
Varinka | Of course.
Edstaston | I must allow myself to say, madam, that your uncle had better not attempt to kick an English officer downstairs.
Patiomkin | You want me to kick you upstairs: eh? You want an audience of the Empress.
Edstaston | I have said nothing about kicking, sir. If it comes to that, my boots shall speak for me. Her Majesty has signified a desire to have news of the rebellion in America. I have served against the rebels; and I am instructed to place myself at the disposal of her Majesty, and to describe the events of the war to her as an eyewitness, in a discreet and agreeable manner.
Patiomkin | Psha! I know. You think if she once sets eyes on your face and your uniform your fortune is made. You think that if she could stand a man like me, with only one eye, and a cross eye at that, she must fall down at your feet at first sight, eh?
Edstaston | Shocked and indignant. I think nothing of the sort; and I’ll trouble you not to repeat it. If I were a Russian subject and you made such a boast about my queen, I’d strike you across the face with my sword. Patiomkin, with a yell of fury, rushes at him. Hands off, you swine! As Patiomkin, towering over him, attempts to seize him by the throat, Edstaston, who is a bit of a wrestler, adroitly backheels him. He falls, amazed, on his back.
Varinka | Rushing out. Help! Call the guard! The Englishman is murdering my uncle! Help! Help!
The Guard and the Sergeant rush in. Edstaston draws a pair of small pistols from his boots, and points one at the Sergeant and the other at Patiomkin, who is sitting on the floor, somewhat sobered. The soldiers stand irresolute.
Edstaston | Stand off. To Patiomkin. Order them off, if you don’t want a bullet through your silly head.
The Sergeant | Little Father: tell us what to do. Our lives are yours; but God knows you are not fit to die.
Patiomkin | Absurdly self-possessed. Get out.
The Sergeant | Little Father—
Patiomkin | Roaring. Get out. Get out, all of you. They withdraw, much relieved at their escape from the pistol. Patiomkin attempts to rise, and rolls over. Here! help me up, will you? Don’t you see that I’m drunk and can’t get up?
Edstaston | Suspiciously. You want to get hold of me.
Patiomkin | Squatting resignedly against the chair on which his clothes hang. Very well, then: I shall stay where I am, because I’m drunk and you’re afraid of me.
Edstaston | I’m not afraid of you, damn you!
Patiomkin | Ecstatically. Darling: your lips are the gates of truth. Now listen to me. He marks off the items of his statement with ridiculous stiff gestures of his head and arms, imitating a puppet. You are Captain Whatshisname; and your uncle is the Earl of Whatdyecallum; and your father is Bishop of Thingummybob; and you are a young man of the highest spr—promise (I told you I was drunk), educated at Cambridge, and got your step as captain in the field at the glorious battle of Bunker’s Hill. Invalided home from America at the request of Aunt Fanny, Lady-in-Waiting to the Queen. All right, eh?
Edstaston | How do you know all this?
Patiomkin | Crowing fantastically. In er lerrer, darling, darling, darling, darling. Lerrer you showed me.
Edstaston | But you didn’t read it.
Patiomkin | Flapping his fingers at him grotesquely. Only one eye, darling. Cross eye. Sees everything. Read lerrer ince—ince—istastaneously. Kindly give me vinegar borle. Green borle. On’y to sober me. Too drunk to speak proply. If you would be so kind, darling. Green borle. Edstaston, still suspicious, shakes his head and keeps his pistols ready. Reach it myself. He reaches behind him up to the table, and snatches at the green bottle, from which he takes a copious draught. Its effect is appalling. His wry faces and agonized belchings are so heartrending that they almost upset Edstaston. When the victim at last staggers to his feet, he is a pale fragile nobleman, aged and quite sober, extremely dignified in manner and address, though shaken by his recent convulsions. Young man: it is not better to be drunk than sober; but it is happier. Goodness is not happiness. That is an epigram. But I have overdone this. I am too sober to be good company. Let me redress the balance. He takes a generous draught of brandy, and recovers his geniality. Aha! That’s better. And now listen, darling. You must not come to Court with pistols in your boots.
Edstaston | I have found them useful.
Patiomkin | Nonsense. I’m your friend. You mistook my intention because I was drunk. Now that I am sober—in moderation—I will prove that I am your friend. Have some diamonds. Roaring. Hullo there! Dogs, pigs: hullo!
The Sergeant comes in.
The Sergeant | God be praised, Little Father: you are still spared to us.
Patiomkin | Tell them to bring some diamonds. Plenty of diamonds. And rubies. Get out. He aims a kick at the Sergeant, who flees. Put up your pistols, darling. I’ll give you a pair with gold handgrips. I am your friend.
Edstaston | Replacing the pistols in his boots rather unwillingly. Your Highness understands that if I am missing, or if anything happens to me, there will be trouble.
Patiomkin | Enthusiastically. Call me darling.
Edstaston | It is not the English custom.
Patiomkin | You have no hearts, you English! Slapping his right breast. Heart! Heart!
Edstaston | Pardon, your Highness: your heart is on the other side.
Patiomkin | Surprised and impressed. Is it? You are learned! You are a doctor! You English are wonderful! We are barbarians, drunken pigs. Catherine does not know it; but we are. Catherine’s a German. But I have given her a Russian heart. He is about to slap himself again.
Edstaston | Delicately. The other side, your Highness.
Patiomkin | Maudlin. Darling: a true Russian has a heart on both sides.
The Sergeant enters carrying a goblet filled with precious stones.
Patiomkin | Get out. He snatches the goblet and kicks the Sergeant out, not maliciously but from habit, indeed not noticing that he does it. Darling: have some diamonds. Have a fistful. He takes up a handful and lets them slip back through his fingers into the goblet, which he then offers to Edstaston.
Edstaston | Thank you: I don’t take presents.
Patiomkin | Amazed. You refuse!
Edstaston | I thank your Highness; but it is not the custom for English gentlemen to take presents of that kind.
Patiomkin | Are you really an Englishman?
Edstaston | Bows.!
Patiomkin | You are the first Englishman I ever saw refuse anything he could get. He puts the goblet on the table; then turns again to Edstaston. Listen, darling. You are a wrestler: a splendid wrestler. You threw me on my back like magic, though I could lift you with one hand. Darling: you are a giant, a paladin.
Edstaston | Complacently. We wrestle rather well in my part of England.
Patiomkin | I have a Turk who is a wrestler: a prisoner of war. You shall wrestle with him for me. I’ll stake a million roubles on you.
Edstaston | Incensed. Damn you! do you take me for a prizefighter? How dare you make me such a proposal?
Patiomkin | With wounded feeling. Darling: there is no pleasing you. Don’t you like me?
Edstaston | Mollified. Well, in a sort of way I do; though I don’t know why I should. But my instructions are that I am to see the Empress; and—
Patiomkin | Darling: you shall see the Empress. A glorious woman, the greatest woman in the world. But lemme give you piece ‘vice—pah! still drunk. They water my vinegar. He shakes himself; clears his throat; and resumes soberly. If Catherine takes a fancy to you, you may ask for roubles, diamonds, palaces, titles, orders, anything! and you may aspire to everything: field-marshal, admiral, minister, what you please—except Tsar.
Edstaston | I tell you I don’t want to ask for anything. Do you suppose I am an adventurer and a beggar?
Patiomkin | Plaintively. Why not, darling? I was an adventurer. I was a beggar.
Edstaston | Oh, you!
Patiomkin | Well: what’s wrong with me?
Edstaston | You are a Russian. That’s different.
Patiomkin | Effusively. Darling: I am a man; and you are a man; and Catherine is a woman. Woman reduces us all to the common denominator. Chuckling. Again an epigram! Gravely. You understand it, I hope. Have you had a college education, darling? I have.
Edstaston | Certainly. I am a Bachelor of Arts.
Patiomkin | It is enough that you are a bachelor, darling: Catherine will supply the arts. Aha! Another epigram! I am in the vein today.
Edstaston | Embarrassed and a little offended. I must ask your Highness to change the subject. As a visitor in Russia, I am the guest of the Empress; and I must tell you plainly that I have neither the right nor the disposition to speak lightly of her Majesty.
Patiomkin | You have conscientious scruples?
Edstaston | I have the scruples of a gentleman.
Patiomkin | In Russia a gentleman has no scruples. In Russia we face facts.
Edstaston | In England, sir, a gentleman never faces any facts if they are unpleasant facts.
Patiomkin | In real life, darling, all facts are unpleasant. Greatly pleased with himself. Another epigram! Where is my accursed chancellor? these gems should be written down and recorded for posterity. He rushes to the table; sits down; and snatches up a pen. Then, recollecting himself. But I have not asked you to sit down. He rises and goes to the other chair. I am a savage: a barbarian. He throws the shirt and coat over the table on to the floor and puts his sword on the table. Be seated, Captain.
Edstaston | Thank you.
They bow to one another ceremoniously. Patiomkin’s tendency to grotesque exaggeration costs him his balance; he nearly falls over Edstaston, who rescues him and takes the proffered chair.
Patiomkin | Resuming his seat. By the way, what was the piece of advice I was going to give you?
Edstaston | As you did not give it, I don’t know. Allow me to add that I have not asked for your advice.
Patiomkin | I give it to you unasked, delightful Englishman. I remember it now. It was this. Don’t try to become Tsar of Russia.
Edstaston | In astonishment. I haven’t the slightest intention—
Patiomkin | Not now; but you will have: take my word for it. It will strike you as a splendid idea to have conscientious scruples—to desire the blessing of the Church on your union with Catherine.
Edstaston | Racing in utter amazement. My union with Catherine! You’re mad.
Patiomkin | Unmoved. The day you hint at such a thing will be the day of your downfall. Besides, it is not lucky to be Catherine’s husband. You know what happened to Peter?
Edstaston | Shortly: sitting down again. I do not wish to discuss it.
Patiomkin | You think she murdered him?
Edstaston | I know that people have said so.
Patiomkin | Thunderously; springing to his feet. It is a lie: Orloff murdered him. Subsiding a little. He also knocked my eye out; but sitting down placidly I succeeded him for all that. And patting Edstaston’s hand very affectionately I’m sorry to say, darling, that if you become Tsar, I shall murder you.
Edstaston | Ironically returning the caress. Thank you. The occasion will not arise. Rising. I have the honor to wish your Highness good morning.
Patiomkin | Jumping up and stopping him on his way to the door. Tut tut! I’m going to take you to the Empress now, this very instant.
Edstaston | In these boots? Impossible! I must change.
Patiomkin | Nonsense! You shall come just as you are. You shall show her your calves later on.
Edstaston | But it will take me only half an hour to—
Patiomkin | In half an hour it will be too late for the petit lever. Come along. Damn it, man, I must oblige the British ambassador, and the French ambassador, and old Fritz, and Monsieur Voltaire and the rest of them. He shouts rudely to the door. Varinka! To Edstaston, with tears in his voice. Varinka shall persuade you: nobody can refuse Varinka anything. My niece. A treasure, I assure you. Beautiful! devoted! fascinating! Shouting again. Varinka: where the devil are you?
Varinka | Returning. I’ll not be shouted for. You have the voice of a bear, and the manners of a tinker.
Patiomkin | Tsh‑sh‑sh. Little angel Mother: you must behave yourself before the English captain. He takes off his dressing gown and throws it over the papers and the breakfasts; picks up his coat; and disappears behind the screen to complete his toilette.
Edstaston | Madam! He bows.
Varinka | Courtseying. Monsieur le Capitaine!
Edstaston | I must apologize for the disturbance I made, madam.
Patiomkin | Behind the screen. You must not call her madam. You must call her Little Mother, and beautiful darling.
Edstaston | My respect for the lady will not permit it.
Varinka | Respect! How can you respect the niece of a savage?
Edstaston | Deprecating. Oh, madam!
Varinka | Heaven is my witness, Little English Father, we need someone who is not afraid of him. He is so strong! I hope you will throw him down on the floor many, many, many times.
Patiomkin | Behind the screen. Varinka!
Varinka | Yes?
Patiomkin | Go and look through the keyhole of the Imperial bedchamber; and bring me word whether the Empress is awake yet.
Varinka | Fi donc! I do not look through keyholes.
Patiomkin | Emerging, having arranged his shirt and put on his diamonded coat. You have been badly brought up, little darling. Would any lady or gentleman walk unannounced into a room without first looking through the keyhole? Taking his sword from the table and putting it on. The great thing in life is to be simple; and the perfectly simple thing is to look through keyholes. Another epigram: the fifth this morning! Where is my fool of a chancellor? Where is Popof?
Edstaston | Choking with suppressed laughter.!!!!
Patiomkin | Gratified. Darling, you appreciate my epigram.
Edstaston | Excuse me. Pop off! Ha! ha! I can’t help laughing. What’s his real name, by the way, in case I meet him?
Varinka | Surprised. His real name? Popof, of course. Why do you laugh, Little Father?
Edstaston | How can anyone with a sense of humor help laughing? Pop off! He is convulsed.
Varinka | Looking at her uncle, taps her forehead significantly.!!
Patiomkin | Aside to Varinka. No: only English. He will amuse Catherine. To Edstaston. Come, you shall tell the joke to the Empress: she is by way of being a humorist. He takes him by the arm, and leads him towards the door.
Edstaston | Resisting. No, really. I am not fit—
Patiomkin | Persuade him, Little angel Mother.
Varinka | Taking his other arm. Yes, yes, yes. Little English Father: God knows it is your duty to be brave and wait on the Empress. Come.
Edstaston | No. I had rather—
Patiomkin | Hauling him along. Come.
Varinka | Pulling him and coaxing him. Come, little love: you can’t refuse me.
Edstaston | But how can I?
Patiomkin | Why not? She won’t eat you.
Varinka | She will; but you must come.
Edstaston | I assure you—it is quite out of the question—my clothes—
Varinka | You look perfect.
Patiomkin | Come along, darling.
Edstaston | Struggling. Impossible—
Varinka | Come, come, come.
Edstaston | No. Believe me—I don’t wish—I—
Varinka | Carry him, uncle.
Patiomkin | Lifting him in his arms like a father carrying a little boy. Yes: I’ll carry you.
Edstaston | Dash it all, this is ridiculous!
Varinka | Seizing his ankles and dancing as he is carried out. You must come. If you kick you will blacken my eyes.
Patiomkin | Come, baby, come.
By this time they have made their way through the door and are out of hearing.

The Second Scene

The Empress’s petit lever. The central doors are closed. Those who enter through them find on their left, on a dais of two broad steps, a magnificent curtained bed. Beyond it a door in the panelling leads to the Empress’s cabinet. Near the foot of the bed, in the middle of the room, stands a gilt chair, with the Imperial arms carved and the Imperial monogram embroidered.

The Court is in attendance, standing in two melancholy rows down the side of the room opposite to the bed, solemn, bored, waiting for the Empress to awaken. The Princess Dashkoff, with two ladies, stands a little in front of the line of courtiers, by the Imperial chair. Silence, broken only by the yawns and whispers of the courtiers. Naryshkin, the Chamberlain, stands by the head of the bed.

A loud yawn is heard from behind the curtains.

Naryshkin | Holding up a warning hand. Ssh!
The courtiers hastily cease whispering; dress up their lines; and stiffen. Dead silence. A bell tinkles within the curtains. Naryshkin and the Princess solemnly draw them and reveal the Empress.
Catherine turns over on her back, and stretches herself.
Catherine | Yawning. Heigho—ah—yah—ah—ow—what o’clock is it? Her accent is German.
Naryshkin | Formally. Her Imperial Majesty is awake. The Court falls on its knees.
All | Good morning to your Majesty.
Naryshkin | Half-past ten, Little Mother.
Catherine | Sitting up abruptly. Potztausend! Contemplating the kneeling courtiers. Oh, get up, get up. All rise. Your etiquette bores me. I am hardly awake in the morning before it begins. Yawning again, and relapsing sleepily against her pillows. Why do they do it, Naryshkin?
Naryshkin | God knows it is not for your sake, Little Mother. But you see if you were not a great queen they would all be nobodies.
Catherine | Sitting up. They make me do it to keep up their own little dignities? So?
Naryshkin | Exactly. Also because if they didn’t you might have them flogged, dear Little Mother.
Catherine | Springing energetically out of bed and seating herself on the edge of it. Flogged! I! A Liberal Empress! A philosopher! You are a barbarian, Naryshkin. She rises and turns to the courtiers. And then, as if I cared! She turns again to Naryshkin. You should know by this time that I am frank and original in character, like an Englishman. She walks about restlessly. No: what maddens me about all this ceremony is that I am the only person in Russia who gets no fun out of my being Empress. You all glory in me: you bask in my smiles: you get titles and honors and favors from me: you are dazzled by my crown and my robes: you feel splendid when you have been admitted to my presence; and when I say a gracious word to you, you talk about it to everyone you meet for a week afterwards. But what do I get out of it? Nothing. She throws herself into the chair. Naryshkin deprecates with a gesture: she hurls an emphatic repetition at him. Nothing!! I wear a crown until my neck aches: I stand looking majestic until I am ready to drop: I have to smile at ugly old ambassadors and frown and turn my back on young and handsome ones. Nobody gives me anything. When I was only an Archduchess, the English ambassador used to give me money whenever I wanted it—or rather whenever he wanted to get anything out of my sacred predecessor Elizabeth the Court bows to the ground; but now that I am Empress he never gives me a kopek. When I have headaches and colics I envy the scullerymaids. And you are not a bit grateful to me for all my care of you, my work, my thought, my fatigue, my sufferings.
The Princess Dashkoff | God knows, Little Mother, we all implore you to give your wonderful brain a rest. That is why you get headaches. Monsieur Voltaire also has headaches. His brain is just like yours.
Catherine | Dashkoff: what a liar you are! Dashkoff curtsies with impressive dignity. And you think you are flattering me! Let me tell you I would not give a rouble to have the brains of all the philosophers in France. What is our business for today?
Naryshkin | The new museum, Little Mother. But the model will not be ready until tonight.
Catherine | Rising eagerly. Yes: the museum. An enlightened capital should have a museum. She paces the chamber with a deep sense of the importance of the museum. It shall be one of the wonders of the world. I must have specimens: specimens, specimens, specimens.
Naryshkin | You are in high spirits this morning, Little Mother.
Catherine | With sudden levity. I am always in high spirits, even when people do not bring me my slippers. She runs to the chair and sits down, thrusting her feet out.
The two ladies rush to her feet, each carrying a slipper. Catherine, about to put her feet into them, is checked by a disturbance in the antechamber.
Patiomkin |

Carrying Edstaston through the antechamber. Useless to struggle. Come along, beautiful baby darling. Come to Little Mother. He sings.

March him baby,
Baby, baby,
Lit‑tle ba‑by bumpkins.

Varinka | Joining in to the same doggerel in canon, a third above. March him, baby, etc., etc.
Edstaston | Trying to make himself heard. No, no. This is carrying a joke too far. I must insist. Let me down! Hang it, will you let me down! Confound it! No, no. Stop playing the fool, will you? We don’t understand this sort of thing in England. I shall be disgraced. Let me down.
Catherine | Meanwhile. What a horrible noise! Naryshkin, see what it is.
Naryshkin goes to the door.
Catherine | Listening. That is Prince Patiomkin.
Naryshkin | Calling from the door. Little Mother, a stranger.
Catherine plunges into bed again and covers herself up. Patiomkin, followed by Varinka, carries Edstaston in; dumps him down on the foot of the bed; and staggers past it to the cabinet door. Varinka joins the courtiers at the opposite side of the room. Catherine, blazing with wrath, pushes Edstaston off her bed on to the floor; gets out of bed; and turns on Patiomkin with so terrible an expression that all kneel down hastily except Edstaston, who is sprawling on the carpet in angry confusion.
Catherine | Patiomkin: how dare you? Looking at Edstaston. What is this?
Patiomkin | On his knees: tearfully. I don’t know. I am drunk. What is this, Varinka?
Edstaston | Scrambling to his feet. Madam: this drunken ruffian—
Patiomkin | Thas true. Drung’n ruffian. Took ’dvantage of my being drunk. Said: take me to Lil’ angel Mother. Take me to beauf’l Empress. Take me to the grea’st woman on earth. Thas whas he he said. I took him. I was wrong. I am not sober.
Catherine | Men have grown sober in Siberia for less, Prince.
Patiomkin | Serve ’em right! ’Sgusting habit. Ask Varinka.
Catherine turns her face from him to the Court. The courtiers see that she is trying not to laugh, and know by experience that she will not succeed. They rise, relieved and grinning.
Varinka | It is true. He drinks like a pig.
Patiomkin | Plaintively. No: not like pig. Like prince. Lil’ Mother made poor Patiomkin prince. Whas use being prince if I mayn’t drink?
Catherine | Biting her lips. Go. I am offended.
Patiomkin | Don’t scold, Lil’ Mother.
Catherine | Imperiously. Go.
Patiomkin | Rising unsteadily. Yes: go. Go bye bye. Very sleepy. Berr go bye bye than go Siberia. Go bye bye in Lil’ Mother’s bed. He pretends to make an attempt to get into the bed.
Catherine | Energetically pulling him back. No, no! Patiomkin! What are you thinking of? He falls like a log on the floor, apparently dead drunk.
The Princess Dashkoff | Scandalous! An insult to your Imperial Majesty!
Catherine | Dashkoff: you have no sense of humor. She steps down to the door level and looks indulgently at Patiomkin. He gurgles brutishly. She has an impulse of disgust. Hog. She kicks him as hard as she can. Oh! You have broken my toe. Brute. Beast. Dashkoff is quite right. Do you hear?
Patiomkin | If you ask my pi-pinion of Dashkoff, my pipinion is that Dashkoff is drunk. Scan’lous. Poor Patiomkin go bye bye. He relapses into drunken slumbers.
Some of the courtiers move to carry him away.
Catherine | Stopping them. Let him lie. Let him sleep it off. If he goes out it will be to a tavern and low company for the rest of the day. Indulgently. There! She takes a pillow from the bed and puts it under his head; then turns to Edstaston; surveys him with perfect dignity; and asks, in her queenliest manner. Varinka, who is this gentleman?
Varinka | A foreign captain: I cannot pronounce his name. I think he is mad. He came to the Prince and said he must see your Majesty. He can talk of nothing else. We could not prevent him.
Edstaston | Overwhelmed by this apparent betrayal. Oh! Madam: I am perfectly sane: I am actually an Englishman. I should never have dreamt of approaching your Majesty without the fullest credentials. I have letters from the English ambassador, from the Prussian ambassador. Naively. But everybody assured me that Prince Patiomkin is all-powerful with your Majesty; so I naturally applied to him.
Patiomkin | Interrupts the conversation by an agonized wheezing groan as of a donkey beginning to bray.!!!
Catherine | Like a fishfag. Schweig, du Hund. Resuming her impressive royal manner. Have you never been taught, sir, how a gentleman should enter the presence of a sovereign?
Edstaston | Yes, Madam; but I did not enter your presence: I was carried.
Catherine | But you say you asked the Prince to carry you.
Edstaston | Certainly not, Madam. I protested against it with all my might. I appeal to this lady to confirm me.
Varinka | Pretending to be indignant. Yes, you protested. But, all the same, you were very very very anxious to see her Imperial Majesty. You blushed when the Prince spoke of her. You threatened to strike him across the face with your sword because you thought he did not speak enthusiastically enough of her. To Catherine. Trust me: he has seen your Imperial Majesty before.
Catherine | To Edstaston. You have seen us before?
Edstaston | At the review, Madam.
Varinka | Triumphantly. Aha! I knew it. Your Majesty wore the hussar uniform. He saw how radiant! how splendid! your Majesty looked. Oh! he has dared to admire your Majesty. Such insolence is not to be endured.
Edstaston | All Europe is a party to that insolence, Madam.
The Princess Dashkoff | All Europe is content to do so at a respectful distance. It is possible to admire her Majesty’s policy and her eminence in literature and philosophy without performing acrobatic feats in the Imperial bed.
Edstaston | I know nothing about her Majesty’s eminence in policy or philosophy: I don’t pretend to understand such things. I speak as a practical man. And I never knew that foreigners had any policy: I always thought that policy was Mr. Pitt’s business.
Catherine | Lifting her eyebrows. So?
Varinka | What else did you presume to admire her Majesty for, pray?
Edstaston | Addled. Well, I—I—I—that is, I—He stammers himself dumb.
Catherine | After a pitiless silence. We are waiting for your answer.
Edstaston | But I never said I admired your Majesty. The lady has twisted my words.
Varinka | You don’t admire her, then?
Edstaston | Well, I—naturally—of course, I can’t deny that the uniform was very becoming—perhaps a little unfeminine—still—
Dead silence. Catherine and the Court watch him stonily. He is wretchedly embarrassed.
Catherine | With cold majesty. Well, sir: is that all you have to say?
Edstaston | Surely there is no harm in noticing that er—that er—He stops again.
Catherine | Noticing that er—? He gazes at her, speechless, like a fascinated rabbit. She repeats fiercely. That er—?
Edstaston | Startled into speech. Well, that your Majesty was—was—Soothingly. Well, let me put it this way: that it was rather natural for a man to admire your Majesty without being a philosopher.
Catherine | Suddenly smiling and extending her hand to him to be kissed. Courtier!
Edstaston | Kissing it. Not at all. Your Majesty is very good. I have been very awkward; but I did not intend it. I am rather stupid, I am afraid.
Catherine | Stupid! By no means. Courage, Captain: we are pleased. He falls on his knee. She takes his cheeks in her hands: turns up his face: and adds: We are greatly pleased. She slaps his cheek coquettishly: he bows almost to his knee. The petit lever is over. She turns to go into the cabinet, and stumbles against the supine Patiomkin. Ach! Edstaston springs to her assistance, seizing Patiomkin’s heels and shifting him out of the Empress’s path. We thank you, Captain.
He bows gallantly and is rewarded by a very gracious smile. Then Catherine goes into her cabinet, followed by the Princess Dashkoff, who turns at the door to make a deep courtsey to Edstaston.
Varinka | Happy Little Father! Remember: I did this for you. She runs out after the Empress.
Edstaston, somewhat dazed, crosses the room to the courtiers, and is received with marked deference, each courtier making him a profound bow or curtsey before withdrawing through the central doors. He returns each obeisance with a nervous jerk, and turns away from it, only to find another courtier bowing at the other side. The process finally reduces him to distraction, as he bumps into one in the act of bowing to another and then has to bow his apologies. But at last they are all gone except Naryshkin.
Edstaston | Ouf!
Patiomkin | Jumping up vigorously. You have done it, darling. Superbly! Beautifully!
Edstaston | Astonished. Do you mean to say you are not drunk?
Patiomkin | Not dead drunk, darling. Only diplomatically drunk. As a drunken hog, I have done for you in five minutes what I could not have done in five months as a sober man. Your fortune is made. She likes you.
Edstaston | The devil she does!
Patiomkin | Why? Aren’t you delighted?
Edstaston | Delighted! Gracious heavens, man, I am engaged to be married.
Patiomkin | What matter? She is in England, isn’t she?
Edstaston | No. She has just arrived in St. Petersburg.
The Princess Dashkoff | Returning. Captain Edstaston, the Empress is robed, and commands your presence.
Edstaston | Say I was gone before you arrived with the message. He hurries out. The other three, too taken aback to stop him, stare after him in the utmost astonishment.
Naryshkin | Turning from the door. She will have him knouted. He is a dead man.
The Princess Dashkoff | But what am I to do? I cannot take such an answer to the Empress.
Patiomkin | P‑P‑P‑P‑P‑P‑W‑W‑W‑W‑W‑rrrrrr! A long puff, turning into a growl. He spits. I must kick somebody.
Naryshkin | Flying precipitately through the central doors. No, no. Please.
The Princess Dashkoff | Throwing herself recklessly in front of Patiomkin as he starts in pursuit of the Chamberlain. Kick me. Disable me. It will be an excuse for not going back to her. Kick me hard.
Patiomkin | Yah! He flings her on the bed and dashes after Naryshkin.

The Third Scene

In a terrace garden overlooking the Neva. Claire, a robust young English lady, is leaning on the river wall. She turns expectantly on hearing the garden gate opened and closed. Edstaston hurries in. With a cry of delight she throws her arms round his neck.

Claire | Darling!
Edstaston | Making a wry face. Don’t call me darling.
Claire | Amazed and chilled. Why?
Edstaston | I have been called darling all the morning.
Claire | With a flash of jealousy. By whom?
Edstaston | By everybody. By the most unutterable swine. And if we do not leave this abominable city now: do you hear? now; I shall be called darling by the Empress.
Claire | With magnificent snobbery. She would not dare. Did you tell her you were engaged to me?
Edstaston | Of course not.
Claire | Why?
Edstaston | Because I didn’t particularly want to have you knouted, and to be hanged or sent to Siberia myself.
Claire | What on earth do you mean?
Edstaston | Well, the long and short of it is—don’t think me a coxcomb, Claire: it is too serious to mince matters—I have seen the Empress; and—
Claire | Well, you wanted to see her.
Edstaston | Yes; but the Empress has seen me.
Claire | She has fallen in love with you!
Edstaston | How did you know?
Claire | Dearest: as if anyone could help it.
Edstaston | Oh, don’t make me feel like a fool. But, though it does sound conceited to say it, I flatter myself I’m better looking than Patiomkin and the other hogs she is accustomed to. Anyhow, I daren’t risk staying.
Claire | What a nuisance! Mamma will be furious at having to pack, and at missing the Court ball this evening.
Edstaston | I can’t help that. We haven’t a moment to lose.
Claire | May I tell her she will be knouted if we stay?
Edstaston | Do, dearest.
He kisses her and lets her go, expecting her to run into the house.
Claire | Pausing thoughtfully. Is she—is she good-looking when you see her close?
Edstaston | Not a patch on you, dearest.
Claire | Jealous. Then you did see her close?
Edstaston | Fairly close.
Claire | Indeed! How close? No: that’s silly of me: I will tell mamma. She is going out when Naryshkin enters with the Sergeant and a squad of soldiers. What do you want here?
The Sergeant goes to Edstaston; plumps down on his knees; and takes out a magnificent pair of pistols with gold grips. He proffers them to Edstaston, holding them by the barrels.
Naryshkin | Captain Edstaston: his Highness Prince Patiomkin sends you the pistols he promised you.
The Sergeant | Take them, Little Father; and do not forget us poor soldiers who have brought them to you; for God knows we get but little to drink.
Edstaston | Irresolutely. But I can’t take these valuable things. By Jiminy, though, they’re beautiful! Look at them, Claire.
As he is taking the pistols the kneeling Sergeant suddenly drops them; flings himself forward; and embraces Edstaston’s hips to prevent him from drawing his own pistols from his boots.
The Sergeant | Lay hold of him there. Pin his arms. I have his pistols. The soldiers seize Edstaston.
Edstaston | Ah, would you, damn you! He drives his knee into the Sergeant’s epigastrium, and struggles furiously with his captors.
The Sergeant | Rolling on the ground, gasping and groaning. Owgh! Murder! Holy Nicholas! Owwwgh!
Claire | Help! help! They are killing Charles. Help!
Naryshkin | Seizing her and clapping his hand over her mouth. Tie him neck and crop. Ten thousand blows of the stick if you let him go. Claire twists herself loose; turns on him; and cuffs him furiously. Yow—ow! Have mercy, Little Mother.
Claire | You wretch! Help! Help! Police! We are being murdered. Help!
The Sergeant, who has risen, comes to Naryshkin’s rescue, and grasps Claire’s hands, enabling Naryshkin to gag her again. By this time Edstaston and his captors are all rolling on the ground together. They get Edstaston on his back and fasten his wrists together behind his knees. Next they put a broad strap round his ribs. Finally they pass a pole through this breast strap and through the waist strap and lift him by it, helplessly trussed up, to carry him off. Meanwhile he is by no means suffering in silence.
Edstaston | Gasping. You shall hear more of this. Damn you, will you untie me? I will complain to the ambassador. I will write to the Gazette. England will blow your trumpery little fleet out of the water and sweep your tinpot army into Siberia for this. Will you let me go? Damn you! Curse you! What the devil do you mean by it? I’ll—I’ll—I’ll—He is carried out of hearing.
Naryshkin | Snatching his hands from Claire’s face with a scream, and shaking his finger frantically. Agh! The Sergeant, amazed, lets go her hands. She has bitten me, the little vixen.
Claire | Spitting and wiping her mouth disgustedly. How dare you put your dirty paws on my mouth? Ugh! Psha!
The Sergeant | Be merciful, Little angel Mother.
Claire | Do not presume to call me your little angel mother. Where are the police?
Naryshkin | We are the police in St. Petersburg, little spitfire.
The Sergeant | God knows we have no orders to harm you, Little Mother. Our duty is done. You are well and strong; but I shall never be the same man again. He is a mighty and terrible fighter, as stout as a bear. He has broken my sweetbread with his strong knees. God knows poor folk should not be set upon such dangerous adversaries!
Claire | Serve you right! Where have they taken Captain Edstaston to?
Naryshkin | Spitefully. To the Empress, little beauty. He has insulted the Empress. He will receive a hundred and one blows of the knout. He laughs and goes out, nursing his bitten finger.
The Sergeant | He will feel only the first twenty and he will be mercifully dead long before the end, little darling.
Claire | Sustained by an invincible snobbery. They dare not touch an English officer. I will go to the Empress myself: she cannot know who Captain Edstaston is—who we are.
The Sergeant | Do so in the name of the Holy Nicholas, little beauty.
Claire | Don’t be impertinent. How can I get admission to the palace?
The Sergeant | Everybody goes in and out of the palace, little love.
Claire | But I must get into the Empress’s presence. I must speak to her.
The Sergeant | You shall, dear Little Mother. You shall give the poor old Sergeant a rouble; and the blessed Nicholas will make your salvation his charge.
Claire | Impetuously. I will give you she is about to say fifty roubles, but checks herself cautiously—Well: I don’t mind giving you two roubles if I can speak to the Empress.
The Sergeant | Joyfully. I praise Heaven for you, Little Mother. Come. He leads the way out. It was the temptation of the devil that led your young man to bruise my vitals and deprive me of breath. We must be merciful to one another’s faults.

The Fourth Scene

A triangular recess communicating by a heavily curtained arch with the huge ballroom of the palace. The light is subdued by red shades on the candles. In the wall adjoining that pierced by the arch is a door. The only piece of furniture is a very handsome chair on the arch side. In the ballroom they are dancing a polonaise to the music of a brass band.

Naryshkin enters through the door, followed by the soldiers carrying Edstaston, still trussed to the pole. Exhausted and dogged, he makes no sound.

Naryshkin | Halt. Get that pole clear of the prisoner. They dump Edstaston on the floor and detach the pole. Naryshkin stoops over him and addresses him insultingly. Well! are you ready to be tortured? This is the Empress’s private torture chamber. Can I do anything to make you quite comfortable? You have only to mention it.
Edstaston | Have you any back teeth?
Naryshkin | Surprised. Why?
Edstaston | His Majesty King George the Third will send for six of them when the news of this reaches London; so look out, damn your eyes!
Naryshkin | Frightened. Oh, I assure you I am only obeying my orders. Personally I abhor torture, and would save you if I could. But the Empress is proud; and what woman would forgive the slight you put upon her?
Edstaston | As I said before: Damn your eyes!
Naryshkin | Almost in tears. Well, it isn’t my fault. To the soldiers, insolently. You know your orders? You remember what you have to do when the Empress gives you the word? The soldiers salute in assent.
Naryshkin passes through the curtains, admitting a blare of music and a strip of the brilliant white candlelight from the chandeliers in the ballroom as he does so. The white light vanishes and the music is muffled as the curtains fall together behind him. Presently the band stops abruptly; and Naryshkin comes back through the curtains. He makes a warning gesture to the soldiers, who stand at attention. Then he moves the curtain to allow Catherine to enter. She is in full Imperial regalia, and stops sternly just where she has entered. The soldiers fall on their knees.
Catherine | Obey your orders.
The soldiers seize Edstaston, and throw him roughly at the feet of the Empress.
Catherine | Looking down coldly on him. Also the German word, you have put me to the trouble of sending for you twice. You had better have come the first time.
Edstaston | Exsufflicate, and pettishly angry. I haven’t come either time. I’ve been carried. I call it infernal impudence.
Catherine | Take care what you say.
Edstaston | No use. I daresay you look very majestic and very handsome; but I can’t see you; and I am not intimidated. I am an Englishman; and you can kidnap me; but you can’t bully me.
Naryshkin | Remember to whom you are speaking.
Catherine | Violently, furious at his intrusion. Remember that dogs should be dumb. He shrivels. And do you, Captain, remember that famous as I am for my clemency, there are limits to the patience even of an Empress.
Edstaston | How is a man to remember anything when he is trussed up in this ridiculous fashion? I can hardly breathe. He makes a futile struggle to free himself. Here: don’t be unkind, your Majesty: tell these fellows to unstrap me. You know you really owe me an apology.
Catherine | You think you can escape by appealing, like Prince Patiomkin, to my sense of humor?
Edstaston | Sense of humor! Ho! Ha, ha! I like that. Would anybody with a sense of humor make a guy of a man like this, and then expect him to take it seriously? I say: do tell them to loosen these straps.
Catherine | Seating herself. Why should I, pray?
Edstaston | Why! Why!! Why, because they’re hurting me.
Catherine | People sometimes learn through suffering. Manners, for instance.
Edstaston | Oh, well, of course, if you’re an ill-natured woman, hurting me on purpose, I have nothing more to say.
Catherine | A monarch, sir, has sometimes to employ a necessary and salutary severity—
Edstaston | Interrupting her petulantly. Quack! quack! quack!
Catherine | Donnerwetter!
Edstaston | Continuing recklessly. This isn’t severity: it’s tomfoolery. And if you think it’s reforming my character or teaching me anything, you’re mistaken. It may be a satisfaction to you; but if it is, all I can say is that it’s not an amiable satisfaction.
Catherine | Turning suddenly and balefully on Naryshkin. What are you grinning at?
Naryshkin | Falling on his knees in terror. Be merciful, Little Mother. My heart is in my mouth.
Catherine | Your heart and your mouth will be in two separate parts of your body if you again forget in whose presence you stand. Go. And take your men with you. Naryshkin crawls to the door. The soldiers rise. Stop. Roll that indicating Edstaston nearer. The soldiers obey. Not so close. Did I ask you for a footstool? She pushes Edstaston away with her foot.
Edstaston | With a sudden squeal. Agh!!! I must really ask your Majesty not to put the point of your Imperial toe between my ribs. I am ticklesome.
Catherine | Indeed? All the more reason for you to treat me with respect, Captain. To the others. Begone. How many times must I give an order before it is obeyed?
Naryshkin | Little Mother: they have brought some instruments of torture. Will they be needed?
Catherine | Indignantly. How dare you name such abominations to a Liberal Empress? You will always be a savage and a fool, Naryshkin. These relics of barbarism are buried, thank God, in the grave of Peter the Great. My methods are more civilized. She extends her toe towards Edstaston’s ribs.
Edstaston | Shrieking hysterically. Yagh! Ah! Furiously. If your Majesty does that again I will write to the London Gazette.
Catherine | To the soldiers. Leave us. Quick! do you hear? Five thousand blows of the stick for the soldier who is in the room when I speak next. The soldiers rush out. Naryshkin: are you waiting to be knouted? Naryshkin backs out hastily.
Catherine and Edstaston are now alone. Catherine has in her hand a sceptre or baton of gold. Wrapped round it is a new pamphlet, in French, entitled L’Homme aux Quarante Ecus. She calmly unrolls this and begins to read it at her ease as if she were quite alone. Several seconds elapse in dead silence. She becomes more and more absorbed in the pamphlet, and more and more amused by it.
Catherine | Greatly pleased by a passage, and turning over the leaf. Ausgezeiehnet!
Edstaston | Ahem!
Silence. Catherine reads on.
Catherine | Wie komisch!
Edstaston | Ahem! ahem!
Silence.
Catherine | Soliloquizing enthusiastically. What a wonderful author is Monsieur Voltaire! How lucidly he exposes the folly of this crazy plan for raising the entire revenue of the country from a single tax on land! how he withers it with his irony! how he makes you laugh whilst he is convincing you! how sure one feels that the proposal is killed by his wit and economic penetration: killed never to be mentioned again among educated people!
Edstaston | For Heaven’s sake, Madam, do you intend to leave me tied up like this while you discuss the blasphemies of that abominable infidel? Agh!! She has again applied her toe. Oh! Oo!
Catherine | Calmly. Do I understand you to say that Monsieur Voltaire is a great philanthropist and a great philosopher as well as the wittiest man in Europe?
Edstaston | Certainly not. I say that his books ought to be burnt by the common hangman. Her toe touches his ribs. Yagh! Oh don’t. I shall faint. I can’t bear it.
Catherine | Have you changed your opinion of Monsieur Voltaire?
Edstaston | But you can’t expect me as a member of the Church of England she tickles him—Agh! Ow! Oh Lord! he is anything you like. He is a philanthropist, a philosopher, a beauty: he ought to have a statue, damn him! She tickles him. No! bless him! save him victorious, happy and glorious! Oh, let eternal honors crown his name: Voltaire thrice worthy on the rolls of fame! Exhausted. Now will you let me up? And look here! I can see your ankles when you tickle me: it’s not ladylike.
Catherine | Sticking out her toe and admiring it critically. Is the spectacle so disagreeable?
Edstaston | It’s agreeable enough; only with intense expression for heaven’s sake don’t touch me in the ribs.
Catherine | Putting aside the pamphlet. Captain Edstaston, why did you refuse to come when I sent for you?
Edstaston | Madam: I cannot talk tied up like this.
Catherine | Do you still admire me as much as you did this morning?
Edstaston | How can I possibly tell when I can’t see you? Let me get up and look. I can’t see anything now except my toes and yours.
Catherine | Do you still intend to write to the London Gazette about me?
Edstaston | Not if you will loosen these straps. Quick: loosen me. I’m fainting.
Catherine | I don’t think you are. Tickling him.
Edstaston | Agh! Cat!
Catherine | What! She tickles him again.
Edstaston | With a shriek. No: angel, angel!
Catherine | Tenderly. Geliebter!
Edstaston | I don’t know a word of German; but that sounded kind. Becoming hysterical. Little Mother, beautiful little darling angel mother: don’t be cruel: untie me. Oh, I beg and implore you. Don’t be unkind. I shall go mad.
Catherine | You are expected to go mad with love when an Empress deigns to interest herself in you. When an Empress allows you to see her foot you should kiss it. Captain Edstaston: you are a booby.
Edstaston | Indignantly. I am nothing of the kind. I have been mentioned in dispatches as a highly intelligent officer. And let me warn your Majesty that I am not so helpless as you think. The English Ambassador is in that ballroom. A shout from me will bring him to my side; and then where will your Majesty be?
Catherine | I should like to see the English Ambassador or anyone else pass through that curtain against my orders. It might be a stone wall ten feet thick. Shout your loudest. Sob. Curse. Scream. Yell. She tickles him unmercifully.
Edstaston | Frantically. Ahowyow!!!! Agh! Ooh! Stop! Oh Lord! Ya‑a‑a‑ah! A tumult in the ballroom responds to his cries.
Voices from the Ballroom | Stand back. You cannot pass. Hold her back there. The Empress’s orders. It is out of the question. No, little darling, not in there. Nobody is allowed in there. You will be sent to Siberia. Don’t let her through there, on your life. Drag her back. You will be knouted. It is hopeless, Mademoiselle: you must obey orders. Guard there! Send some men to hold her.
Claire’s Voice | Let me go. They are torturing Charles in there. I will go. How can you all dance as if nothing was happening? Let me go, I tell you. Let—me—go. She dashes through the curtain. No one dares follow her.
Catherine | Rising in wrath. How dare you?
Claire | Recklessly. Oh, dare your grandmother! Where is my Charles? What are they doing to him?
Edstaston | Shouting. Claire: loosen these straps, in Heaven’s name. Quick.
Claire | Seeing him and throwing herself on her knees at his side. Oh, how dare they tie you up like that! To Catherine. You wicked wretch! You Russian savage! She pounces on the straps, and begins unbuckling them.
Catherine | Conquering herself with a mighty effort. Now self-control. Self-control, Catherine. Philosophy. Europe is looking on. She forces herself to sit down.
Edstaston | Steady, dearest: it is the Empress. Call her your Imperial Majesty. Call her Star of the North, Little Mother, Little Darling: that’s what she likes; but get the straps off.
Claire | Keep quiet, dear: I cannot get them off if you move.
Catherine | Calmly. Keep quite still, Captain. She tickles him.
Edstaston | Ow! Agh! Ahowyow!
Claire | Stopping dead in the act of unbuckling the straps and turning sick with jealousy as she grasps the situation. Was that what I thought was your being tortured?
Catherine | Urbanely. That is the favorite torture of Catherine the Second, Mademoiselle. I think the Captain enjoys it very much.
Claire | Then he can have as much more of it as he wants. I am sorry I intruded. She rises to go.
Edstaston | Catching her train in his teeth and holding on like a bulldog. Don’t go. Don’t leave me in this horrible state. Loosen me. This is what he is saying: but as he says it with the train in his mouth it is not very intelligible.
Claire | Let go. You are undignified and ridiculous enough yourself without making me ridiculous. She snatches her train away.
Edstaston | Ow! You’ve nearly pulled my teeth out: you’re worse than the Star of the North. To Catherine. Darling Little Mother: you have a kind heart, the kindest in Europe. Have pity. Have mercy. I love you. Claire bursts into tears. Release me.
Catherine | Well, just to show you how much kinder a Russian savage can be than an English one (though I am sorry to say I am a German) here goes! She stoops to loosen the straps.
Claire | Jealously. You needn’t trouble, thank you. She pounces on the straps; and the two set Edstaston free between them. Now get up, please; and conduct yourself with some dignity if you are not utterly demoralized.
Edstaston | Dignity! Ow! I can’t. I’m stiff all over. I shall never be able to stand up again. Oh Lord! how it hurts! They seize him by the shoulders and drag him up. Yah! Agh! Wow! Oh! Mmmmmm! Oh, Little Angel Mother, don’t ever do this to a man again. Knout him; kill him; roast him; baste him; head, hang, and quarter him; but don’t tie him up like that and tickle him.
Catherine | Your young lady still seems to think that you enjoyed it.
Claire | I know what I think. I will never speak to him again. Your Majesty can keep him, as far as I am concerned.
Catherine | I would not deprive you of him for worlds; though really I think he’s rather a darling. She pats his cheek.
Claire | Snorting. So I see, indeed.
Edstaston | Don’t be angry, dearest: in this country everybody’s a darling. I’ll prove it to you. To Catherine. Will your Majesty be good enough to call Prince Patiomkin?
Catherine | Surprised into haughtiness. Why?
Edstaston | To oblige me.
Catherine laughs good-humoredly and goes to the curtains and opens them. The band strikes up a Redowa.
Catherine | Calling imperiously. Patiomkin! The music stops suddenly. Here! To me! Go on with your music there, you fools. The Redowa is resumed.
The Sergeant rushes from the ballroom to relieve the Empress of the curtain. Patiomkin comes in dancing with Varinka.
Catherine | To Patiomkin. The English captain wants you, little darling.
Catherine resumes her seat as Patiomkin intimates by a grotesque bow that he is at Edstaston’s service. Varinka passes behind Edstaston and Claire, and posts herself on Claire’s right.
Edstaston | Precisely. To Claire. You observe, my love: “little darling.” Well, if her Majesty calls him a darling, is it my fault that she calls me one too?
Claire | I don’t care: I don’t think you ought to have done it. I am very angry and offended.
Edstaston | They tied me up, dear. I couldn’t help it. I fought for all I was worth.
The Sergeant | At the curtains. He fought with the strength of lions and bears. God knows I shall carry a broken sweetbread to my grave.
Edstaston | You can’t mean to throw me over, Claire. Urgently. Claire. Claire.
Varinka | In a transport of sympathetic emotion, pleading with clasped hands to Claire. Oh, sweet little angel lamb, he loves you: it shines in his darling eyes. Pardon him, pardon him.
Patiomkin | Rushing from the Empress’s side to Claire and falling on his knees to her. Pardon him, pardon him, little cherub! little wild duck! little star! little glory! little jewel in the crown of heaven!
Claire | This is perfectly ridiculous.
Varinka | Kneeling to her. Pardon him, pardon him, little delight, little sleeper in a rosy cradle.
Claire | I’ll do anything if you’ll only let me alone.
The Sergeant | Kneeling to her. Pardon him, pardon him, lest the mighty man bring his whip to you. God knows we all need pardon!
Claire | At the top of her voice. I pardon him! I pardon him!
Patiomkin | Springing up joyfully and going behind Claire, whom he raises in his arms. Embrace her, victor of Bunker’s Hill. Kiss her till she swoons.
The Sergeant | Receive her in the name of the holy Nicholas.
Varinka | She begs you for a thousand dear little kisses all over her body.
Claire | Vehemently. I do not. Patiomkin throws her into Edstaston’s arms. Oh! The pair, awkward and shamefaced, recoil from one another, and remain utterly inexpressive.
Catherine | Pushing Edstaston towards Claire. There is no help for it, Captain. This is Russia, not England.
Edstaston | Plucking up some geniality, and kissing Claire ceremoniously on the brow. I have no objection.
Varinka | Disgusted. Only one kiss! and on the forehead! Fish. See how I kiss, though it is only my horribly ugly old uncle. She throws her arms round Patiomkin’s neck and covers his face with kisses.
The Sergeant | Moved to tears. Sainted Nicholas: bless your lambs!
Catherine | Do you wonder now that I love Russia as I love no other place on earth?
Naryshkin | Appearing at the door. Majesty: the model for the new museum has arrived.
Catherine | Rising eagerly and making for the curtains. Let us go. I can think of nothing but my museum. In the archway she stops and turns to Edstaston, who has hurried to lift the curtain for her. Captain, I wish you every happiness that your little angel can bring you. For his ear alone. I could have brought you more; but you did not think so. Farewell.
Edstaston | Kissing her hand, which, instead of releasing, he holds caressingly and rather patronizingly in his own. I feel your Majesty’s kindness so much that I really cannot leave you without a word of plain wholesome English advice.
Exclaiming simultaneously.
Catherine | Snatching her hand away and bounding forward as if he had touched her with a spur. Advice!!!
Patiomkin | Madman: take care!
Naryshkin | Advise the Empress!!
The Sergeant | Sainted Nicholas!
Varinka | Hoo hoo! A stifled splutter of laughter.
Edstaston | Following the Empress and resuming kindly but judicially. After all, though your Majesty is of course a great queen, yet when all is said, I am a man; and your Majesty is only a woman.
Catherine | Only a wo— She chokes.
Edstaston | Continuing. Believe me, this Russian extravagance will not do. I appreciate as much as any man the warmth of heart that prompts it; but it is overdone: it is hardly in the best taste: it is—really I must say it—it is not proper.
Catherine | Ironically, in German. So!
Edstaston | Not that I cannot make allowances. Your Majesty has, I know, been unfortunate in your experience as a married woman—
Catherine | Furious. Alle Wetter!!!
Edstaston | Sentimentally. Don’t say that. Don’t think of him in that way. After all, he was your husband; and whatever his faults may have been, it is not for you to think unkindly of him.
Catherine | Almost bursting. I shall forget myself.
Edstaston | Come! I am sure he really loved you; and you truly loved him.
Catherine | Controlling herself with a supreme effort. No, Catherine. What would Voltaire say?
Edstaston | Oh, never mind that vile scoffer. Set an example to Europe, Madam, by doing what I am going to do. Marry again. Marry some good man who will be a strength and a support to your old age.
Catherine | My old— She again becomes speechless.
Edstaston | Yes: we must all grow old, even the handsomest of us.
Catherine | Sinking into her chair with a gasp. Thank you.
Edstaston | You will thank me more when you see your little ones round your knee, and your man there by the fireside in the winter evenings—by the way, I forgot that you have no fireside here in spite of the coldness of the climate; so shall I say by the stove?
Catherine | Certainly, if you wish. The stove by all means.
Edstaston | Impulsively. Ah, Madam, abolish the stove: believe me, there is nothing like the good old open grate. Home! duty! happiness! they all mean the same thing; and they all flourish best on the drawing room hearthrug. Turning to Claire. And now, my love, we must not detain the Queen: she is anxious to inspect the model of her museum, to which I am sure we wish every success.
Claire | Coldly. I am not detaining her.
Edstaston | Well, goodbye wringing Patiomkin’s hand goo‑oo‑oodbye, Prince: come and see us if ever you visit England. Spire View, Deepdene, Little Mugford, Devon, will always find me. To Varinka, kissing her hand. Goodbye, Mademoiselle: goodbye, Little Mother, if I may call you that just once. Varinka puts up her face to be kissed. Eh? No, no, no, no: you don’t mean that, you know. Naughty! To the Sergeant. Goodbye, my friend. You will drink our healths with this. Tipping him.
The Sergeant | The blessed Nicholas will multiply your fruits, Little Father.
Edstaston | Goodbye, goodbye, goodbye, goodbye, goodbye, goodbye.
He goes out backwards, bowing, with Claire curtseying, having been listened to in utter dumbfoundedness by Patiomkin and Naryshkin, in childlike awe by Varinka, and with quite inexpressible feelings by Catherine. When he is out of sight she rises with clenched fists and raises her arms and her closed eyes to Heaven. Patiomkin, rousing himself from his stupor of amazement, springs to her like a tiger, and throws himself at her feet.
Patiomkin | What shall I do to him for you? Skin him alive? Cut off his eyelids and stand him in the sun? Tear his tongue out? What shall it be?
Catherine | Opening her eyes. Nothing. But oh, if I could only have had him for my—for my—for my—
Patiomkin | In a growl of jealousy. For your lover?
Catherine | With an ineffable smile. No: for my museum.

How He Lied to Her Husband

Preface

Like many other works of mine, this playlet is a piêce d’occasion. In 1905 it happened that Mr. Arnold Daly, who was then playing the part of Napoleon in The Man of Destiny in New York, found that whilst the play was too long to take a secondary place in the evening’s performance, it was too short to suffice by itself. I therefore took advantage of four days continuous rain during a holiday in the north of Scotland to write “How He Lied To Her Husband” for Mr. Daly. In his hands, it served its turn very effectively.

I print it here as a sample of what can be done with even the most hackneyed stage framework by filling it in with an observed touch of actual humanity instead of with doctrinaire romanticism. Nothing in the theatre is staler than the situation of husband, wife and lover, or the fun of knockabout farce. I have taken both, and got an original play out of them, as anybody else can if only he will look about him for his material instead of plagiarizing Othello and the thousand plays that have proceeded on Othello’s romantic assumptions and false point of honor.

A further experiment made by Mr. Arnold Daly with this play is worth recording. In 1905 Mr. Daly produced Mrs. Warren’s Profession in New York. The press of that city instantly raised a cry that such persons as Mrs. Warren are “ordure,” and should not be mentioned in the presence of decent people. This hideous repudiation of humanity and social conscience so took possession of the New York journalists that the few among them who kept their feet morally and intellectually could do nothing to check the epidemic of foul language, gross suggestion, and raving obscenity of word and thought that broke out. The writers abandoned all self-restraint under the impression that they were upholding virtue instead of outraging it. They infected each other with their hysteria until they were for all practical purposes indecently mad. They finally forced the police to arrest Mr. Daly and his company, and led the magistrate to express his loathing of the duty thus forced upon him of reading an unmentionable and abominable play. Of course the convulsion soon exhausted itself. The magistrate, naturally somewhat impatient when he found that what he had to read was a strenuously ethical play forming part of a book which had been in circulation unchallenged for eight years, and had been received without protest by the whole London and New York press, gave the journalists a piece of his mind as to their moral taste in plays. By consent, he passed the case on to a higher court, which declared that the play was not immoral; acquitted Mr. Daly; and made an end of the attempt to use the law to declare living women to be “ordure,” and thus enforce silence as to the far-reaching fact that you cannot cheapen women in the market for industrial purposes without cheapening them for other purposes as well. I hope Mrs. Warren’s Profession will be played everywhere, in season and out of season, until Mrs. Warren has bitten that fact into the public conscience, and shamed the newspapers which support a tariff to keep up the price of every American commodity except American manhood and womanhood.

Unfortunately, Mr. Daly had already suffered the usual fate of those who direct public attention to the profits of the sweater or the pleasures of the voluptuary. He was morally lynched side by side with me. Months elapsed before the decision of the courts vindicated him; and even then, since his vindication implied the condemnation of the press, which was by that time sober again, and ashamed of its orgy, his triumph received a rather sulky and grudging publicity. In the meantime he had hardly been able to approach an American city, including even those cities which had heaped applause on him as the defender of hearth and home when he produced Candida, without having to face articles discussing whether mothers could allow their daughters to attend such plays as You Never Can Tell, written by the infamous author of Mrs. Warren’s Profession, and acted by the monster who produced it. What made this harder to bear was that though no fact is better established in theatrical business than the financial disastrousness of moral discredit, the journalists who had done all the mischief kept paying vice the homage of assuming that it is enormously popular and lucrative, and that I and Mr. Daly, being exploiters of vice, must therefore be making colossal fortunes out of the abuse heaped on us, and had in fact provoked it and welcomed it with that express object. Ignorance of real life could hardly go further.

One consequence was that Mr. Daly could not have kept his financial engagements or maintained his hold on the public had he not accepted engagements to appear for a season in the vaudeville theatres (the American equivalent of our music halls), where he played “How He Lied To Her Husband” comparatively unhampered by the press censorship of the theatre, or by that sophistication of the audience through press suggestion from which I suffer more, perhaps, than any other author. Vaudeville authors are fortunately unknown: the audiences see what the play contains and what the actor can do, not what the papers have told them to expect. Success under such circumstances had a value both for Mr. Daly and myself which did something to console us for the very unsavory mobbing which the New York press organized for us, and which was not the less disgusting because we suffered in a good cause and in the very best company.

Mr. Daly, having weathered the storm, can perhaps shake his soul free of it as he heads for fresh successes with younger authors. But I have certain sensitive places in my soul: I do not like that word “ordure.” Apply it to my work, and I can afford to smile, since the world, on the whole, will smile with me. But to apply it to the woman in the street, whose spirit is of one substance with our own and her body no less holy: to look your women folk in the face afterwards and not go out and hang yourself: that is not on the list of pardonable sins.

Postscript. Since the above was written news has arrived from America that a leading New York newspaper, which was among the most abusively clamorous for the suppression of Mrs. Warren’s Profession, has just been fined heavily for deriving part of its revenue from advertisements of Mrs. Warren’s houses.

Many people have been puzzled by the fact that whilst stage entertainments which are frankly meant to act on the spectators as aphrodisiacs, are everywhere tolerated, plays which have an almost horrifyingly contrary effect are fiercely attacked by persons and papers notoriously indifferent to public morals on all other occasions. The explanation is very simple. The profits of Mrs. Warren’s profession are shared not only by Mrs. Warren and Sir George Crofts, but by the landlords of their houses, the newspapers which advertise them, the restaurants which cater for them, and, in short, all the trades to which they are good customers, not to mention the public officials and representatives whom they silence by complicity, corruption, or blackmail. Add to these the employers who profit by cheap female labor, and the shareholders whose dividends depend on it (you find such people everywhere, even on the judicial bench and in the highest places in Church and State), and you get a large and powerful class with a strong pecuniary incentive to protect Mrs. Warren’s profession, and a correspondingly strong incentive to conceal, from their own consciences no less than from the world, the real sources of their gain. These are the people who declare that it is feminine vice and not poverty that drives women to the streets, as if vicious women with independent incomes ever went there. These are the people who, indulgent or indifferent to aphrodisiac plays, raise the moral hue and cry against performances of Mrs. Warren’s Profession, and drag actresses to the police court to be insulted, bullied, and threatened for fulfilling their engagements. For please observe that the judicial decision in New York State in favor of the play does not end the matter. In Kansas City, for instance, the municipality, finding itself restrained by the courts from preventing the performance, fell back on a local bylaw against indecency to evade the Constitution of the United States. They summoned the actress who impersonated Mrs. Warren to the police court, and offered her and her colleagues the alternative of leaving the city or being prosecuted under this bylaw.

Now nothing is more possible than that the city councillors who suddenly displayed such concern for the morals of the theatre were either Mrs. Warren’s landlords, or employers of women at starvation wages, or restaurant keepers, or newspaper proprietors, or in some other more or less direct way sharers of the profits of her trade. No doubt it is equally possible that they were simply stupid men who thought that indecency consists, not in evil, but in mentioning it. I have, however, been myself a member of a municipal council, and have not found municipal councillors quite so simple and inexperienced as this. At all events I do not propose to give the Kansas councillors the benefit of the doubt. I therefore advise the public at large, which will finally decide the matter, to keep a vigilant eye on gentlemen who will stand anything at the theatre except a performance of Mrs. Warren’s Profession, and who assert in the same breath that (a) the play is too loathsome to be bearable by civilized people, and (b) that unless its performance is prohibited the whole town will throng to see it. They may be merely excited and foolish; but I am bound to warn the public that it is equally likely that they may be collected and knavish.

At all events, to prohibit the play is to protect the evil which the play exposes; and in view of that fact, I see no reason for assuming that the prohibitionists are disinterested moralists, and that the author, the managers, and the performers, who depend for their livelihood on their personal reputations and not on rents, advertisements, or dividends, are grossly inferior to them in moral sense and public responsibility.

It is true that in Mrs. Warren’s Profession, Society, and not any individual, is the villain of the piece; but it does not follow that the people who take offence at it are all champions of society. Their credentials cannot be too carefully examined.

Dramatis Personae

He (Henry Apjohn)

She (Aurora Bompas)

Her Husband (Teddy Bompas)

How He Lied to Her Husband

It is eight o’clock in the evening. The curtains are drawn and the lamps lighted in the drawing room of Her flat in Cromwell Road. Her lover, a beautiful youth of eighteen, in evening dress and cape, with a bunch of flowers and an opera hat in his hands, comes in alone. The door is near the corner; and as he appears in the doorway, he has the fireplace on the nearest wall to his right, and the grand piano along the opposite wall to his left. Near the fireplace a small ornamental table has on it a hand mirror, a fan, a pair of long white gloves, and a little white woollen cloud to wrap a woman’s head in. On the other side of the room, near the piano, is a broad, square, softly upholstered stool. The room is furnished in the most approved South Kensington fashion: that is, it is as like a show room as possible, and is intended to demonstrate the racial position and spending powers of its owners, and not in the least to make them comfortable.

He is, be it repeated, a very beautiful youth, moving as in a dream, walking as on air. He puts his flowers down carefully on the table beside the fan; takes off his cape, and, as there is no room on the table for it, takes it to the piano; puts his hat on the cape; crosses to the hearth; looks at his watch; puts it up again; notices the things on the table; lights up as if he saw heaven opening before him; goes to the table and takes the cloud in both hands, nestling his nose into its softness and kissing it; kisses the gloves one after another; kisses the fan: gasps a long shuddering sigh of ecstasy; sits down on the stool and presses his hands to his eyes to shut out reality and dream a little; takes his hands down and shakes his head with a little smile of rebuke for his folly; catches sight of a speck of dust on his shoes and hastily and carefully brushes it off with his handkerchief; rises and takes the hand mirror from the table to make sure of his tie with the gravest anxiety; and is looking at his watch again when She comes in, much flustered. As she is dressed for the theatre; has spoilt, petted ways; and wears many diamonds, she has an air of being a young and beautiful woman; but as a matter of hard fact, she is, dress and pretensions apart, a very ordinary South Kensington female of about 37, hopelessly inferior in physical and spiritual distinction to the beautiful youth, who hastily puts down the mirror as she enters.

He | Kissing her hand. At last!
She | Henry: something dreadful has happened.
He | What’s the matter?
She | I have lost your poems.
He | They were unworthy of you. I will write you some more.
She | No, thank you. Never any more poems for me. Oh, how could I have been so mad! so rash! so imprudent!
He | Thank Heaven for your madness, your rashness, your imprudence!
She | Impatiently. Oh, be sensible, Henry. Can’t you see what a terrible thing this is for me? Suppose anybody finds these poems! what will they think?
He | They will think that a man once loved a woman more devotedly than ever man loved woman before. But they will not know what man it was.
She | What good is that to me if everybody will know what woman it was?
He | But how will they know?
She | How will they know! Why, my name is all over them: my silly, unhappy name. Oh, if I had only been christened Mary Jane, or Gladys Muriel, or Beatrice, or Francesca, or Guinevere, or something quite common! But Aurora! Aurora! I’m the only Aurora in London; and everybody knows it. I believe I’m the only Aurora in the world. And it’s so horribly easy to rhyme to it! Oh, Henry, why didn’t you try to restrain your feelings a little in common consideration for me? Why didn’t you write with some little reserve?
He | Write poems to you with reserve! You ask me that!
She | With perfunctory tenderness. Yes, dear, of course it was very nice of you; and I know it was my own fault as much as yours. I ought to have noticed that your verses ought never to have been addressed to a married woman.
He | Ah, how I wish they had been addressed to an unmarried woman! how I wish they had!
She | Indeed you have no right to wish anything of the sort. They are quite unfit for anybody but a married woman. That’s just the difficulty. What will my sisters-in-law think of them?
He | Painfully jarred. Have you got sisters-in-law?
She | Yes, of course I have. Do you suppose I am an angel?
He | Biting his lips. I do. Heaven help me, I do—or I did—or He almost chokes a sob.
She | Softening and putting her hand caressingly on his shoulder. Listen to me, dear. It’s very nice of you to live with me in a dream, and to love me, and so on; but I can’t help my husband having disagreeable relatives, can I?
He | Brightening up. Ah, of course they are your husband’s relatives: I forgot that. Forgive me, Aurora. He takes her hand from his shoulder and kisses it. She sits down on the stool. He remains near the table, with his back to it, smiling fatuously down at her.
She | The fact is, Teddy’s got nothing but relatives. He has eight sisters and six half-sisters, and ever so many brothers—but I don’t mind his brothers. Now if you only knew the least little thing about the world, Henry, you’d know that in a large family, though the sisters quarrel with one another like mad all the time, yet let one of the brothers marry, and they all turn on their unfortunate sister-in-law and devote the rest of their lives with perfect unanimity to persuading him that his wife is unworthy of him. They can do it to her very face without her knowing it, because there are always a lot of stupid low family jokes that nobody understands but themselves. Half the time you can’t tell what they’re talking about: it just drives you wild. There ought to be a law against a man’s sister ever entering his house after he’s married. I’m as certain as that I’m sitting here that Georgina stole those poems out of my workbox.
He | She will not understand them, I think.
She | Oh, won’t she! She’ll understand them only too well. She’ll understand more harm than ever was in them: nasty vulgar-minded cat!
He | Going to her. Oh don’t, don’t think of people in that way. Don’t think of her at all. He takes her hand and sits down on the carpet at her feet. Aurora: do you remember the evening when I sat here at your feet and read you those poems for the first time?
She | I shouldn’t have let you: I see that now. When I think of Georgina sitting there at Teddy’s feet and reading them to him for the first time, I feel I shall just go distracted.
He | Yes, you are right. It will be a profanation.
She | Oh, I don’t care about the profanation; but what will Teddy think? what will he do? Suddenly throwing his head away from her knee. You don’t seem to think a bit about Teddy. She jumps up, more and more agitated.
He | Supine on the floor; for she has thrown him off his balance. To me Teddy is nothing, and Georgina less than nothing.
She | You’ll soon find out how much less than nothing she is. If you think a woman can’t do any harm because she’s only a scandalmongering dowdy ragbag, you’re greatly mistaken. She flounces about the room. He gets up slowly and dusts his hands. Suddenly she runs to him and throws herself into his arms. Henry: help me. Find a way out of this for me; and I’ll bless you as long as you live. Oh, how wretched I am! She sobs on his breast.
He | And oh! how happy I am!
She | Whisking herself abruptly away. Don’t be selfish.
He | Humbly. Yes: I deserve that. I think if I were going to the stake with you, I should still be so happy with you that I could hardly feel your danger more than my own.
She | Relenting and patting his hand fondly. Oh, you are a dear darling boy, Henry; but throwing his hand away fretfully you’re no use. I want somebody to tell me what to do.
He | With quiet conviction. Your heart will tell you at the right time. I have thought deeply over this; and I know what we two must do, sooner or later.
She | No, Henry. I will do nothing improper, nothing dishonorable. She sits down plump on the stool and looks inflexible.
He | If you did, you would no longer be Aurora. Our course is perfectly simple, perfectly straightforward, perfectly stainless and true. We love one another. I am not ashamed of that: I am ready to go out and proclaim it to all London as simply as I will declare it to your husband when you see—as you soon will see—that this is the only way honorable enough for your feet to tread. Let us go out together to our own house, this evening, without concealment and without shame. Remember! we owe something to your husband. We are his guests here: he is an honorable man: he has been kind to us: he has perhaps loved you as well as his prosaic nature and his sordid commercial environment permitted. We owe it to him in all honor not to let him learn the truth from the lips of a scandalmonger. Let us go to him now quietly, hand in hand; bid him farewell; and walk out of the house without concealment and subterfuge, freely and honestly, in full honor and self-respect.
She | Staring at him. And where shall we go to?
He | We shall not depart by a hair’s breadth from the ordinary natural current of our lives. We were going to the theatre when the loss of the poems compelled us to take action at once. We shall go to the theatre still; but we shall leave your diamonds here; for we cannot afford diamonds, and do not need them.
She | Fretfully. I have told you already that I hate diamonds; only Teddy insists on hanging me all over with them. You need not preach simplicity to me.
He | I never thought of doing so, dearest: I know that these trivialities are nothing to you. What was I saying—oh yes. Instead of coming back here from the theatre, you will come with me to my home—now and henceforth our home—and in due course of time, when you are divorced, we shall go through whatever idle legal ceremony you may desire. I attach no importance to the law: my love was not created in me by the law, nor can it be bound or loosed by it. That is simple enough, and sweet enough, is it not? He takes the flower from the table. Here are flowers for you: I have the tickets: we will ask your husband to lend us the carriage to show that there is no malice, no grudge, between us. Come!
She | Spiritlessly, taking the flowers without looking at them, and temporizing. Teddy isn’t in yet.
He | Well, let us take that calmly. Let us go to the theatre as if nothing had happened, and tell him when we come back. Now or three hours hence: today or tomorrow: what does it matter, provided all is done in honor, without shame or fear?
She | What did you get tickets for? Lohengrin?
He | I tried; but Lohengrin was sold out for tonight. He takes out two Court Theatre tickets.
She | Then what did you get?
He | Can you ask me? What is there besides Lohengrin that we two could endure, except Candida?
She | Springing up. Candida! No, I won’t go to it again, Henry Tossing the flower on the piano. It is that play that has done all the mischief. I’m very sorry I ever saw it: it ought to be stopped.
He | Amazed. Aurora!
She | Yes: I mean it.
He | That divinest love poem! the poem that gave us courage to speak to one another! that revealed to us what we really felt for one another! That—
She | Just so. It put a lot of stuff into my head that I should never have dreamt of for myself. I imagined myself just like Candida.
He | Catching her hands and looking earnestly at her. You were right. You are like Candida.
She | Snatching her hands away. Oh, stuff! And I thought you were just like Eugene. Looking critically at him. Now that I come to look at you, you are rather like him, too. She throws herself discontentedly into the nearest seat, which happens to be the bench at the piano. He goes to her.
He | Very earnestly. Aurora: if Candida had loved Eugene she would have gone out into the night with him without a moment’s hesitation.
She | With equal earnestness. Henry: do you know what’s wanting in that play?
He | There is nothing wanting in it.
She | Yes there is. There’s a Georgina wanting in it. If Georgina had been there to make trouble, that play would have been a true-to-life tragedy. Now I’ll tell you something about it that I have never told you before.
He | What is that?
She | I took Teddy to it. I thought it would do him good; and so it would if I could only have kept him awake. Georgina came too; and you should have heard the way she went on about it. She said it was downright immoral, and that she knew the sort of woman that encourages boys to sit on the hearthrug and make love to her. She was just preparing Teddy’s mind to poison it about me.
He | Let us be just to Georgina, dearest
She | Let her deserve it first. Just to Georgina, indeed!
He | She really sees the world in that way. That is her punishment.
She | How can it be her punishment when she likes it? It’ll be my punishment when she brings that budget of poems to Teddy. I wish you’d have some sense, and sympathize with my position a little.
He | Going away from the piano and beginning to walk about rather testily. My dear: I really don’t care about Georgina or about Teddy. All these squabbles belong to a plane on which I am, as you say, no use. I have counted the cost; and I do not fear the consequences. After all, what is there to fear? Where is the difficulty? What can Georgina do? What can your husband do? What can anybody do?
She | Do you mean to say that you propose that we should walk right bang up to Teddy and tell him we’re going away together?
He | Yes. What can be simpler?
She | And do you think for a moment he’d stand it, like that half-baked clergyman in the play? He’d just kill you.
He | Coming to a sudden stop and speaking with considerable confidence. You don’t understand these things, my darling, how could you? In one respect I am unlike the poet in the play. I have followed the Greek ideal and not neglected the culture of my body. Your husband would make a tolerable second-rate heavy weight if he were in training and ten years younger. As it is, he could, if strung up to a great effort by a burst of passion, give a good account of himself for perhaps fifteen seconds. But I am active enough to keep out of his reach for fifteen seconds; and after that I should be simply all over him.
She | Rising and coming to him in consternation. What do you mean by all over him?
He | Gently. Don’t ask me, dearest. At all events, I swear to you that you need not be anxious about me.
She | And what about Teddy? Do you mean to tell me that you are going to beat Teddy before my face like a brutal prizefighter?
He | All this alarm is needless, dearest. Believe me, nothing will happen. Your husband knows that I am capable of defending myself. Under such circumstances nothing ever does happen. And of course I shall do nothing. The man who once loved you is sacred to me.
She | Suspiciously. Doesn’t he love me still? Has he told you anything?
He | No, no. He takes her tenderly in his arms. Dearest, dearest: how agitated you are! how unlike yourself! All these worries belong to the lower plane. Come up with me to the higher one. The heights, the solitudes, the soul world!
She | Avoiding his gaze. No: stop: it’s no use, Mr. Apjohn.
He | Recoiling. Mr. Apjohn!!!
She | Excuse me: I meant Henry, of course.
He | How could you even think of me as Mr. Apjohn? I never think of you as Mrs. Bompas: it is always Cand—I mean Aurora, Aurora, Auro—
She | Yes, yes: that’s all very well, Mr. Apjohn he is about to interrupt again: but she won’t have it no: it’s no use: I’ve suddenly begun to think of you as Mr. Apjohn; and it’s ridiculous to go on calling you Henry. I thought you were only a boy, a child, a dreamer. I thought you would be too much afraid to do anything. And now you want to beat Teddy and to break up my home and disgrace me and make a horrible scandal in the papers. It’s cruel, unmanly, cowardly.
He | With grave wonder. Are you afraid?
She | Oh, of course I’m afraid. So would you be if you had any common sense. She goes to the hearth, turning her back to him, and puts one tapping foot on the fender.
He | Watching her with great gravity. Perfect love casteth out fear. That is why I am not afraid. Mrs. Bompas: you do not love me.
She | Turning to him with a gasp of relief. Oh, thank you, thank you! You really can be very nice, Henry.
He | Why do you thank me?
She | Coming prettily to him from the fireplace. For calling me Mrs. Bompas again. I feel now that you are going to be reasonable and behave like a gentleman. He drops on the stool; covers his face with his hand; and groans. What’s the matter?
He | Once or twice in my life I have dreamed that I was exquisitely happy and blessed. But oh! the misgiving at the first stir of consciousness! the stab of reality! the prison walls of the bedroom! the bitter, bitter disappointment of waking! And this time! oh, this time I thought I was awake.
She | Listen to me, Henry: we really haven’t time for all that sort of flapdoodle now. He starts to his feet as if she had pulled a trigger and straightened him by the release of a powerful spring, and goes past her with set teeth to the little table. Oh, take care: you nearly hit me in the chin with the top of your head.
He | With fierce politeness. I beg your pardon. What is it you want me to do? I am at your service. I am ready to behave like a gentleman if you will be kind enough to explain exactly how.
She | A little frightened. Thank you, Henry: I was sure you would. You’re not angry with me, are you?
He | Go on. Go on quickly. Give me something to think about, or I will—I will—He suddenly snatches up her fan and it about to break it in his clenched fists.
She | Running forward and catching at the fan, with loud lamentation. Don’t break my fan—no, don’t. He slowly relaxes his grip of it as she draws it anxiously out of his hands. No, really, that’s a stupid trick. I don’t like that. You’ve no right to do that. She opens the fan, and finds that the sticks are disconnected. Oh, how could you be so inconsiderate?
He | I beg your pardon. I will buy you a new one.
She | Querulously. You will never be able to match it. And it was a particular favorite of mine.
He | Shortly. Then you will have to do without it: that’s all.
She | That’s not a very nice thing to say after breaking my pet fan, I think.
He | If you knew how near I was to breaking Teddy’s pet wife and presenting him with the pieces, you would be thankful that you are alive instead of—of—of howling about five shillings worth of ivory. Damn your fan!
She | Oh! Don’t you dare swear in my presence. One would think you were my husband.
He | Again collapsing on the stool. This is some horrible dream. What has become of you? You are not my Aurora.
She | Oh, well, if you come to that, what has become of you? Do you think I would ever have encouraged you if I had known you were such a little devil?
He | Don’t drag me down—don’t—don’t. Help me to find the way back to the heights.
She | Kneeling beside him and pleading. If you would only be reasonable, Henry. If you would only remember that I am on the brink of ruin, and not go on calmly saying it’s all quite simple.
He | It seems so to me.
She | Jumping up distractedly. If you say that again I shall do something I’ll be sorry for. Here we are, standing on the edge of a frightful precipice. No doubt it’s quite simple to go over and have done with it. But can’t you suggest anything more agreeable?
He | I can suggest nothing now. A chill black darkness has fallen: I can see nothing but the ruins of our dream. He rises with a deep sigh.
She | Can’t you? Well, I can. I can see Georgina rubbing those poems into Teddy. Facing him determinedly. And I tell you, Henry Apjohn, that you got me into this mess; and you must get me out of it again.
He | Polite and hopeless. All I can say is that I am entirely at your service. What do you wish me to do?
She | Do you know anybody else named Aurora?
He | No.
She | There’s no use in saying No in that frozen pigheaded way. You must know some Aurora or other somewhere.
He | You said you were the only Aurora in the world. And lifting his clasped fists with a sudden return of his emotion oh God! you were the only Aurora in the world to me. He turns away from her, hiding his face.
She | Petting him. Yes, yes, dear: of course. It’s very nice of you; and I appreciate it: indeed I do; but it’s not reasonable just at present. Now just listen to me. I suppose you know all those poems by heart.
He | Yes, by heart. Raising his head and looking at her, with a sudden suspicion. Don’t you?
She | Well, I never can remember verses; and besides, I’ve been so busy that I’ve not had time to read them all; though I intend to the very first moment I can get: I promise you that most faithfully, Henry. But now try and remember very particularly. Does the name of Bompas occur in any of the poems?
He | Indignantly. No.
She | You’re quite sure?
He | Of course I am quite sure. How could I use such a name in a poem?
She | Well, I don’t see why not. It rhymes to rumpus, which seems appropriate enough at present, goodness knows! However, you’re a poet, and you ought to know.
He | What does it matter—now?
She | It matters a lot, I can tell you. If there’s nothing about Bompas in the poems, we can say that they were written to some other Aurora, and that you showed them to me because my name was Aurora too. So you’ve got to invent another Aurora for the occasion.
He | Very coldly. Oh, if you wish me to tell a lie—
She | Surely, as a man of honor—as a gentleman, you wouldn’t tell the truth, would you?
He | Very well. You have broken my spirit and desecrated my dreams. I will lie and protest and stand on my honor: oh, I will play the gentleman, never fear.
She | Yes, put it all on me, of course. Don’t be mean, Henry.
He | Rousing himself with an effort. You are quite right, Mrs. Bompas: I beg your pardon. You must excuse my temper. I have got growing pains, I think.
She | Growing pains!
He | The process of growing from romantic boyhood into cynical maturity usually takes fifteen years. When it is compressed into fifteen minutes, the pace is too fast; and growing pains are the result.
She | Oh, is this a time for cleverness? It’s settled, isn’t it, that you’re going to be nice and good, and that you’ll brazen it out to Teddy that you have some other Aurora?
He | Yes: I’m capable of anything now. I should not have told him the truth by halves; and now I will not lie by halves. I’ll wallow in the honor of a gentleman.
She | Dearest boy, I knew you would. I—Sh! She rushes to the door, and holds it ajar, listening breathlessly.
He | What is it?
She | White with apprehension. It’s Teddy: I hear him tapping the new barometer. He can’t have anything serious on his mind or he wouldn’t do that. Perhaps Georgina hasn’t said anything. She steals back to the hearth. Try and look as if there was nothing the matter. Give me my gloves, quick. He hands them to her. She pulls on one hastily and begins buttoning it with ostentatious unconcern. Go further away from me, quick. He walks doggedly away from her until the piano prevents his going farther. If I button my glove, and you were to hum a tune, don’t you think that—
He | The tableau would be complete in its guiltiness. For Heaven’s sake, Mrs. Bompas, let that glove alone: you look like a pickpocket.
Her Husband comes in: a robust, thicknecked, well groomed city man, with a strong chin but a blithering eye and credulous mouth. He has a momentous air, but shows no sign of displeasure: rather the contrary.
Her Husband | Hallo! I thought you two were at the theatre.
She | I felt anxious about you, Teddy. Why didn’t you come home to dinner?
Her Husband | I got a message from Georgina. She wanted me to go to her.
She | Poor dear Georgina! I’m sorry I haven’t been able to call on her this last week. I hope there’s nothing the matter with her.
Her Husband | Nothing, except anxiety for my welfare and yours. She steals a terrified look at Henry. By, the way, Apjohn, I should like a word with you this evening, if Aurora can spare you for a moment.
He | Formally. I am at your service.
Her Husband | No hurry. After the theatre will do.
He | We have decided not to go.
Her Husband | Indeed! Well, then, shall we adjourn to my snuggery?
She | You needn’t move. I shall go and lock up my diamonds since I’m not going to the theatre. Give me my things.
Her Husband | As he hands her the cloud and the mirror. Well, we shall have more room here.
He | Looking about him and shaking his shoulders loose. I think I should prefer plenty of room.
Her Husband | So, if it’s not disturbing you, Rory—?
She | Not at all. She goes out.
When the two men are alone together, Bompas deliberately takes the poems from his breast pocket; looks at them reflectively; then looks at Henry, mutely inviting his attention. Henry refuses to understand, doing his best to look unconcerned.
Her Husband | Do these manuscripts seem at all familiar to you, may I ask?
He | Manuscripts?
Her Husband | Yes. Would you like to look at them a little closer? He proffers them under Henry’s nose.
He | As with a sudden illumination of glad surprise. Why, these are my poems.
Her Husband | So I gather.
He | What a shame! Mrs. Bompas has shown them to you! You must think me an utter ass. I wrote them years ago after reading Swinburne’s Songs Before Sunrise. Nothing would do me then but I must reel off a set of Songs to the Sunrise. Aurora, you know: the rosy fingered Aurora. They’re all about Aurora. When Mrs. Bompas told me her name was Aurora, I couldn’t resist the temptation to lend them to her to read. But I didn’t bargain for your unsympathetic eyes.
Her Husband | Grinning. Apjohn: that’s really very ready of you. You are cut out for literature; and the day will come when Rory and I will be proud to have you about the house. I have heard far thinner stories from much older men.
He | With an air of great surprise. Do you mean to imply that you don’t believe me?
Her Husband | Do you expect me to believe you?
He | Why not? I don’t understand.
Her Husband | Come! Don’t underrate your own cleverness, Apjohn. I think you understand pretty well.
He | I assure you I am quite at a loss. Can you not be a little more explicit?
Her Husband | Don’t overdo it, old chap. However, I will just be so far explicit as to say that if you think these poems read as if they were addressed, not to a live woman, but to a shivering cold time of day at which you were never out of bed in your life, you hardly do justice to your own literary powers—which I admire and appreciate, mind you, as much as any man. Come! own up. You wrote those poems to my wife. An internal struggle prevents Henry from answering. Of course you did. He throws the poems on the table; and goes to the hearthrug, where he plants himself solidly, chuckling a little and waiting for the next move.
He | Formally and carefully. Mr. Bompas: I pledge you my word you are mistaken. I need not tell you that Mrs. Bompas is a lady of stainless honor, who has never cast an unworthy thought on me. The fact that she has shown you my poems—
Her Husband | That’s not a fact. I came by them without her knowledge. She didn’t show them to me.
He | Does not that prove their perfect innocence? She would have shown them to you at once if she had taken your quite unfounded view of them.
Her Husband | Shaken. Apjohn: play fair. Don’t abuse your intellectual gifts. Do you really mean that I am making a fool of myself?
He | Earnestly. Believe me, you are. I assure you, on my honor as a gentleman, that I have never had the slightest feeling for Mrs. Bompas beyond the ordinary esteem and regard of a pleasant acquaintance.
Her Husband | Shortly, showing ill humor for the first time. Oh, indeed. He leaves his hearth and begins to approach Henry slowly, looking him up and down with growing resentment.
He | Hastening to improve the impression made by his mendacity. I should never have dreamt of writing poems to her. The thing is absurd.
Her Husband | Reddening ominously. Why is it absurd?
He | Shrugging his shoulders. Well, it happens that I do not admire Mrs. Bompas—in that way.
Her Husband | Breaking out in Henry’s face. Let me tell you that Mrs. Bompas has been admired by better men than you, you soapy headed little puppy, you.
He | Much taken aback. There is no need to insult me like this. I assure you, on my honor as a—
Her Husband | Too angry to tolerate a reply, and boring Henry more and more towards the piano. You don’t admire Mrs. Bompas! You would never dream of writing poems to Mrs. Bompas! My wife’s not good enough for you, isn’t she. Fiercely. Who are you, pray, that you should be so jolly superior?
He | Mr. Bompas: I can make allowances for your jealousy—
Her Husband | Jealousy! do you suppose I’m jealous of YOU? No, nor of ten like you. But if you think I’ll stand here and let you insult my wife in her own house, you’re mistaken.
He | Very uncomfortable with his back against the piano and Teddy standing over him threateningly. How can I convince you? Be reasonable. I tell you my relations with Mrs. Bompas are relations of perfect coldness—of indifference—
Her Husband | Scornfully. Say it again: say it again. You’re proud of it, aren’t you? Yah! You’re not worth kicking.
Henry suddenly executes the feat known to pugilists as dipping, and changes sides with Teddy, who it now between Henry and the piano.
He | Look here: I’m not going to stand this.
Her Husband | Oh, you have some blood in your body after all! Good job!
He | This is ridiculous. I assure you Mrs. Bompas is quite—
Her Husband | What is Mrs. Bompas to you, I’d like to know. I’ll tell you what Mrs. Bompas is. She’s the smartest woman in the smartest set in South Kensington, and the handsomest, and the cleverest, and the most fetching to experienced men who know a good thing when they see it, whatever she may be to conceited penny-a-lining puppies who think nothing good enough for them. It’s admitted by the best people; and not to know it argues yourself unknown. Three of our first actor-managers have offered her a hundred a week if she’d go on the stage when they start a repertory theatre; and I think they know what they’re about as well as you. The only member of the present Cabinet that you might call a handsome man has neglected the business of the country to dance with her, though he don’t belong to our set as a regular thing. One of the first professional poets in Bedford Park wrote a sonnet to her, worth all your amateur trash. At Ascot last season the eldest son of a duke excused himself from calling on me on the ground that his feelings for Mrs. Bompas were not consistent with his duty to me as host; and it did him honor and me too. But with gathering fury she isn’t good enough for you, it seems. You regard her with coldness, with indifference; and you have the cool cheek to tell me so to my face. For two pins I’d flatten your nose in to teach you manners. Introducing a fine woman to you is casting pearls before swine yelling at him before SWINE! d’ye hear?
He | With a deplorable lack of polish. You call me a swine again and I’ll land you one on the chin that’ll make your head sing for a week.
Her Husband | Exploding. What—!
He charges at Henry with bull-like fury. Henry places himself on guard in the manner of a well taught boxer, and gets away smartly, but unfortunately forgets the stool which is just behind him. He falls backwards over it, unintentionally pushing it against the shins of Bompas, who falls forward over it. Mrs. Bompas, with a scream, rushes into the room between the sprawling champions, and sits down on the floor in order to get her right arm round Her Husband’s neck.
She | You shan’t, Teddy: you shan’t. You will be killed: he is a prizefighter.
Her Husband | Vengefully. I’ll prizefight him. He struggles vainly to free himself from her embrace.
She | Henry: don’t let him fight you. Promise me that you won’t.
He | Ruefully. I have got a most frightful bump on the back of my head. He tries to rise.
She | Reaching out her left hand to seize his coat tail, and pulling him down again, whilst keeping fast hold of Teddy with the other hand. Not until you have promised: not until you both have promised. Teddy tries to rise: she pulls him back again. Teddy: you promise, don’t you? Yes, yes. Be good: you promise.
Her Husband | I won’t, unless he takes it back.
She | He will: he does. You take it back, Henry?—yes.
He | Savagely. Yes. I take it back. She lets go his coat. He gets up. So does Teddy. I take it all back, all, without reserve.
She | On the carpet. Is nobody going to help me up? They each take a hand and pull her up. Now won’t you shake hands and be good?
He | Recklessly. I shall do nothing of the sort. I have steeped myself in lies for your sake; and the only reward I get is a lump on the back of my head the size of an apple. Now I will go back to the straight path.
She | Henry: for Heaven’s sake—
He | It’s no use. Your husband is a fool and a brute—
Her Husband | What’s that you say?
He | I say you are a fool and a brute; and if you’ll step outside with me I’ll say it again. Teddy begins to take off his coat for combat. Those poems were written to your wife, every word of them, and to nobody else. The scowl clears away from Bompas’s countenance. Radiant, he replaces his coat. I wrote them because I loved her. I thought her the most beautiful woman in the world; and I told her so over and over again. I adored her: do you hear? I told her that you were a sordid commercial chump, utterly unworthy of her; and so you are.
Her Husband | So gratified, he can hardly believe his ears. You don’t mean it!
He | Yes, I do mean it, and a lot more too. I asked Mrs. Bompas to walk out of the house with me—to leave you—to get divorced from you and marry me. I begged and implored her to do it this very night. It was her refusal that ended everything between us. Looking very disparagingly at him. What she can see in you, goodness only knows!
Her Husband | Beaming with remorse. My dear chap, why didn’t you say so before? I apologize. Come! Don’t bear malice: shake hands. Make him shake hands, Rory.
She | For my sake, Henry. After all, he’s my husband. Forgive him. Take his hand. Henry, dazed, lets her take his hand and place it in Teddy’s.
Her Husband | Shaking it heartily. You’ve got to own that none of your literary heroines can touch my Rory. He turns to her and claps her with fond pride on the shoulder. Eh, Rory? They can’t resist you: none of em. Never knew a man yet that could hold out three days.
She | Don’t be foolish, Teddy. I hope you were not really hurt, Henry. She feels the back of his head. He flinches. Oh, poor boy, what a bump! I must get some vinegar and brown paper. She goes to the bell and rings.
Her Husband | Will you do me a great favor, Apjohn. I hardly like to ask; but it would be a real kindness to us both.
He | What can I do?
Her Husband | Taking up the poems. Well, may I get these printed? It shall be done in the best style. The finest paper, sumptuous binding, everything first class. They’re beautiful poems. I should like to show them about a bit.
She | Running back from the bell, delighted with the idea, and coming between them. Oh Henry, if you wouldn’t mind!
He | Oh, I don’t mind. I am past minding anything. I have grown too fast this evening.
She | How old are you, Henry?
He | This morning I was eighteen. Now I am—confound it! I’m quoting that beast of a play. He takes the Candida tickets out of his pocket and tears them up viciously.
Her Husband | What shall we call the volume? To Aurora, or something like that, eh?
He | I should call it How He Lied to Her Husband.

Passion, Poison, and Petrifaction

Or, The Fatal Gazogene

A Brief Tragedy for Barns and Booths

Dramatis Personae

Character, a character

Scene: A scene.

Passion, Poison and Petrifaction

In a bed-sitting room in a fashionable quarter of London a lady sits at her dressing-table, with her maid combing her hair. It is late; and the electric lamps are glowing. Apparently the room is bedless, but there stands against the opposite wall to that at which the dressing-table is placed a piece of furniture that suggests a bookcase without carrying conviction. On the same side is a chest of drawers of that disastrous kind which, recalcitrant to the opener until she is provoked to violence, then suddenly come wholly out and defy all her efforts to fit them in again. Opposite this chest of drawers, on the lady’s side of the room, is a cupboard. The presence of a row of gentleman’s boots beside the chest of drawers proclaims that the lady is married. Her own boots are beside the cupboard. The third wall is pierced midway by the door, above which is a cuckoo clock. Near the door a pedestal bears a portrait bust of the lady in plaster. There is a fan on the dressing-table, a hatbox and rug strap on the chest of drawers, an umbrella and a bootjack against the wall near the bed. The general impression is one of brightness, beauty, and social ambition, damped by somewhat inadequate means. A certain air of theatricality is produced by the fact that though the room is rectangular it has only three walls. Not a sound is heard except the overture and the crackling of the lady’s hair as the maid’s brush draws electric sparks from it in the dry air of the London midsummer. The cuckoo clock strikes sixteen.

The Lady | How much did the clock strike, Phyllis?
Phyllis | Sixteen, my lady.
The Lady | That means eleven o’clock, does it not?
Phyllis | Eleven at night, my lady. In the morning it means half-past two; so if you hear it strike sixteen during your slumbers, do not rise.
The Lady | I will not, Phyllis. Phyllis: I am weary. I will go to bed. Prepare my couch.
Phyllis crosses the room to the bookcase and touches a button. The front of the bookcase falls out with a crash and becomes a bed. A roll of distant thunder echoes the crash.
Phyllis | Shuddering. It is a terrible night Heaven help all poor mariners at sea! My master is late. I trust nothing has happened to him. Your bed is ready, my lady.
The Lady | Thank you, Phyllis. She rises and approaches the bed. Goodnight.
Phyllis | Will your ladyship not undress?
The Lady | Not tonight, Phyllis. Glancing through where the fourth wall is missing. Not under the circumstances.
Phyllis | Impulsively throwing herself on her knees by her mistress’s side, and clasping her round the waist. Oh, my beloved mistress, I know not why or how; but I feel that I shall never see you alive again. There is murder in the air. Thunder. Hark!
The Lady | Strange! As I sat there methought I heard angels singing. “Oh, wont you come home. Bill Bailey?” Why should angels call me Bill Bailey? My name is Magnesia Fitztollemache.
Phyllis | Emphasizing the title. Lady Magnesia Fitztollemache.
Lady Magnesia | In case we should never again meet in this world, let us take a last farewell.
Phyllis | Embracing her with tears. My poor murdered angel mistress!
Lady Magnesia | In case we should meet again, call me at half-past eleven.
Phyllis | I will, I will.
Phyllis withdraws, overcome by emotion. Lady Magnesia switches off the electric light, and immediately hears the angels quite distinctly. They sing Bill Bailey so sweetly that she can attend to nothing else and forgets to remove even her boots as she draws the coverlet over herself and sinks to sleep, lulled by celestial harmony. A white radiance plays on her pillow, and lights up her beautiful face. But the thunder growls again, and a lurid red glow concentrates itself on the door, which is presently flung open, revealing a saturnine figure in evening dress, partially concealed by a crimson cloak. As he steals towards the bed the unnatural glare in his eyes and the broad-bladed dagger nervously gripped in his right hand bode ill for the sleeping lady. Providentially she sneezes on the very brink of eternity, and the tension of the murderer’s nerves is such that he bolts precipitately under the bed at the sudden and startling Atscha! A dull, heavy, rhythmic thumping—the beating of his heart—betrays his whereabouts. Soon he emerges cautiously and raises his head above the bed coverlet level.
The Murderer | I can no longer cower here listening to the agonized thumpings of my own heart She but snoze in her sleep. I’ll do’t. He again raises the dagger. The angels sing again. He cowers. What is this? Has that tune reached Heaven?
Lady Magnesia | Waking and sitting up. My husband! All the colors of the rainbow chase one another up his face with ghastly brilliancy. Why do you change color? And what on earth are you doing with that dagger?
Fitz | Affecting unconcern, hut unhinged. It is a present for you: a present from mother. Pretty. Isnt it? He displays it fatuously.
Lady Magnesia | But she promised me a fish slice.
Fitz | This is a combination fish slice and dagger. One day you have salmon for dinner. The next you have a murder to commit. See?
Lady Magnesia | My sweet mother-in-law! Someone knocks at the door. That is Adolphus’s knock. Fitz’s face turns a dazzling green. What has happened to your complexion? You have turned green. Now I think of it, you always do when Adolphus is mentioned. Arnt you going to let him in?
Fitz | Certainly not. He goes to the door. Adolphus: you cannot enter. My wife is undressed and in bed.
Lady Magnesia | Rising. I am not Come in, Adolphus. She switches on the electric light.
Adolphus | Without. Something most important has happened. I must come in for a moment.
Fitz | Calling to Adolphus Something important happened? What is it?
Adolphus | Without. My new clothes have come home.
Fitz | He says his new clothes have come home.
Lady Magnesia | Running to the door and opening it. Oh, come in, come in. Let me see.
Adolphus Bastable enters. He is in evening dress, made in the latest fashion, with the right half of the coat and the left half of the trousers yellow and the other halves black. His silver-spangled waistcoat has a crimson handkerchief stuck between it and his shirt front.
Adolphus | What do you think of it?
Lady Magnesia | It is a dream! a creation! She turns him about to admire him.
Adolphus | Proudly. I shall never be mistaken for a waiter again.
Fitz | A drink, Adolphus?
Adolphus | Thanks.
Fitztollemache goes to the cupboard and takes out a tray with tumblers and a bottle of whisky. He puts them an the dressing-table.
Fitz | Is the gazogene full?
Lady Magnesia | Yes: you put in the powders yourself today.
Fitz | Sardonically. So I did. The special powders! Hal ha! ha! ha! ha! His face Is again strangely variegated.
Lady Magnesia | Your complexion is really going to pieces. Why do you laugh in that silly way at nothing?
Fitz | Nothing! Ha, ha! Nothing! Ha, ha, ha!
Adolphus | I hope, Mr. Fitztollemache, you are not laughing at my dothes. I warn you that I am an Englishman. You may laugh at my manners, at my brains, at my national institutions; but if you laugh at my clothes, one of us must die.
Thunder.
Fitz | I laughed but at the irony of Fate. He takes a gazogene from the cupboard.
Adolphus | Satisfied. Oh, that! Oh, yes, of course!
Fitz | Let us drown all unkindness in a loving cup. He puts the gazogene on the floor in the middle of the room. Pardon the absence of a table: we found it in the way and pawned it. He takes the whisky bottle from the dressing-table.
Lady Magnesia | We picnic at home now. It is delightful. She takes three tumblers from the dressing-table and sits on the floor, presiding over the gazogene, with Fitz and Adolphus squatting on her left and right respectively. Fitz pours whisky into the tumblers.
Fitz | As Magnesia is about to squirt soda into his tumbler. Stay! No soda for me. Let Adolphus have it all—all. I will take mine neat.
Lady Magnesia | Proffering tumbler to Adolphus Pledge me, Adolphus.
Fitz | Kiss the cup, Magnesia. Pledge her, man. Drink deep.
Adolphus | To Magnesia!
Fitz | To Magnesia! The two men drink. It is done. Scrambling to his feet. Adolphus: you have but ten minutes to live—if so long.
Adolphus | What mean you?
Magnesia | Rising. My mind misgives me. I have a strange feeling here. Touching her heart.
Adolphus | So have I, but lower down. Touching his stomach. That gazogene is disagreeing with me.
Fitz | It was poisoned!
Sensation.
Adolphus | Rising. Help! Police!
Fitz | Dastard! you would appeal to the law! Can you not die like a gentleman?
Adolphus | But so young! when I have only worn my new clothes once.
Magnesia | It is too horrible. To Fitz Fiend! what drove you to this wicked deed?
Fitz | Jealousy. You admired his clothes: you did not admire mine.
Adolphus | My clothes His face lights up with heavenly radiance. Have I indeed been found worthy to be the first clothes-martyr? Welcome, death! Hark! angels call me. The celestial choir again raises its favorite chant. He listens with a rapt expression. Suddenly the angels sing out of tune, and the radiance on the poisoned man’s face turns a sickly green. Yah—ah! Oh—ahoo! The gazogene is disagreeing extremely. Oh! He throws himself on the bed, writhing.
Magnesia | To Fitz. Monster: what have you done? She points to the distorted figure on the bed. That was once a Man, beautiful and glorious. What have you made of it? A writhing, agonized,miserable, moribund worm.
Adolphus | In a tone of the strongest remonstrance. Oh, I say! Oh, come! No: look here. Magnesia! Really!
Magnesia | Oh, is this a time for petty vanity? Think of your misspent life—
Adolphus | Much injured. Whose misspent life?
Magnesia | Continuing relentlessly. Look into your conscience: look into your stomach. Adolphus collapses in hideous spasms. She turns to Fitz. And this is your handiwork!
Fitz | Mine is a passionate nature. Magnesia. I must have your undivided love. I must have your love: do you hear? LOVE! LOVE!! LOVE!!! LOVE!!!! LOVE!!!!! He raves, accompanied by a fresh paroxysm from the victim on the bed.
Magnesia | With sudden resolution. You shall have it.
Fitz | Enraptured. Magnesia! I have recovered your love! Oh, how slight appears the sacrifice of this man compared to so glorious a reward! I would poison ten men without a thought of self to gain one smile from you.
Adolphus | In a broken voice. Farewell, Magnesia: my last hour is at hand. Farewell, farewell, farewell!
Magnesia | At this supreme moment, George Fitztollemache, I solemnly dedicate to you all that I formerly dedicated to poor Adolphus.
Adolphus | Oh, please not poor Adolphus yet. I still live, you know.
Magnesia | The vital spark but flashes before it vanishes. Adolphus groans. And now, Adolphus, take this last comfort from the unhappy Magnesia Fitztollemache. As I have dedicated to George all that I gave to you, so I will bury in your grave—or in your urn if you are cremated—all that I gave to him.
Fitz | I hardly follow this.
Magnesia | I will explain. George: hitherto I have given Adolphus all the romance of my nature—all my love—all my dreams—all my caresses. Henceforth they are yours!
Fitz | Angel!
Magnesia | Adolphus: forgive me if this pains you.
Adolphus | Dont mention it I hardly feel it The gazogene is so much worse. Taken bad again. Oh!
Magnesia | Peace, poor sufferer: there is still some balm. You are about to hear what I am going to dedicate to you.
Adolphus | All I ask is a peppermint lozenge, for mercy’s sake.
Magnesia | I have something far better than any lozenge: the devotion of a lifetime. Formerly it was George’s. I kept his house, or rather, his lodgings. I mended his clothes. I darned his socks. I bought his food. I interviewed his creditors. I stood between him and the servants. I administered his domestic finances. When his hair needed cutting or his countenance was imperfectly washed, I pointed it out to him. The trouble that all this gave me made him prosaic in my eyes. Familiarity bred contempt Now all that shall end. My husband shall be my hero, my lover, my perfect knight He shall shield me from all care and trouble. He shall ask nothing in return but love—boundless, priceless, rapturous, soul-enthralling love. Love! LOVE! LOVE! She raves and flings her arms about Fitz. And the duties I formerly discharged shall be replaced by the one supreme duty of duties: the duty of weeping at Adolphus’s tomb.
Fitz | Reflectively. My ownest, this sacrifice makes me feel that I have perhaps been a little selfish. I cannot help feeling that there is much to be said for the old arrangement Why should Adolphus die for my sake?
Adolphus | I am not dying for your sake, Fitz. I am dying because you poisoned me.
Magnesia | You do not fear to die, Adolphus, do you?
Adolphus | N-n-no, I dont exactly fear to die. Still—
Fitz | Still, if an antidote—
Adolphus | Bounding from the bed. Antidote!
Magnesia | With wild hope. Antidote!
Fitz | If an antidote would not be too much of an anticlimax.
Adolphus | Anticlimax be blowed! Do you think I am going to die to please the critics? Out with your antidote. Quick!
Fitz | The best antidote to the poison I have given you is lime, plenty of lime.
Adolphus | Lime! You mock me! Do you think I carry lime about in my pockets?
Fitz | There is the plaster ceiling.
Magnesia | Yes, the ceiling. Saved, saved, saved!
All three frantically shy boots at the ceiling. Flakes of plaster rain down which Adolphus devours, at first ravenously, then with a marked falling off in relish.
Magnesia | Picking up a huge slice. Take this, Adolphus: it is the largest. She crams it into his mouth.
Fitz | Ha! a lump off the cornice! Try this.
Adolphus | Desperately. Stop! stop!
Magnesia | Do not stop. You will die. She tries to stuff him again.
Adolphus | Resolutely. I prefer death.
Magnesia and Fitz | Throwing themselves on their knees on either side of him. For our sakes, Adolphus, persevere.
Adolphus | No: unless you can supply lime in liquid form, I must perish. Finish that ceiling I cannot and will not.
Magnesia | I have a thought—an inspiration. My bust She snatches it from its pedestal and brings it to him.
Adolphus | Gazing fondly at it. Can I resist it?
Fitz | Try the bun.
Adolphus | Gnawing the knot of hair at the back of the bust’s head: it makes him ill. Yah, I cannot. I cannot. Not even your bust, Magnesia. Do not ask me. Let me die.
Fitz | Pressing the bust on him. Force yourself to take a mouthful. Down with it, Adolphus!
Adolphus | Useless. It would not stay down. Water! Some fluid! Ring for something to drink He chokes. MAGNESIA. I will save you She rushes to the bell and rings.
Phyllis, in her nightgown, with her hair prettify made up into a chevaux defrise of crocuses with pink and yellow curlpapers, rushes in straight to Magnesia.
Phyllis | Hysterically. My beloved mistress, once more we meet She sees Fitztollemache and screams. Ah! ah! ah! A man! She sees Adolphus Men!! She flies, but Fitztollemache seizes her by the nightgown just as she is escaping. Unhand me, villain!
Fitz | This is no time for prudery, girl. Mr. Bastable is dying.
Phyllis | With concern. Indeed, sir? I hope he will not think it unfeeling of me to appear at his deathbed in curl papers.
Magnesia | We know you have a good heart, Phyllis. Take this giving her the bust; dissolve it in a jug of hot water; and bring it back instantly. Mr. Bastable’s life depends on your haste.
Phyllis | Hesitating. It do seem a pity, dont it, my lady, to spoil your lovely bust?
Adolphus | Tush! This craze for fine art is beyond alt bounds. Off with you [he pushes her out]. Drink, drink, drink! My entrails are parched. Drink! He rushes deliriously to the gazogene.
Fitz | Rushing after him. Madman, you forget! It is poisoned!
Adolphus | I dont care. Drink, drink! They wrestle madly for the gazogene. In the struggle they squirt all its contents away, mostly into one another’s face. Adolphus at last flings Fitztollemache to the floor, and puts the spout into his mouth. Empty! empty! With a shriek of despair he collapses on the bed, clasping the gazogene like a baby, and weeping over it.
Fitz | Aside to Magnesia Magnesia: I have always pretended not to notice it; but you keep a siphon for your private use in my hatbox.
Magnesia | I use it for washing old lace; but no matter: he shall have it She produces a siphon from the hatbox, and offers a tumbler of soda-water to Adolphus.
Adolphus | Thanks, thanks, oh, thanks! He drinks. A terrific fizzing is heard. He starts up screaming. Help! help! The ceiling is effervescing! I am BURSTING! He wallows convulsively on the bed.
Fitz | Quick! the rug strap! They pack him with blankets and strap him. Is that tight enough?
Magnesia | Anxiously. Will you hold, do you think?
Adolphus | The peril is past The soda-water has gone flat.
Magnesia and Fitz | Thank heaven!
Phyllis returns with a washstand ewer, in which she has dissolved the bust.
Magnesia | Snatching it. At last!
Fitz | You are saved. Drain it to the dregs.
Fitztollemache holds the lip of the ewer to Adolphus’s mouth and gradually raises it until it stands upside down. Adolphus’s efforts to swallow it are fearful, Phyllis thumping his back when he chokes and Magnesia loosening the straps when he moans. At last, with a sigh of relief, he sinks back in the women’s arms. Fitz shakes the empty ewer upside down like a potman shaking the froth out of a flagon.
Adolphus | How inexpressibly soothing to the chest! A delicious numbness steals through all my members. I would sleep.
Magnesia—Fitz—Phyllis | Whispering together. Let him sleep.
He sleeps. Celestial harps are heard, but their chords cease on the abrupt entrance of the landlord, a vulgar person in pyjamas.
The Landlord | Eah! Eah! Wots this? Wots all this noise? Ah kin ennybody sleep through it? Looking at the floor and ceiling. Ellow! wot you bin doin te maw ceilin?
Fitz | Silence, or leave the room. If you wake that man he dies.
The Landlord | If e kin sleep through the noise you three mikes e kin sleep through ennythink.
Magnesia | Detestable vulgarian: your pronunciation jars on the finest chords of my nature. Begone!
The Landlord | Looking at Adolphus Aw downt blieve eze esleep. Aw blieve eze dead. Calling. Pleece! Pleecel Merder! A blue halo plays mysteriously on the door,which opens and reveals a policeman. Thunder. Eah, pleecmin: these three’s bin an murdered this gent between em, an naw tore moy ahse dahn.
The Policeman | Offended. Policeman, indeed! Wheres your manners?
Fitz | Officer—
The Policeman | With distinguished consideration. Sir?
Fitz | As between gentlemen—
The Policeman | Bowing. Sir: to you.
Fitz | Bowing. I may inform you that my friend had an acute attack of indigestion. No carbonate of soda being available, he swallowed a portion of this man’s ceiling. Pointing to Adolphus Behold the result!
The Policeman | The ceiling was poisoned! Well, of all the artful—He collars the landlord. I arrest you for wilful murder.
The Landlord | Appealing to the heavens. Ow, is this jesticel Ah could aw tell e wiz gowin te eat moy ceilin?
The Policeman | Releasing him. True. The case is more complicated than I thought He tries to lift Adolphus’s arm but cannot. Stiff already.
The Landlord | Trying to lift Adolphus’s leg. An’ precious evvy.Feeling the calf. Woy, eze gorn ez awd ez niles.
Fitz | Rushing to the bed. What is this?
Magnesia | Oh, say not he is dead. Phyllis: fetch a doctor. Phyllis runs out. They all try to lift Adolphus, but he is perfectly stiff, and as heavy as lead. Rouse him. Shake him.
The Policeman | Exhausted. Whew! Is he a man or a statue? Magnesia utters a piercing scream. Whats wrong, Miss?
Magnesia | To Fitz Do you not see what has happened?
Fitz | Striking his forehead. Horror on horror’s head!
The Landlord | Wotjemean?
Magnesia | The plaster has set inside him. The officer was right: he is indeed a living statue.
Magnesia flings herself on the stony breast of Adolphus. Fitztollemache buries his head in his hands, and his chest heaves convulsively. The policeman takes a small volume from his pocket and consults it.
The Policeman | This case is not provided for in my book of instructions. It dont seem no use trying artificial respiration, do it? To the landlord Here! lend a hand, you. We’d best take him and set him up in Trafalgar Square.
The Landlord | Aushd pat im in the cestern an worsh it aht of im.
Phyllis comes back with a Doctor.
Phyllis | The medical man, my lady.
The Policeman | A poison case, sir.
The Doctor | Do you mean to say that an unqualified person! a layman! has dared to administer poison in my district?
The Policeman | Raising Magnesia tenderly. It looks like it. Hold up, my lady.
The Doctor | Not a moment must be lost The patient must be kept awake at all costs. Constant and violent motion is necessary. He snatches Magnesia from the policeman, and rushes her about the room.
Fitz | Stop! That is not the poisoned person!
The Doctor | It is you, then. Why did you not say so before?He seizes Fitztollemache and rushes him about.
The Landlord | Naow, naow, thet ynt im.
The Doctor | What, you! He pounces on the landlord and rushes him round.
The Landlord | Eah! chack it He trips the doctor up. Both fall. Jest owld this leoonatic, will you. Mister Horficer?
The Policeman | Dragging both of them to their feet. Come out of it, will you. You must all come with me to me station.
Thunder.
Magnesia | What! In this frightful storm!
The hail patters noisily on the window.
Phyllis | I think it’s raining.
The wind howls.
The Landlord | It’s thanderin and lawtnin.
Fitz | It’s dangerous.
The Policeman | Drawing his baton and whistle. If you wont come quietly, then—
He whistles. A fearful flash is followed by an appalling explosion of heaven’s artillery. A thunderbolt enters the room, and strikes the helmet of the devoted constable, whence it is attracted to the waistcoat of the doctor by the lancet in his pocket. Finally it leaps with fearful force on the landlord, who, being of a gross and spongy nature, absorbs the electric fluid at the cost of his life. The others look on horror-stricken as the three victims, after reeling, jostling, cannoning through a ghastly quadrille, at last sink inanimate on the carpet.
Magnesia | Listening at the doctor’s chest. Dead!
Fitz | Kneeling by the landlord, and raising his hand, which drops with a thud. Dead!
Phyllis | Seizing the looking-glass and holding it to the Policeman’s lips. Dead!
Fitz | Solemnly rising. The copper attracted the lightning.
Magnesia | Rising. After life’s fitful fever they sleep well. Phyllis: sweep them up.
Phyllis replaces the looking-glass on the dressing-table, takes up the fan, and fans the policeman, who rolls away like a leaf before the wind, to the wall. She disposes similarly of the landlord and doctor.
Phyllis | Will they be in your way if I leave them there until morning, my lady? Or shall I bring up the ashpan and take them away?
Magnesia | They will not disturb us. Goodnight, Phyllis.
Phyllis | Goodnight, my lady. Goodnight, sir. She retires.
Magnesia | And now, husband, let us perform our last sad duty to our friend. He has become his own monument. Let us erect him. He is heavy; but love can do much.
Fitz | A litte leverage will get him on his feet Give me my umbrella.
Magnesia | True.
She hands him the umbrella, and takes up the bootjack.They get them under Adolphus’s back, and prize him up on his feet.
Fitz | Thats done it! Whew!
Magnesia | Kneeling at the left hand of the statue. For ever and for ever, Adolphus.
Fitz | Kneeling at the right hand of the statue. The rest is silence.
The Angels sing Bill Bailey. The statue raises its hands in an attitude of blessing, and turns its limelit face to heaven as the curtain falls. National Anthem.
Attendants | In front. All out for the next performance. Pass along, please, ladies and gentlemen: pass along.

Passion, Poison, and Petrifaction

or, The Fatal Gazogene

A Brief Tragedy for Barns and Booths

Dramatis Personae

Character, a character

Scene: A scene.

Passion, Poison and Petrifaction

In a bed-sitting room in a fashionable quarter of London a lady sits at her dressing-table, with her maid combing her hair. It is late. and the electric lamps are glowing. Apparently the room is bedless, but there stands against the opposite wall to that at which the dressing-table is placed a piece of furniture that suggests a bookcase without carrying conviction. On the same side is a chest of drawers of that disastrous kind which, recalcitrant to the opener until she is provoked to violence, then suddenly come wholly out and defy all her efforts to fit them in again. Opposite this chest of drawers, on the lady’s side of the room, is a cupboard. The presence of a row of gentleman’s boots beside the chest of drawers proclaims that the lady is married. Her own boots are beside the cupboard. The third wall is pierced midway by the door, above which is a cuckoo clock. Near the door a pedestal bears a portrait bust of the lady in plaster. There is a fan on the dressing-table, a hatbox and rug strap on the chest of drawers, an umbrella and a bootjack against the wall near the bed. The general impression is one of brightness, beauty, and social ambition, damped by somewhat inadequate means. A certain air of theatricality is produced by the fact that though the room is rectangular it has only three walls. Not a sound is heard except the overture and the crackling of the lady’s hair as the maid’s brush draws electric sparks from it in the dry air of the London midsummer. The cuckoo clock strikes sixteen.

The Lady | How much did the clock strike, Phyllis?
Phyllis | Sixteen, my lady.
The Lady | That means eleven o’clock, does it not?
Phyllis | Eleven at night, my lady. In the morning it means half-past two; so if you hear it strike sixteen during your slumbers, do not rise.
The Lady | I will not, Phyllis. Phyllis: I am weary. I will go to bed. Prepare my couch.
Phyllis crosses the room to the bookcase and touches a button. The front of the bookcase falls out with a crash and becomes a bed. A roll of distant thunder echoes the crash. Phyllis | shuddering It is a terrible night Heaven help all poor mariners at sea! My master is late. I trust nothing has happened to him. Your bed is ready, my lady.
The Lady | Thank you, Phyllis. She rises and approaches the bed. Goodnight.
Phyllis | Will your ladyship not undress?
The Lady | Not tonight, Phyllis. Glancing through where the fourth wall is missing Not under the circumstances.
Phyllis | impulsively throwing herself on her knees by her mistress’s side, and clasping her round the waist Oh, my beloved mistress, I know not why or how; but I feel that I shall never see you alive again. There is murder in the air. Thunder. Hark!
The Lady | Strange! As I sat there methought I heard angels singing. “Oh, wont you come home. Bill Bailey?” Why should angels call me Bill Bailey? My name is Magnesia Fitztollemache.
Phyllis | emphasizing the title Lady Magnesia Fitztollemache.
Lady Magnesia | In case we should never again meet in this world, let us take a last farewell.
Phyllis | embracing her with tears My poor murdered angel mistress!
Lady Magnesia | In case we should meet again, call me at half-past eleven.
Phyllis | I will, I will.
Phyllis withdraws, overcome by emotion. Lady Magnesia switches off the electric light, and immediately hears the angels quite distinctly. They sing Bill Bailey so sweetly that she can attend to nothing else and forgets to remove even her boots as she draws the coverlet over herself and sinks to sleep, lulled by celestial harmony. A white radiance plays on her pillow, and lights up her beautiful face. But the thunder growls again, and a lurid red glow concentrates itself on the door, which is presently flung open, revealing a saturnine figure in evening dress, partially concealed by a crimson cloak. As he steals towards the bed the unnatural glare in his eyes and the broad-bladed dagger nervously gripped in his right hand bode ill for the sleeping lady. Providentially she sneezes on the very brink of eternity, and the tension of the murderer’s nerves is such that he bolts precipitately under the bed at the sudden and startling Atscha! A dull, heavy, rhythmic thumping—the beating of his heart—betrays his whereabouts. Soon he emerges cautiously and raises his head above the bed coverlet level. The Murderer | I can no longer cower here listening to the agonized thumpings of my own heart She but snoze in her sleep. I’ll do’t. He again raises the dagger. The angels sing again. He cowers What is this? Has that tune reached Heaven?
Lady Magnesia | waking and sitting up My husband! All the colors of the rainbow chase one another up his face with ghastly brilliancy. Why do you change color? And what on earth are you doing with that dagger?
Fitz | affecting unconcern, hut unhinged It is a present for you: a present from mother. Pretty. Isnt it? he displays it fatuously.
Lady Magnesia | But she promised me a fish slice.
Fitz | This is a combination fish slice and dagger. One day you have salmon for dinner. The next you have a murder to commit. See?
Lady Magnesia | My sweet mother-in-law! Someone knocks at the door. That is Adolphus’s knock. Fitz’s face turns a dazzling green. What has happened to your complexion? You have turned green. Now I think of it, you always do when Adolphus is mentioned. Arnt you going to let him in?
Fitz | Certainly not. He goes to the door. Adolphus: you cannot enter. My wife is undressed and in bed.
Lady Magnesia | rising I am not Come in, Adolphus. she switches on the electric light.
Adolphus | without Something most important has happened. I must come in for a moment.
Fitz | calling to Adolphus Something important happened? What is it?
Adolphus | without My new clothes have come home.
Fitz | He says his new clothes have come home.
Lady Magnesia | running to the door and opening it Oh, come in, come in. Let me see.
Adolphus Bastable enters. He is in evening dress, made in the latest fashion, with the right half of the coat and the left half of the trousers yellow and the other halves black. His silver-spangled waistcoat has a crimson handkerchief stuck between it and his shirt front. Adolphus | What do you think of it?
Lady Magnesia | It is a dream! a creation! she turns him about to admire him.
Adolphus | proudly I shall never be mistaken for a waiter again.
Fitz | A drink, Adolphus?
Adolphus | Thanks.
Fitztollemache goes to the cupboard and takes out a tray with tumblers and a bottle of whisky. He puts them an the dressing-table. Fitz | Is the gazogene full?
Lady Magnesia | Yes: you put in the powders yourself today.
Fitz | sardonically So I did. The special powders! Hal ha! ha! ha! ha! His face Is again strangely variegated.
Lady Magnesia | Your complexion is really going to pieces. Why do you laugh in that silly way at nothing?
Fitz | Nothing! Ha, ha! Nothing! Ha, ha, ha!
Adolphus | I hope, Mr. Fitztollemache, you are not laughing at my dothes. I warn you that I am an Englishman. You may laugh at my manners, at my brains, at my national institutions; but if you laugh at my clothes, one of us must die.
Thunder. Fitz | I laughed but at the irony of Fate. He takes a gazogene from the cupboard.
Adolphus | satisfied Oh, that! Oh, yes, of course!
Fitz | Let us drown all unkindness in a loving cup. He puts the gazogene on the floor in the middle of the room. Pardon the absence of a table: we found it in the way and pawned it. He takes the whisky bottle from the dressing-table.
Lady Magnesia | We picnic at home now. It is delightful. She takes three tumblers from the dressing-table and sits on the floor, presiding over the gazogene, with Fitz and Adolphus squatting on her left and right respectively. Fitz pours whisky into the tumblers.
Fitz | as Magnesia is about to squirt soda into his tumbler Stay! No soda for me. Let Adolphus have it all—all. I will take mine neat.
Lady Magnesia | proffering tumbler to Adolphus Pledge me, Adolphus.
Fitz | Kiss the cup, Magnesia. Pledge her, man. Drink deep.
Adolphus | To Magnesia!
Fitz | To Magnesia! The two men drink. It is done. Scrambling to his feet Adolphus: you have but ten minutes to live—if so long.
Adolphus | What mean you?
Magnesia | rising My mind misgives me. I have a strange feeling here. touching her heart
Adolphus | So have I, but lower down. touching his stomach That gazogene is disagreeing with me.
Fitz | It was poisoned!
Sensation. Adolphus | rising Help! Police!
Fitz | Dastard! you would appeal to the law! Can you not die like a gentleman?
Adolphus | But so young! when I have only worn my new clothes once.
Magnesia | It is too horrible. To Fitz Fiend! what drove you to this wicked deed?
Fitz | Jealousy. You admired his clothes: you did not admire mine.
Adolphus | My clothes his face lights up with heavenly radiance Have I indeed been found worthy to be the first clothes-martyr? Welcome, death! Hark! angels call me. The celestial choir again raises its favorite chant. He listens with a rapt expression. Suddenly the angels sing out of tune, and the radiance on the poisoned man’s face turns a sickly green Yah—ah! Oh—ahoo! The gazogene is disagreeing extremely. Oh! he throws himself on the bed, writhing.
Magnesia | to Fitz Monster: what have you done? She points to the distorted figure on the bed. That was once a Man, beautiful and glorious. What have you made of it? A writhing, agonized,miserable, moribund worm.
Adolphus | in a tone of the strongest remonstrance Oh, I say! Oh, come! No: look here. Magnesia! Really!
Magnesia | Oh, is this a time for petty vanity? Think of your misspent life—
Adolphus | much injured Whose misspent life?
Magnesia | continuing relentlessly Look into your conscience: look into your stomach. Adolphus collapses in hideous spasms. She turns to Fitz. And this is your handiwork!
Fitz | Mine is a passionate nature. Magnesia. I must have your undivided love. I must have your love: do you hear? LOVE! LOVE!! LOVE!!! LOVE!!!! LOVE!!!!! He raves, accompanied by a fresh paroxysm from the victim on the bed.
Magnesia | with sudden resolution You shall have it.
Fitz | enraptured Magnesia! I have recovered your love! Oh, how slight appears the sacrifice of this man compared to so glorious a reward! I would poison ten men without a thought of self to gain one smile from you.
Adolphus | in a broken voice Farewell, Magnesia: my last hour is at hand. Farewell, farewell, farewell!
Magnesia | At this supreme moment, George Fitztollemache, I solemnly dedicate to you all that I formerly dedicated to poor Adolphus.
Adolphus | Oh, please not poor Adolphus yet. I still live, you know.
Magnesia | The vital spark but flashes before it vanishes. Adolphus groans. And now, Adolphus, take this last comfort from the unhappy Magnesia Fitztollemache. As I have dedicated to George all that I gave to you, so I will bury in your grave—or in your urn if you are cremated—all that I gave to him.
Fitz | I hardly follow this.
Magnesia | I will explain. George: hitherto I have given Adolphus all the romance of my nature—all my love—all my dreams—all my caresses. Henceforth they are yours!
Fitz | Angel!
Magnesia | Adolphus: forgive me if this pains you.
Adolphus | Dont mention it I hardly feel it The gazogene is so much worse. Taken bad again Oh!
Magnesia | Peace, poor sufferer: there is still some balm. You are about to hear what I am going to dedicate to you.
Adolphus | All I ask is a peppermint lozenge, for mercy’s sake.
Magnesia | I have something far better than any lozenge: the devotion of a lifetime. Formerly it was George’s. I kept his house, or rather, his lodgings. I mended his clothes. I darned his socks. I bought his food. I interviewed his creditors. I stood between him and the servants. I administered his domestic finances. When his hair needed cutting or his countenance was imperfectly washed, I pointed it out to him. The trouble that all this gave me made him prosaic in my eyes. Familiarity bred contempt Now all that shall end. My husband shall be my hero, my lover, my perfect knight He shall shield me from all care and trouble. He shall ask nothing in return but love—boundless, priceless, rapturous, soul-enthralling love. Love! LOVE! LOVE! she raves and flings her arms about Fitz. And the duties I formerly discharged shall be replaced by the one supreme duty of duties: the duty of weeping at Adolphus’s tomb.
Fitz | reflectively My ownest, this sacrifice makes me feel that I have perhaps been a little selfish. I cannot help feeling that there is much to be said for the old arrangement Why should Adolphus die for my sake?
Adolphus | I am not dying for your sake, Fitz. I am dying because you poisoned me.
Magnesia | You do not fear to die, Adolphus, do you?
Adolphus | N-n-no, I dont exactly fear to die. Still—
Fitz | Still, if an antidote—
Adolphus | bounding from the bed Antidote!
Magnesia | with wild hope Antidote!
Fitz | If an antidote would not be too much of an anticlimax.
Adolphus | Anticlimax be blowed! Do you think I am going to die to please the critics? Out with your antidote. Quick!
Fitz | The best antidote to the poison I have given you is lime, plenty of lime.
Adolphus | Lime! You mock me! Do you think I carry lime about in my pockets?
Fitz | There is the plaster ceiling.
Magnesia | Yes, the ceiling. Saved, saved, saved!
All three frantically shy boots at the ceiling. Flakes of plaster rain down which Adolphus devours, at first ravenously, then with a marked falling off in relish. Magnesia | picking up a huge slice Take this, Adolphus: it is the largest. she crams it into his mouth.
Fitz | Ha! a lump off the cornice! Try this.
Adolphus | desperately Stop! stop!
Magnesia | Do not stop. You will die. She tries to stuff him again.
Adolphus | resolutely I prefer death.
Magnesia and Fitz | throwing themselves on their knees on either side of him For our sakes, Adolphus, persevere.
Adolphus | No: unless you can supply lime in liquid form, I must perish. Finish that ceiling I cannot and will not.
Magnesia | I have a thought—an inspiration. My bust She snatches it from its pedestal and brings it to him.
Adolphus | gazing fondly at it Can I resist it?
Fitz | Try the bun.
Adolphus | gnawing the knot of hair at the back of the bust’s head: it makes him ill. Yah, I cannot. I cannot. Not even your bust, Magnesia. Do not ask me. Let me die.
Fitz | pressing the bust on him Force yourself to take a mouthful. Down with it, Adolphus!
Adolphus | Useless. It would not stay down. Water! Some fluid! Ring for something to drink He chokes. MAGNESIA. I will save you She rushes to the bell and rings.
Phyllis, in her nightgown, with her hair prettify made up into a chevaux defrise of crocuses with pink and yellow curlpapers, rushes in straight to Magnesia. Phyllis | hysterically My beloved mistress, once more we meet She sees Fitztollemache and screams. Ah! ah! ah! A man! She sees Adolphus Men!! She flies, but Fitztollemache seizes her by the nightgown just as she is escaping. Unhand me, villain!
Fitz | This is no time for prudery, girl. Mr. Bastable is dying.
Phyllis | with concern Indeed, sir? I hope he will not think it unfeeling of me to appear at his deathbed in curl papers.
Magnesia | We know you have a good heart, Phyllis. Take this giving her the bust; dissolve it in a jug of hot water; and bring it back instantly. Mr. Bastable’s life depends on your haste.
Phyllis | hesitating It do seem a pity, dont it, my lady, to spoil your lovely bust?
Adolphus | Tush! This craze for fine art is beyond alt bounds. Off with you [he pushes her out]. Drink, drink, drink! My entrails are parched. Drink! he rushes deliriously to the gazogene.
Fitz | rushing after him Madman, you forget! It is poisoned!
Adolphus | I dont care. Drink, drink! They wrestle madly for the gazogene. In the struggle they squirt all its contents away, mostly into one another’s face. Adolphus at last flings Fitztollemache to the floor, and puts the spout into his mouth. Empty! empty! with a shriek of despair he collapses on the bed, clasping the gazogene like a baby, and weeping over it.
Fitz | aside to Magnesia Magnesia: I have always pretended not to notice it; but you keep a siphon for your private use in my hatbox.
Magnesia | I use it for washing old lace; but no matter: he shall have it she produces a siphon from the hatbox, and offers a tumbler of soda-water to Adolphus.
Adolphus | Thanks, thanks, oh, thanks! He drinks. A terrific fizzing is heard. He starts up screaming Help! help! The ceiling is effervescing! I am BURSTING! He wallows convulsively on the bed.
Fitz | Quick! the rug strap! They pack him with blankets and strap him. Is that tight enough?
Magnesia | anxiously Will you hold, do you think?
Adolphus | The peril is past The soda-water has gone flat.
Magnesia and Fitz | Thank heaven!
Phyllis returns with a washstand ewer, in which she has dissolved the bust. Magnesia | snatching it At last!
Fitz | You are saved. Drain it to the dregs.
Fitztollemache holds the lip of the ewer to Adolphus’s mouth and gradually raises it until it stands upside down. Adolphus’s efforts to swallow it are fearful, Phyllis thumping his back when he chokes and Magnesia loosening the straps when he moans. At last, with a sigh of relief, he sinks back in the women’s arms. Fitz shakes the empty ewer upside down like a potman shaking the froth out of a flagon. Adolphus | How inexpressibly soothing to the chest! A delicious numbness steals through all my members. I would sleep.
Magnesia—Fitz—Phyllis | whispering together Let him sleep.
He sleeps. Celestial harps are heard, but their chords cease on the abrupt entrance of the landlord, a vulgar person in pyjamas. The Landlord | Eah! Eah! Wots this? Wots all this noise? Ah kin ennybody sleep through it? Looking at the floor and ceiling Ellow! wot you bin doin te maw ceilin?
Fitz | Silence, or leave the room. If you wake that man he dies.
The Landlord | If e kin sleep through the noise you three mikes e kin sleep through ennythink.
Magnesia | Detestable vulgarian: your pronunciation jars on the finest chords of my nature. Begone!
The Landlord | looking at Adolphus Aw downt blieve eze esleep. Aw blieve eze dead. Calling Pleece! Pleecel Merder! A blue halo plays mysteriously on the door,which opens and reveals a policeman. Thunder Eah, pleecmin: these three’s bin an murdered this gent between em, an naw tore moy ahse dahn.
The Policeman | offended Policeman, indeed! Wheres your manners?
Fitz | Officer—
The Policeman | with distinguished consideration Sir?
Fitz | As between gentlemen—
The Policeman | bowing Sir. to you.
Fitz | bowing I may inform you that my friend had an acute attack of indigestion. No carbonate of soda being available, he swallowed a portion of this man’s ceiling. Pointing to Adolphus Behold the result!
The Policeman | The ceiling was poisoned! Well, of all the artful—he collars the landlord. I arrest you for wilful murder.
The Landlord | appealing to the heavens Ow, is this jesticel Ah could aw tell e wiz gowin te eat moy ceilin?
The Policeman | releasing him True. The case is more complicated than I thought He tries to lift Adolphus’s arm but cannot. Stiff already.
The Landlord | trying to lift Adolphus’s leg An’ precious evvy.Feeling the calf Woy, eze gorn ez awd ez niles.
Fitz | rushing to the bed What is this?
Magnesia | Oh, say not he is dead. Phyllis: fetch a doctor. Phyllis runs out. They all try to lift Adolphus, but he is perfectly stiff, and as heavy as lead. Rouse him. Shake him.
The Policeman | exhausted Whew! Is he a man or a statue? Magnesia utters a piercing scream. Whats wrong, Miss?
Magnesia | to Fitz Do you not see what has happened?
Fitz | striking his forehead Horror on horror’s head!
The Landlord | Wotjemean?
Magnesia | The plaster has set inside him. The officer was right: he is indeed a living statue.
Magnesia flings herself on the stony breast of Adolphus. Fitztollemache buries his head in his hands, and his chest heaves convulsively. The policeman takes a small volume from his pocket and consults it. The Policeman | This case is not provided for in my book of instructions. It dont seem no use trying artificial respiration, do it? To the landlord Here! lend a hand, you. We’d best take him and set him up in Trafalgar Square.
The Landlord | Aushd pat im in the cestern an worsh it aht of im.
Phyllis comes back with a Doctor. Phyllis | The medical man, my lady.
The Policeman | A poison case, sir.
The Doctor | Do you mean to say that an unqualified person! a layman! has dared to administer poison in my district?
The Policeman | raising Magnesia tenderly It looks like it. Hold up, my lady.
The Doctor | Not a moment must be lost The patient must be kept awake at all costs. Constant and violent motion is necessary. He snatches Magnesia from the policeman, and rushes her about the room.
Fitz | Stop! That is not the poisoned person!
The Doctor | It is you, then. Why did you not say so before?He seizes Fitztollemache and rushes him about.
The Landlord | Naow, naow, thet ynt im.
The Doctor | What, you! He pounces on the landlord and rushes him round.
The Landlord | Eah! chack it He trips the doctor up. Both fall. Jest owld this leoonatic, will you. Mister Horficer?
The Policeman | dragging both of them to their feet Come out of it, will you. You must all come with me to me station.
Thunder. Magnesia | What! In this frightful storm!
The hail patters noisily on the window. Phyllis | I think it’s raining.
The wind howls. The Landlord | It’s thanderin and lawtnin.
Fitz | It’s dangerous.
The Policeman | drawing his baton and whistle If you wont come quietly, then—
He whistles. A fearful flash is followed by an appalling explosion of heaven’s artillery. A thunderbolt enters the room, and strikes the helmet of the devoted constable, whence it is attracted to the waistcoat of the doctor by the lancet in his pocket. Finally it leaps with fearful force on the landlord, who, being of a gross and spongy nature, absorbs the electric fluid at the cost of his life. The others look on horror-stricken as the three victims, after reeling, jostling, cannoning through a ghastly quadrille, at last sink inanimate on the carpet. Magnesia | listening at the doctor’s chest Dead!
Fitz | kneeling by the landlord, and raising his hand, which drops with a thud Dead!
Phyllis | seizing the looking-glass and holding it to the Policeman’s lips Dead!
Fitz | solemnly rising The copper attracted the lightning.
Magnesia | rising After life’s fitful fever they sleep well. Phyllis: sweep them up.
Phyllis replaces the looking-glass on the dressing-table, takes up the fan, and fans the policeman, who rolls away like a leaf before the wind, to the wall. She disposes similarly of the landlord and doctor. Phyllis | Will they be in your way if I leave them there until morning, my lady? Or shall I bring up the ashpan and take them away?
Magnesia | They will not disturb us. Goodnight, Phyllis.
Phyllis | Goodnight, my lady. Goodnight, sir. She retires.
Magnesia | And now, husband, let us perform our last sad duty to our friend. He has become his own monument. Let us erect him. He is heavy; but love can do much.
Fitz | A litte leverage will get him on his feet Give me my umbrella.
Magnesia | True.
She hands him the umbrella, and takes up the bootjack.They get them under Adolphus’s back, and prize him up on his feet. Fitz | Thats done it! Whew!
Magnesia | kneeling at the left hand of the statue For ever and for ever, Adolphus.
Fitz | kneeling at the right hand of the statue The rest is silence.
The Angels sing Bill Bailey. The statue raises its hands in an attitude of blessing, and turns its limelit face to heaven as the curtain falls. National Anthem. Attendants | in front All out for the next performance. Pass along, please, ladies and gentlemen: pass along.

PASSION, POISON, AND PETRIFACTION or

THE FATAL GAZOGENE

In a bed-sitting room in a fashionable quarter of London a lady sits at her dressing-table, with her maid combing her hair. It is late. and the electric lamps are glowing. Apparently the room is bedless, but there stands against the opposite wall to that at which the dressing-table is placed a piece of furniture that suggests a bookcase without carrying conviction. On the same side is a chest of drawers of that disastrous kind which, recalcitrant to the opener until she is provoked to violence, then suddenly come wholly out and defy all her efforts to fit them in again. Opposite this chest of drawers, on the lady's side of the room, is a cupboard. The presence of a row of gentleman's boots beside the chest of drawers proclaims that the lady is married. Her own boots are beside the cupboard. The third wall is pierced midway by the door, above which is a cuckoo clock. Near the door a pedestal bears a portrait bust of the lady in plaster. There is a fan on the dressing-table, a hatbox and rug strap on the chest of drawers, an umbrella and a bootjack against the wall near the bed. The general impression is one of brightness, beauty, and social ambition, damped by somewhat inadequate means. A certain air of theatricality is produced by the fact that though the room is rectangular it has only three walls. Not a sound is heard except the overture and the crackling of the lady’s hair as the maid's brush draws electric sparks from it in the dry air of the London midsummer. The cuckoo clock strikes sixteen.

THE LADY. How much did the clock strike, Phyllis?

PHYLLIS. Sixteen, my lady.

THE LADY. That means eleven o'clock, does it not?

PHYLLIS. Eleven at night, my lady. In the morning it means half-past two; so if you hear it strike sixteen during your slumbers, do not rise.

THE LADY. I will not, Phyllis. Phyllis: I am weary. I will go to bed. Prepare my couch.

Phyllis crosses the room to the bookcase and touches a button. The front of the bookcase falls out with a crash and becomes a bed. A roll of distant thunder echoes the crash.

PHYLLIS [shuddering] It is a terrible night Heaven help all poor mariners at sea! My master is late. I trust nothing has happened to him. Your bed is ready, my lady.

THE LADY. Thank you, Phyllis. [She rises and approaches the bed.] Goodnight.

PHYLLIS. Will your ladyship not undress?

THE LADY. Not tonight, Phyllis. [Glancing through where the fourth wall is missing] Not under the circumstances.

PHYLLIS [impulsively throwing herself on her knees by her mistress's side, and clasping her round the waist] Oh, my beloved mistress, I know not why or how; but I feel that I shall never see you alive again. There is murder in the air. [Thunder.] Hark!

THE LADY. Strange! As I sat there methought I heard angels singing. “Oh, wont you come home. Bill Bailey?” Why should angels call me Bill Bailey? My name is Magnesia Fitztollemache.

PHYLLIS [emphasizing the title] Lady Magnesia Fitztollemache.

LADY MAGNESIA. In case we should never again meet in this world, let us take a last farewell.

PHYLLIS [embracing her with tears] My poor murdered angel mistress!

LADY MAGNESIA. In case we should meet again, call me at half-past eleven.

PHYLLIS. I will, I will.

Phyllis withdraws, overcome by emotion. Lady Magnesia switches off the electric light, and immediately hears the angels quite distinctly. They sing Bill Bailey so sweetly that she can attend to nothing else and forgets to remove even her boots as she draws the coverlet over herself and sinks to sleep, lulled by celestial harmony. A white radiance plays on her pillow, and lights up her beautiful face. But the thunder growls again, and a lurid red glow concentrates itself on the door, which is presently flung open, revealing a saturnine figure in evening dress, partially concealed by a crimson cloak. As he steals towards the bed the unnatural glare in his eyes and the broad-bladed dagger nervously gripped in his right hand bode ill for the sleeping lady. Providentially she sneezes on the very brink of eternity, and the tension of the murderer's nerves is such that he bolts precipitately under the bed at the sudden and startling Atscha! A dull, heavy, rhythmic thumping—the beating of his heart—betrays his whereabouts. Soon he emerges cautiously and raises his head above the bed coverlet level.

THE MURDERER. I can no longer cower here listening to the agonized thumpings of my own heart She but snoze in her sleep. I'll do't. [He again raises the dagger. The angels sing again. He cowers] What is this? Has that tune reached Heaven?

LADY MAGNESIA. [waking and sitting up] My husband! [All the colors of the rainbow chase one another up his face with ghastly brilliancy.] Why do you change color? And what on earth are you doing with that dagger?

FITZ [affecting unconcern, hut unhinged] It is a present for you: a present from mother. Pretty. Isnt it? [he displays it fatuously].

LADY MAGNESIA. But she promised me a fish slice.

FITZ. This is a combination fish slice and dagger. One day you have salmon for dinner. The next you have a murder to commit. See?

LADY MAGNESIA. My sweet mother-in-law! [Someone knocks at the door.] That is Adolphus's knock. [Fitz’s face turns a dazzling green.] What has happened to your complexion? You have turned green. Now I think of it, you always do when Adolphus is mentioned. Arnt you going to let him in?

FITZ. Certainly not. [He goes to the door.] Adolphus: you cannot enter. My wife is undressed and in bed.

LADY MAGNESIA. [rising] I am not Come in, Adolphus. [she switches on the electric light.]

ADOLPHUS. [without] Something most important has happened. I must come in for a moment.

FITZ. [calling to Adolphus] Something important happened? What is it?

ADOLPHUS [without] My new clothes have come home.

FITZ. He says his new clothes have come home.

LADY MAGNESIA [running to the door and opening it] Oh, come in, come in. Let me see.

Adolphus Bastable enters. He is in evening dress, made in the latest fashion, with the right half of the coat and the left half of the trousers yellow and the other halves black. His silver-spangled waistcoat has a crimson handkerchief stuck between it and his shirt front.

ADOLPHUS. What do you think of it?

LADY MAGNESIA. It is a dream! a creation! [she turns him about to admire him.]

ADOLPHUS [proudly] I shall never be mistaken for a waiter again.

FITZ. A drink, Adolphus?

ADOLPHUS. Thanks.

Fitztollemache goes to the cupboard and takes out a tray with tumblers and a bottle of whisky. He puts them an the dressing-table.

FITZ. Is the gazogene full?

LADY MAGNESIA. Yes: you put in the powders yourself today.

FITZ. [sardonically] So I did. The special powders! Hal ha! ha! ha! ha! [His face Is again strangely variegated.]

LADY MAGNESIA. Your complexion is really going to pieces. Why do you laugh in that silly way at nothing?

FITZ. Nothing! Ha, ha! Nothing! Ha, ha, ha!

ADOLPHUS. I hope, Mr Fitztollemache, you are not laughing at my dothes. I warn you that I am an Englishman. You may laugh at my manners, at my brains, at my national institutions; but if you laugh at my clothes, one of us must die.

Thunder.

FITZ. I laughed but at the irony of Fate. [He takes a gazogene from the cupboard.]

ADOLPHUS. [satisfied] Oh, that! Oh, yes, of course!

FITZ. Let us drown all unkindness in a loving cup. [He puts the gazogene on the floor in the middle of the room.] Pardon the absence of a table: we found it in the way and pawned it. [He takes the whisky bottle from the dressing-table.]

LADY MAGNESIA. We picnic at home now. It is delightful. [She takes three tumblers from the dressing-table and sits on the floor, presiding over the gazogene, with Fitz and Adolphus squatting on her left and right respectively. Fitz pours whisky into the tumblers.]

FITZ. [as Magnesia is about to squirt soda into his tumbler] Stay! No soda for me. Let Adolphus have it all—all. I will take mine neat.

LADY MAGNESIA [proffering tumbler to Adolphus] Pledge me, Adolphus.

FITZ. Kiss the cup, Magnesia. Pledge her, man. Drink deep.

ADOLPHUS. To Magnesia!

FITZ. To Magnesia! [The two men drink.] It is done. [Scrambling to his feet] Adolphus: you have but ten minutes to live—if so long.

ADOLPHUS. What mean you?

MAGNESIA. [rising] My mind misgives me. I have a strange feeling here. [touching her heart]

ADOLPHUS. So have I, but lower down. [touching his stomach] That gazogene is disagreeing with me.

FITZ. It was poisoned!

Sensation.

ADOLPHUS [rising] Help! Police!

FITZ. Dastard! you would appeal to the law! Can you not die like a gentleman?

ADOLPHUS. But so young! when I have only worn my new clothes once.

MAGNESIA. It is too horrible. [To Fitz] Fiend! what drove you to this wicked deed?

FITZ. Jealousy. You admired his clothes: you did not admire mine.

ADOLPHUS. My clothes [his face lights up with heavenly radiance] Have I indeed been found worthy to be the first clothes-martyr? Welcome, death! Hark! angels call me. [The celestial choir again raises its favorite chant. He listens with a rapt expression. Suddenly the angels sing out of tune, and the radiance on the poisoned man's face turns a sickly green] Yah—ah! Oh—ahoo! The gazogene is disagreeing extremely. Oh! [he throws himself on the bed,writhing.]

MAGNESIA. [to Fitz] Monster: what have you done? [She points to the distorted figure on the bed.] That was once a Man, beautiful and glorious. What have you made of it? A writhing, agonized,miserable, moribund worm.

ADOLPHUS. [in a tone of the strongest remonstrance] Oh, I say! Oh, come! No: look here. Magnesia! Really!

MAGNESIA. Oh, is this a time for petty vanity? Think of your misspent life—

ADOLPHUS [much injured] Whose misspent life?

MAGNESIA [continuing relentlessly] Look into your conscience: look into your stomach. [Adolphus collapses in hideous spasms. She turns to Fitz.] And this is your handiwork!

FITZ. Mine is a passionate nature. Magnesia. I must have your undivided love. I must have your love: do you hear? LOVE! LOVE!! LOVE!!! LOVE!!!! LOVE!!!!! [He raves, accompanied by a fresh paroxysm from the victim on the bed.]

MAGNESIA. [with sudden resolution] You shall have it.

FITZ [enraptured] Magnesia! I have recovered your love! Oh, how slight appears the sacrifice of this man compared to so glorious a reward! I would poison ten men without a thought of self to gain one smile from you.

ADOLPHUS. [in a broken voice] Farewell, Magnesia: my last hour is at hand. Farewell, farewell, farewell!

MAGNESIA. At this supreme moment, George Fitztollemache, I solemnly dedicate to you all that I formerly dedicated to poor Adolphus.

ADOLPHUS. Oh, please not poor Adolphus yet. I still live, you know.

MAGNESIA. The vital spark but flashes before it vanishes. [Adolphus groans.] And now, Adolphus, take this last comfort from the unhappy Magnesia Fitztollemache. As I have dedicated to George all that I gave to you, so I will bury in your grave—or in your urn if you are cremated—all that I gave to him.

FITZ. I hardly follow this.

MAGNESIA. I will explain. George: hitherto I have given Adolphus all the romance of my nature—all my love—all my dreams—all my caresses. Henceforth they are yours!

FITZ. Angel!

MAGNESIA. Adolphus: forgive me if this pains you.

ADOLPHUS. Dont mention it I hardly feel it The gazogene is so much worse. [Taken bad again] Oh!

MAGNESIA. Peace, poor sufferer: there is still some balm. You are about to hear what I am going to dedicate to you.

ADOLPHUS. All I ask is a peppermint lozenge, for mercy's sake.

MAGNESIA. I have something far better than any lozenge: the devotion of a lifetime. Formerly it was George's. I kept his house, or rather, his lodgings. I mended his clothes. I darned his socks. I bought his food. I interviewed his creditors. I stood between him and the servants. I administered his domestic finances. When his hair needed cutting or his countenance was imperfectly washed, I pointed it out to him. The trouble that all this gave me made him prosaic in my eyes. Familiarity bred contempt Now all that shall end. My husband shall be my hero, my lover, my perfect knight He shall shield me from all care and trouble. He shall ask nothing in return but love—boundless, priceless, rapturous, soul-enthralling love. Love! LOVE! LOVE! [she raves and flings her arms about Fitz.] And the duties I formerly discharged shall be replaced by the one supreme duty of duties: the duty of weeping at Adolphus's tomb.

FITZ.[reflectively] My ownest, this sacrifice makes me feel that I have perhaps been a little selfish. I cannot help feeling that there is much to be said for the old arrangement Why should Adolphus die for my sake?

ADOLPHUS. I am not dying for your sake, Fitz. I am dying because you poisoned me.

MAGNESIA. You do not fear to die, Adolphus, do you?

ADOLPHUS. N-n-no, I dont exactly fear to die. Still—

FITZ. Still, if an antidote—

ADOLPHUS. [bounding from the bed] Antidote!

MAGNESIA. [with wild hope] Antidote!

FITZ. If an antidote would not be too much of an anti-climax.

ADOLPHUS. Anti-climax be blowed! Do you think I am going to die to please the critics? Out with your antidote. Quick!

FITZ. The best antidote to the poison I have given you is lime, plenty of lime.

ADOLPHUS. Lime! You mock me! Do you think I carry lime about in my pockets?

FITZ. There is the plaster ceiling.

MAGNESIA. Yes, the ceiling. Saved, saved, saved!

All three frantically shy boots at the ceiling. Flakes of plaster rain down which Adolphus devours, at first ravenously, then with a marked falling off in relish.

MAGNESIA. [picking up a huge slice] Take this, Adolphus: it is the largest. [she crams it into his mouth.]

FITZ. Ha! a lump off the cornice! Try this.

ADOLPHUS. [desperately] Stop! stop!

MAGNESIA. Do not stop. You will die. [She tries to stuff him again.]

ADOLPHUS [resolutely] I prefer death.

MAGNESIA and FITZ. [throwing themselves on their knees on either side of him] For our sakes, Adolphus, persevere.

ADOLPHUS. No: unless you can supply lime in liquid form, I must perish. Finish that ceiling I cannot and will not.

MAGNESIA. I have a thought—an inspiration. My bust [She snatches it from its pedestal and brings it to him.]

ADOLPHUS [gazing fondly at it] Can I resist it?

FITZ. Try the bun.

ADOLPHUS. [gnawing the knot of hair at the back of the bust's head: it makes him ill.] Yah, I cannot. I cannot. Not even your bust, Magnesia. Do not ask me. Let me die.

FITZ. [pressing the bust on him] Force yourself to take a mouthful. Down with it, Adolphus!

ADOLPHUS. Useless. It would not stay down. Water! Some fluid! Ring for something to drink [He chokes.] MAGNESIA. I will save you [She rushes to the bell and rings.]

Phyllis, in her night-gown, with her hair prettify made up into a chevaux defrise of crocuses with pink and yellow curlpapers, rushes in straight to Magnesia.

PHYLLIS. [hysterically] My beloved mistress, once more we meet [She sees Fitztollemache and screams.] Ah! ah! ah! A man! [She sees Adolphus] Men!! [She flies, but Fitztollemache seizes her by the night-gown just as she is escaping.] Unhand me, villain!

FITZ. This is no time for prudery, girl. Mr Bastable is dying.

PHYLLIS. [with concern] Indeed, sir? I hope he will not think it unfeeling of me to appear at his deathbed in curl papers.

MAGNESIA. We know you have a good heart, Phyllis. Take this [giving her the bust]; dissolve it in a jug of hot water; and bring it back instantly. Mr Bastable's life depends on your haste.

PHYLLIS. [hesitating] It do seem a pity, dont it, my lady, to spoil your lovely bust?

ADOLPHUS. Tush! This craze for fine art is beyond alt bounds. Off with you [he pushes her out]. Drink, drink, drink! My entrails are parched. Drink! [he rushes deliriously to the gazogene.]

FITZ. [rushing after him] Madman, you forget! It is poisoned!

ADOLPHUS. I dont care. Drink, drink! [They wrestle madly for the gazogene. In the struggle they squirt all its contents away, mostly into one another's face. Adolphus at last flings Fitztollemache to the floor, and puts the spout into his mouth.] Empty! empty! [with a shriek of despair he collapses on the bed, clasping the gazogene like a baby, and weeping over it.]

FITZ. [aside to Magnesia] Magnesia: I have always pretended not to notice it; but you keep a siphon for your private use in my hatbox.

MAGNESIA. I use it for washing old lace; but no matter: he shall have it [she produces a siphon from the hat-box, and offers a tumbler of soda-water to Adolphus.]

ADOLPHUS. Thanks, thanks, oh, thanks! [He drinks. A terrific fizzing is heard. He starts up screaming] Help! help! The ceiling is effervescing! I am BURSTING! [He wallows convulsively on the bed.]

FITZ. Quick! the rug strap! [They pack him with blankets and strap him.] Is that tight enough?

MAGNESIA. [anxiously] Will you hold, do you think?

ADOLPHUS. The peril is past The soda-water has gone flat.

MAGNESIA and FITZ Thank heaven!

Phyllis returns with a washstand ewer, in which she has dissolved the bust.

MAGNESIA [snatching it] At last!

FITZ. You are saved. Drain it to the dregs.

Fitztollemache holds the lip of the ewer to Adolphus’s mouth and gradually raises it until it stands upside down. Adolphus's efforts to swallow it are fearful, Phyllis thumping his back when he chokes and Magnesia loosening the straps when he moans. At last, with a sigh of relief, he sinks tack in the women's arms. Fitz shakes the empty ewer upside down like a potman shaking the froth out of a flagon.

ADOLPHUS. How inexpressibly soothing to the chest! A delicious numbness steals through all my members. I would sleep.

MAGNESIA–
FITZ ——> [whispering together] Let him sleep.
PHYLLIS–

He sleeps. Celestial harps are heard, but their chords cease on the abrupt entrance of the landlord, a vulgar person in pyjamas.

THE LANDLORD. Eah! Eah! Wots this? Wots all this noise? Ah kin ennybody sleep through it? [Looking at the floor and ceiling] Ellow! wot you bin doin te maw ceilin?

FITZ. Silence, or leave the room. If you wake that man he dies.

THE LANDLORD. If e kin sleep through the noise you three mikes e kin sleep through ennythink.

MAGNESIA. Detestable vulgarian: your pronunciation jars on the finest chords of my nature. Begone!

THE LANDLORD. [looking at Adolphus] Aw downt blieve eze esleep. Aw blieve eze dead. [Calling] Pleece! Pleecel Merder! [A blue halo plays mysteriously on the door,which opens and reveals a policeman. Thunder] Eah, pleecmin: these three's bin an murdered this gent between em, an naw tore moy ahse dahn.

THE POLICEMAN. [offended] Policeman, indeed! Wheres your manners?

FITZ. Officer—

THE POLICEMAN. [with distinguished consideration] Sir?

FITZ. As between gentlemen—

THE POLICEMAN. [bowing] Sir. to you.

FITZ. [bowing] I may inform you that my friend had an acute attack of indigestion. No carbonate of soda being available, he swallowed a portion of this man's ceiling. [Pointing to Adolphus] Behold the result!

THE POLICEMAN. The ceiling was poisoned! Well, of all the artful— [he collars the landlord.] I arrest you for wilful murder.

THE LANDLORD. [appealing to the heavens] Ow, is this jesticel Ah could aw tell e wiz gowin te eat moy ceilin?

THE POLICEMAN. [releasing him] True. The case is more complicated than I thought [He tries to lift Adolphus's arm but cannot.] Stiff already.

THE LANDLORD [trying to lift Adolphus's leg] An' precious evvy.[Feeling the calf] Woy, eze gorn ez awd ez niles.

FITZ [rushing to the bed] What is this?

MAGNESIA. Oh, say not he is dead. Phyllis: fetch a doctor. [Phyllis runs out. They all try to lift Adolphus, but he is perfectly stiff, and as heavy as lead.] Rouse him. Shake him.

THE POLICEMAN. [exhausted] Whew! Is he a man or a statue? [Magnesia utters a piercing scream.] Whats wrong, Miss?

MAGNESIA. [to Fitz] Do you not see what has happened?

FITZ. [striking his forehead] Horror on horror's head!

THE LANDLORD. Wotjemean?

MAGNESIA The plaster has set inside him. The officer was right: he is indeed a living statue.

Magnesia flings herself on the stony breast of Adolphus. Fitztollemache buries his head in his hands, and his chest heaves convulsively. The policeman takes a small volume from his pocket and consults it.

THE POLICEMAN. This case is not provided for in my book of instructions. It dont seem no use trying artificial respiration, do it? [To the landlord] Here! lend a hand, you. We'd best take him and set him up in Trafalgar Square.

THE LANDLORD. Aushd pat im in the cestern an worsh it aht of im.

Phyllis comes back with a Doctor.

PHYLLIS. The medical man, my lady.

THE POLICEMAN. A poison case, sir.

THE DOCTOR. Do you mean to say that an unqualified person! a layman! has dared to administer poison in my district?

THE POLICEMAN. [raising Magnesia tenderly] It looks like it. Hold up, my lady.

THE DOCTOR Not a moment must be lost The patient must be kept awake at all costs. Constant and violent motion is necessary. [He snatches Magnesia from the policeman, and rushes her about the room.]

FITZ. Stop! That is not the poisoned person!

THE DOCTOR. It is you, then. Why did you not say so before?[He seizes Fitztollemache and rushes him about.]

THE LANDLORD. Naow, naow, thet ynt im.

THE DOCTOR. What, you! [He pounces on the landlord and rushes him round.]

THE LANDLORD. Eah! chack it [He trips the doctor up. Both fall.] Jest owld this leoonatic, will you. Mister Horficer?

THE POLICEMAN. [dragging both of them to their feet] Come out of it, will you. You must all come with me to me station.

Thunder.

MAGNESIA What! In this frightful storm!

The hail patters noisily on the window.

PHYLLIS. I think it's raining.

The wind howls.

THE LANDLORD. It's thanderin and lawtnin.

FITZ. It's dangerous.

THE POLICEMAN [drawing his baton and whistle] If you wont come quietly, then—

He whistles. A fearful flash is followed by an appalling explosion of heaven's artillery. A thunderbolt enters the room, and strikes the helmet of the devoted constable, whence it is attracted to the waistcoat of the doctor by the lancet in his pocket. Finally it leaps with fearful force on the landlord, who, being of a gross and spongy nature, absorbs the electric fluid at the cost of his life. The others look on horrorstricken as the three victims, after reeling, jostling, cannoning through a ghastly quadrille, at last sink inanimate on the carpet.

MAGNESIA [listening at the doctor's chest] Dead!

FITZ. [kneeling by the landlord, and raising his hand, which drops with a thud] Dead!

PHYLLIS [seizing the looking-glass and holding it to the Policeman's lips] Dead!

FITZ [solemnly rising] The copper attracted the lightning.

MAGNESIA [rising] After life's fitful fever they sleep well. Phyllis: sweep them up.

Phyllis replaces the looking-glass on the dressing-table, takes up the fan, and fans the policeman, who rolls away like a leaf before the wind, to the wall. She disposes similarly of the landlord and doctor.

PHYLLIS Will they be in your way if I leave them there until morning, my lady? Or shall I bring up the ashpan and take them away?

MAGNESIA. They will not disturb us. Goodnight, Phyllis.

PHYLLIS. Goodnight, my lady. Goodnight, sir. [She retires.]

MAGNESIA. And now, husband, let us perform our last sad duty to our friend. He has become his own monument. Let us erect him. He is heavy; but love can do much.

FITZ. A litte leverage will get him on his feet Give me my umbrella.

MAGNESIA. True.

She hands him the umbrella, and takes up the bootjack.They get them under Adolphus's back, and prize him up on his feet.

FITZ. Thats done it! Whew!

MAGNESIA. [kneeling at the left hand of the statue] For ever and for ever, Adolphus.

FITZ.[kneeling at the right hand of the statue] The rest is silence.

The Angels sing Bill Bailey. The statue raises its hands in an attitude of blessing, and turns its limelit face to heaven as the curtain falls. National Anthem.

ATTENDANTS [in front] All out for the next performance. Pass along, please, ladies and gentlemen: pass along.

Press Cuttings

By direction of the Lord Chamberlain the General and the Prime Minister in this play must in all public performances of it be addressed and described as General Bones and Mr. Johnson, and by no means as General Mitchener and Mr. Balsquith. The allusions to commoner persons are allowed to stand as they are.

General Mitchener, by the way, is not the late Lord Kitchener, but an earlier and more highly connected commander. Balsquith (Balfour-Asquith) is obviously neither of these statesmen, and cannot in the course of nature be both.

Dramatis Personae

Character, a character

Scene: A scene.

Press Cuttings

The forenoon of the first of April, 1911.

General Mitchener is at his writing table in the War Office, opening letters. On his left is the fireplace, with a fire burning. On his right, against the opposite wall, is a standing desk with an office stool. The door is in the wall behind him, half way between the table and the desk. The table is not quite in the middle of the room: it is nearer to the hearthrug than to the desk. There is a chair at each end of it for persons having business with the General. There is a telephone on the table.

Long silence.

A Voice Outside | Votes for Women!
The General starts convulsively; snatches a revolver from a drawer; and listens in an agony of apprehension. Nothing happens. He puts the revolver back, ashamed; wipes his brow; and resumes his work. He is startled afresh by the entry of an Orderly. This Orderly is an unsoldierly, slovenly, discontented young man.
Mitchener | Oh, it’s only you. Well?
The Orderly | Another one, sir. She’s chained herself.
Mitchener | Chained herself? How? To what? We’ve taken away the railings and everything that a chain can be passed through.
The Orderly | We forgot the doorscraper, sir. She lay down on the flags and got the chain through before she started hollerin’. She’s lyin’ there now; and she downfaces us that you’ve got the key of the padlock in a letter in a buff envelope, and that you’ll see her when you open it.
Mitchener | She’s mad. Have the scraper dug up and let her go home with it hanging round her neck.
The Orderly | There is a buff envelope there, sir.
Mitchener | You’re all afraid of these women. He picks the letter up. It does seem to have a key in it. He opens the letter; takes out a key and a note; and reads: “Dear Mitch”—Well, I’m dashed!
The Orderly | Yes, sir.
Mitchener | What do you mean by ”Yes, sir”?
The Orderly | Well, you said you was dashed, sir; and you did look—if you’ll excuse my saying it, sir—well, you looked it.
Mitchener | Who has been reading the letter, and is too astonished to attend to the Orderly’s reply. This is a letter from the Prime Minister asking me to release the woman with this key if she padlocks herself, and to have her shown up and see her at once.
The Orderly | Tremulously. Don’t do it, governor.
Mitchener | Angrily. How often have I ordered you not to address me as “governor.” Remember that you are a soldier and not a vulgar civilian. Remember also that when a man enters the army he leaves fear behind him. Here’s the key. Unlock her and show her up.
The Orderly | Me unlock her! I dursen’t. Lord knows what she’d do to me.
Mitchener | Pepperily, rising. Obey your orders instantly, sir; and don’t presume to argue. Even if she kills you, it is your duty to die for your country. Right about face. March.
The Orderly goes out, trembling.
The Voice Outside | Votes for Women! Votes for Women! Votes for Women!
Mitchener | Mimicking her. Votes for Women! Votes for Women! Votes for Women! In his natural voice. Votes for children! Votes for babies! Votes for monkeys! He posts himself on the hearthrug and awaits the enemy.
The Orderly | Outside. In you go. He pushes a panting Suffragette into the room. The person, sir. He withdraws.
The Suffragette takes off her tailor made skirt and reveals a pair of fashionable trousers.
Mitchener | Horrified. Stop, madam. What are you doing? You must not undress in my presence. I protest. Not even your letter from the Prime Minister—
The Suffragette | My dear Mitchener: I am the Prime Minister. He takes off his hat and cloak; throws them on the desk; and confronts the General in the ordinary costume of a Cabinet Minister.
Mitchener | Good heavens! Balsquith!
Balsquith | Throwing himself into Mitchener’s chair. Yes: it is indeed Balsquith. It has come to this: that the only way that the Prime Minister of England can get from Downing Street to the War Office is by assuming this disguise; shrieking “Votes for Women”; and chaining himself to your doorscraper. They were at the corner in force. They cheered me. Bellachristina herself was there. She shook my hand and told me to say I was a vegetarian, as the diet was better in Holloway for vegetarians.
Mitchener | Why didn’t you telephone?
Balsquith | They tap the telephone. Every switchboard in London is in their hands, or in those of their young men.
Mitchener | Where on earth did you get the dress? I hope it’s not a French dress!
Balsquith | I stole it from a little Exhibition got up by my wife in Downing Street.
Mitchener | You don’t mean to say its a French dress?
Balsquith | Great heavens, no. We’re not allowed even to put on our gloves with French chalk. Everything’s labelled “Made in Camberwell.”
Mitchener | As a Tariff Reformer, I must say “Quite right.” Balsquith has a strong controversial impulse and is evidently going to dispute this profession of faith. No matter. Don’t argue. What have you come for?
Balsquith | Sandstone has resigned.
Mitchener | Amazed. Old Red resigned!
Balsquith | Resigned.
Mitchener | But how? Why? Oh, impossible! the proclamation of martial law last Tuesday made Sandstone virtually Dictator in the metropolis, and to resign now is flat desertion.
Balsquith | Yes, yes, my dear Mitchener; I know all that as well as you do: I argued with him until I was black in the face, and he so red about the neck that if I had gone on he would have burst. He is furious because we have abandoned his plan.
Mitchener | But you accepted it unconditionally.
Balsquith | Yes, before we knew what it was. It was unworkable, you know.
Mitchener | I don’t know. Why is it unworkable?
Balsquith | I mean the part about drawing a cordon round Westminster at a distance of two miles, and turning all women out of it.
Mitchener | A masterpiece of strategy. Let me explain. The Suffragettes are a very small body; but they are numerous enough to be troublesome—even dangerous—when they are all concentrated in one place—say in Parliament Square. But by making a two-mile radius and pushing them beyond it, you scatter their attack over a circular line twelve miles long. A superb piece of tactics. Just what Wellington would have done.
Balsquith | But the women won’t go.
Mitchener | Nonsense: they must go.
Balsquith | They won’t.
Mitchener | What does Sandstone say?
Balsquith | He says: Shoot them down.
Mitchener | Of course.
Balsquith | You’re not serious?
Mitchener | Im perfectly serious.
Balsquith | But you can’t shoot them down! Women, you know!
Mitchener | Straddling confidently. Yes you can. Strange as it may seem to you as a civilian, Balsquith, if you point a rifle at a woman and fire it, she will drop exactly as a man drops.
Balsquith | But suppose your own daughters—Helen and Georgina—
Mitchener | My daughters would not dream of disobeying the proclamation. As an afterthought. At least Helen wouldn’t.
Balsquith | But Georgina?
Mitchener | Georgina would if she knew she’d be shot if she didnt. That’s how the thing would work. Military methods are really the most merciful in the end. You keep sending these misguided women to Holloway and killing them slowly and inhumanely by ruining their health; and it does no good: they go on worse than ever. Shoot a few, promptly and humanely; and there will be an end at once of all resistance and of all the suffering that resistance entails.
Balsquith | But public opinion would never stand it.
Mitchener | Walking about and laying down the law. There’s no such thing as public opinion.
Balsquith | No such thing as public opinion!!
Mitchener | Absolutely no such thing. There are certain persons who entertain certain opinions. Well, shoot them down. When you have shot them down, there are no longer any persons entertaining those opinions alive, consequently there is no longer any more of the public opinion you are so much afraid of. Grasp that fact, my dear Balsquith; and you have grasped the secret of government. Public opinion is mind. Mind is inseparable from matter. Shoot down the matter and you kill the mind.
Balsquith | But hang it all—
Mitchener | Intolerantly. No I won’t hang it all. It’s no use coming to me and talking about public opinion. You have put yourself into the hands of the army; and you are committed to military methods. And the basis of all military methods is that when people won’t do what they are told to do, you shoot them down.
Balsquith | Oh, yes; it’s all jolly fine for you and Old Red. You don’t depend on votes for your places. What do you suppose would happen at the next election?
Mitchener | Have no next election. Bring in a Bill at once repealing all the Reform Acts and vesting the Government in a properly trained magistracy responsible only to a Council of War. It answers perfectly in India. If anyone objects, shoot him down.
Balsquith | But none of the members of my party would be on the Council of War. Neither should I. Do you expect us to vote for making ourselves nobodies?
Mitchener | You’ll have to, sooner or later, or the Socialists will make nobodies of the lot of you by collaring every penny you possess. Do you suppose this damned democracy can be allowed to go on now that the mob is beginning to take it seriously and using its power to lay hands on property? Parliament must abolish itself. The Irish parliament voted for its own extinction. The English parliament will do the same if the same means are taken to persuade it.
Balsquith | That would cost a lot of money.
Mitchener | Not money necessarily. Bribe them with titles.
Balsquith | Do you think we dare?
Mitchener | Scornfully. Dare! Dare! What is life but daring, man? “To dare, to dare, and again to dare”—
Female Voice in the Street | Votes for Women! Mitchener, revolver in hand, rushes to the door and locks it. Balsquith hides under the table. Votes for Women!
A shot is heard.
Balsquith | Emerging in the greatest alarm. Good heavens, you haven’t given orders to fire on them: have you?
Mitchener | No; but its a sentinel’s duty to fire on anyone who persists in attempting to pass without giving the word.
Balsquith | Wiping his brow. This military business is really awful.
Mitchener | Be calm, Balsquith. These things must happen; they save bloodshed in the long run, believe me. I’ve seen plenty of it; and I know.
Balsquith | I haven’t; and I don’t know. I wish those guns didn’t make such a devil of a noise. We must adopt Maxim’s Silencer for the army rifles if we’re going to shoot women. I really couldn’t stand hearing it. Someone outside tries to open the door and then knocks. What’s that?
Mitchener | Who’s there?
The Orderly | It’s only me, governor. Its all right.
Mitchener | Unlocking the door and admitting the Orderly, who comes between them. What was it?
The Orderly | Suffragette, sir.
Balsquith | Did the sentry shoot her?
The Orderly | No, sir: she shot the sentry.
Balsquith | Relieved. Oh: is that all?
Mitchener | Most indignantly. All? A civilian shoots down one of His Majesty’s soldiers on duty; and the Prime Minister of England asks, Is that all?!!! Have you no regard for the sanctity of human life?
Balsquith | Much relieved. Well, getting shot is what a soldier is for. Besides, he doesn’t vote.
Mitchener | Neither do the Suffragettes.
Balsquith | Their husbands do. To the Orderly. Did she kill him?
The Orderly | No, sir. He got a stinger on his trousers, sir; but it didn’t penetrate. He lost his temper a bit and put down his gun and clouted her head for her. So she said he was no gentleman; and we let her go, thinking she’d had enough, sir.
Mitchener | Groaning. Clouted her head! These women are making the army as lawless as themselves. Clouted her head indeed! A purely civil procedure.
The Orderly | Any orders, sir?
Mitchener | No. Yes. No. Yes: send everybody who took part in this disgraceful scene to the guardroom. No. I’ll address the men on the subject after lunch. Parade them for that purpose: full kit. Don’t grin at me, Sir. Right about face. March.
The Orderly obeys and goes out.
Balsquith | Taking Mitchener affectionately by the arm and walking him persuasively to and fro. And now, Mitchener, will you come to the rescue of the Government and take the command that Old Red has thrown up?
Mitchener | How can I? You know that the people are devoted heart and soul to Sandstone. He is only bringing you “on the knee,” as we say in the army. Could any other living man have persuaded the British nation to accept universal compulsory military service as he did last year? Why, even the Church refused exemption. He is supreme—omnipotent.
Balsquith | He was, a year ago. But ever since your book of reminiscences went into two more editions than his, and the rush for it led to the wrecking of the Times Book Club, you have become to all intents and purposes his senior. He lost ground by saying that the wrecking was got up by the booksellers. It showed jealousy; and the public felt it.
Mitchener | But I cracked him up in my book—you see I could do no less after the handsome way he cracked me up in his—and I can’t go back on it now. Breaking loose from Balsquith. No: its no use, Balsquith: he can dictate his terms to you.
Balsquith | Not a bit of it. That affair of the curate—
Mitchener | Impatiently. Oh, damn that curate. I’ve heard of nothing but that wretched mutineer for a fortnight past. He is not a curate: whilst he is serving in the army he is a private soldier and nothing else. I really haven’t time to discuss him further. Im busy. Good morning. He sits down at his table and takes up his letters.
Balsquith | Near the door. I am sorry you take that tone, Mitchener. Since you do take it, let me tell you frankly that I think Lieutenant Chubbs-Jenkinson showed a great want of consideration for the Government in giving an unreasonable and unpopular order, and bringing compulsory military service into disrepute.
Mitchener | No order is unreasonable; and all orders are unpopular.
Balsquith | When the leader of the Labor Party appealed to me and to the House last year not to throw away all the liberties of Englishmen by accepting compulsory military service without full civil rights for the soldier—
Mitchener | Rot.
Balsquith | —I said that no British officer would be capable of abusing the authority with which it was absolutely necessary to invest him.
Mitchener | Quite right.
Balsquith | That carried the House;—
Mitchener | Naturally.
Balsquith | —and the feeling was that the Labor Party were soulless cads.
Mitchener | So they are.
Balsquith | And now comes this unmannerly young whelp Chubbs-Jenkinson, the only son of what they call a soda king, and orders a curate to lick his boots. And when the curate punches his head, you first sentence him to be shot; and then make a great show of clemency by commuting it to a flogging. What did you expect the curate to do?
Mitchener | Throwing down his pen and his letters and jumping up to confront Balsquith. His duty was perfectly simple. He should have obeyed the order; and then laid his complaint against the officer in proper form. He would have received the fullest satisfaction.
Balsquith | What satisfaction?
Mitchener | Chubbs-Jenkinson would have been reprimanded. In fact, he was reprimanded. Besides, the man was thoroughly insubordinate. You can’t deny that the very first thing he did when they took him down after flogging him was to walk up to Chubbs-Jenkinson and break his jaw. That showed there was no use flogging him; so now he will get two years hard labor; and serve him right!
Balsquith | I bet you a guinea he won’t get even a week. I bet you another that Chubbs-Jenkinson apologizes abjectly. You evidently haven’t heard the news.
Mitchener | What news?
Balsquith | It turns out that the curate is well connected. Mitchener staggers at the shock. He reels into his chair and buries his face in his hands over the blotter. Balsquith continues remorselessly, stooping over him to rub it in. He has three aunts in the peerage; Lady Richmond’s one of them; Mitchener punctuates these announcements with heartrending groans and they all adore him. The invitations for six garden parties and fourteen dances have been cancelled for all the subalterns in Chubbs’s regiment. Mitchener attempts to shoot himself.
Balsquith | Seizing the pistol. No: your country needs you, Mitchener.
Mitchener | Putting down the pistol. For my country’s sake. Balsquith, reassured, sits down. But what an infernal young fool Chubbs-Jenkinson is, not to know the standing of his man better! Why didn’t he know? It was his business to know. He ought to be flogged.
Balsquith | Probably he will be, by the other subalterns.
Mitchener | I hope so. Anyhow, out he goes. Out of the army. He or I.
Balsquith | Steady, steady. His father has subscribed a million to the party funds. We owe him a peerage.
Mitchener | I don’t care.
Balsquith | I do. How do you think parties are kept up? Not by the subscriptions of the local associations, I hope. They don’t pay for the gas at the meetings.
Mitchener | Man: can you not be serious? Here are we, face to face with Lady Richmond’s grave displeasure; and you talk to me about gas and subscriptions. Her own nephew!!!!!
Balsquith | Gloomily. Its unfortunate. He was at Oxford with Bobby Bessborough.
Mitchener | Worse and worse. What shall we do?
A Voice in the Street | Votes for Women! Votes for Women!
A terrific explosion shakes the building. They take no notice.
Mitchener | Breaking down. You don’t know what this means to me, Balsquith. I love the army. I love my country.
Balsquith | It certainly is rather awkward.
The Orderly comes in.
Mitchener | Angrily. What is it? How dare you interrupt us like this?
The Orderly | Didn’t you hear the explosion, sir?
Mitchener | Explosion. What explosion? No: I heard no explosion: I have something more serious to attend to than explosions. Great Heavens! Lady Richmond’s nephew has been treated like any common laborer; and while England is reeling under the shock, a private walks in and asks me if I heard an explosion.
Balsquith | By the way, what was the explosion?
The Orderly | Only a sort of bombshell, sir.
Balsquith | Bombshell!
The Orderly | A pasteboard one, sir. Full of papers with Votes for Women in red letters. Fired into the yard from the roof of the Alliance Office.
Mitchener | Pooh! Go away. Go away.
The >Orderly, bewildered, goes out.
Balsquith | Mitchener: you can save the country yet. Put on your full dress uniform and your medals and orders and so forth. Get a guard of honor—something showy—horse guards or something of that sort; and call on the old girl—
Mitchener | The old girl?
Balsquith | Well, Lady Richmond. Apologize to her. Ask her leave to accept the command. Tell her that you’ve made the curate your adjutant or your aide-de-camp or whatever is the proper thing. By the way, what can you make him?
Mitchener | I might make him my chaplain. I don’t see why I shouldn’t have a chaplain on my staff. He showed a very proper spirit in punching that young cub’s head. I should have done the same myself.
Balsquith | Then I’ve your promise to take command if Lady Richmond consents?
Mitchener | On condition that I have a free hand. No nonsense about public opinion or democracy.
Balsquith | As far as possible, I think I may say yes.
Mitchener | Rising intolerantly and going to the hearthrug. That won’t do for me. Don’t be weak-kneed, Balsquith. You know perfectly well that the real government of this country is and always must be the government of the masses by the classes. You know that democracy is damned nonsense, and that no class stands less of it than the working class. You know that we are already discussing the steps that will have to be taken if the country should ever be face to face with the possibility of a Labor majority in parliament. You know that in that case we should disfranchise the mob, and if they made a fuss, shoot them down. You know that if we need public opinion to support us, we can get any quantity of it manufactured in our papers by poor devils of journalists who will sell their souls for five shillings. You know—
Balsquith | Stop. Stop, I say. I don’t know. That is the difference between your job and mine, Mitchener. After twenty years in the army a man thinks he knows everything. After twenty months in the Cabinet he knows that he knows nothing.
Mitchener | We learn from history—
Balsquith | We learn from history that men never learn anything from history. That’s not my own: its Hegel.
Mitchener | Who’s Hegel?
Balsquith | Dead. A German philosopher. He half rises, but recollects something and sits down again. Oh, confound it: that reminds me. The Germans have laid down four more Dreadnoughts.
Mitchener | Then you must lay down twelve.
Balsquith | Oh yes: its easy to say that; but think of what they’ll cost.
Mitchener | Think of what it would cost to be invaded by Germany and forced to pay an indemnity of five hundred millions.
Balsquith | But you said that if you got compulsory military service there would be an end of the danger of invasion.
Mitchener | On the contrary, my dear fellow, it increases the danger tenfold, because it increases German jealousy of our military supremacy.
Balsquith | After all, why should the Germans invade us?
Mitchener | Why shouldn’t they? What else has their army to do? What else are they building a navy for?
Balsquith | Well, we never think of invading Germany.
Mitchener | Yes, we do. I have thought of nothing else for the last ten years. Say what you will, Balsquith, the Germans have never recognized, and until they get a stern lesson, they never will recognize, the plain fact that the interests of the British Empire are paramount, and that the command of the sea belongs by nature to England.
Balsquith | But if they won’t recognize it, what can I do?
Mitchener | Shoot them down.
Balsquith | I can’t shoot them down.
Mitchener | Yes you can. You don’t realize it; but if you fire a rifle into a German he drops just as surely as a rabbit does.
Balsquith | But dash it all, man, a rabbit hasn’t got a rifle and a German has. Suppose he shoots you down.
Mitchener | Excuse me, Balsquith; but that consideration is what we call cowardice in the army. A soldier always assumes that he is going to shoot, not to be shot.
Balsquith | Jumping up and walking about sulkily. Oh come! I like to hear you military people talking of cowardice. Why, you spend your lives in an ecstasy of terror of imaginary invasions. I don’t believe you ever go to bed without looking under it for a burglar.
Mitchener | Calmly. A very sensible precaution, Balsquith. I always take it; and, in consequence, I’ve never been burgled.
Balsquith | Neither have I. Anyhow, don’t you taunt me with cowardice. He posts himself on the hearthrug beside Mitchener, on his left. I never look under my bed for a burglar. Im not always looking under the nation’s bed for an invader. And if it comes to fighting, Im quite willing to fight without being three to one.
Mitchener | These are the romantic ravings of a Jingo civilian, Balsquith. At least you’ll not deny that the absolute command of the sea is essential to our security.
Balsquith | The absolute command of the sea is essential to the security of the principality of Monaco. But Monaco isn’t going to get it.
Mitchener | And consequently Monaco enjoys no security. What a frightful thing! How do the inhabitants sleep with the possibility of invasion, of bombardment, continually present to their minds? Would you have our English slumbers broken in the same way? Are we also to live without security?
Balsquith | Dogmatically. Yes. There’s no such thing as security in the world: and there never can be as long as men are mortal. England will be secure when England is dead, just as the streets of London will be safe when theres no longer a man in her streets to be run over or a vehicle to run over him. When you military chaps ask for security you are crying for the moon.
Mitchener | Very seriously. Let me tell you, Balsquith, that in these days of aeroplanes and Zeppelin airships, the question of the moon is becoming one of the greatest importance. It will be reached at no very distant date. Can you as an Englishman, tamely contemplate the possibility of having to live under a German moon? The British flag must be planted there at all hazards.
Balsquith | My dear Mitchener, the moon is outside practical politics. I’d swap it for a coaling station tomorrow with Germany or any other Power sufficiently military in its way of thinking to attach any importance to it.
Mitchener | Losing his temper. You are the friend of every country but your own.
Balsquith | Say nobodys enemy but my own. It sounds nicer. You really needn’t be so horribly afraid of the other countries. They’re all in the same fix as we are. Im much more interested in the death rate in Lambeth than in the German fleet.
Mitchener | You daren’t say that in Lambeth.
Balsquith | I’ll say it the day after you publish your scheme for invading Germany and repealing all the Reform Acts.
The Orderly comes in.
Mitchener | What do you want?
The Orderly | I don’t want anything, Governor, thank you. The secretary and president of the Anti-Suffragette League say they had an appointment with the Prime Minister, and that they’ve been sent on here from Downing Street.
Balsquith | Going to the table. Quite right. I forgot them. To Mitchener. Would you mind my seeing them here? I feel extraordinarily grateful to these women for standing by us and facing the suffragettes, especially as they are naturally the gentler and timid sort of women. The Orderly moans. Did you say anything?
The Orderly | No, Sir.
Balsquith | Did you catch their names.
The Orderly | Yes, Sir. The president is Lady Corinthia Fanshawe; and the secretary is Mrs. Banger.
Mitchener | Abruptly. Mrs. what?
The Orderly | Mrs. Banger.
Balsquith | Curious that quiet people always seem to have violent names.
The Orderly | Not much quiet about her, sir.
Mitchener | Outraged. Attention. Speak when you’re spoken to. Hold your tongue when you’re not. Right about face. March. The Orderly obeys. That’s the way to keep these chaps up to the mark. The Orderly returns. Back again! What do you mean by this mutiny?
The Orderly | What am I to say to the ladies, sir?
Balsquith | You don’t mind my seeing them somewhere, do you?
Mitchener | Not at all. Bring them in to see me when you’ve done with them: I understand that Lady Corinthia is a very fascinating woman. Who is she, by the way?
Balsquith | Daughter of Lord Broadstairs, the automatic turbine man. Gave quarter of a million to the party funds. She’s musical and romantic and all that—don’t hunt: hates politics: stops in town all the year round: one never sees her anywhere except at the opera and at musical at-homes and so forth.
Mitchener | What a life! Still, if she wants to see me I don’t mind. To the Orderly. Where are the ladies?
The Orderly | In No. 17, Sir.
Mitchener | Show Mr. Balsquith there. And send Mrs. Farrell here.
The Orderly | Calling into the corridor. Mrs. Farrell! To Balsquith. This way sir. He goes out with Balsquith.
Mrs. Farrell, a lean, highly respectable Irish Charwoman of about 50 comes in.
Mitchener | Mrs. Farrell: I’ve a very important visit to pay: I shall want my full dress uniform and all my medals and orders and my presentation sword. There was a time when the British Army contained men capable of discharging these duties for their commanding officer. Those days are over. The compulsorily enlisted soldier runs to a woman for everything. Im therefore reluctantly obliged to trouble you.
Mrs. Farrell | Your meddles n ordhers n the crooked sword with the ivory handle n your full dress uniform is in the waxworks in the Chamber o Military Glory over in the place they used to call the Banquetin Hall. I told you you’d be sorry for sendin them away; n you told me to mind me own business. You’re wiser now.
Mitchener | I am. I had not at that time discovered that you were the only person in the whole military establishment of this capital who could be trusted to remember where anything was, or to understand an order and obey it.
Mrs. Farrell | Its no good flattherin me. Im too old.
Mitchener | Not at all, Mrs. Farrell. How is your daughter?
Mrs. Farrell | Which daughther.
Mitchener | The one who has made such a gratifying success in the Music Halls.
Mrs. Farrell | There’s no music halls nowadays: they’re Variety Theatres. She’s got an offer of marriage from a young jook.
Mitchener | Is it possible? What did you do?
Mrs. Farrell | I told his mother on him.
Mitchener | Oh! what did she say?
Mrs. Farrell | She was as pleased as Punch. Thank Heaven, she says, hes got somebody thatll be able to keep him when the supertax is put up to twenty shillings in the pound.
Mitchener | But your daughter herself? What did she say?
Mrs. Farrell | Accepted him, of course. What else would a young fool like her do? He inthrojooced her to the Poet Laureate, thinking shed inspire him.
Mitchener | Did she?
Mrs. Farrell | Faith I dunna. All I know is she walked up to him as bold as brass n said “Write me a sketch, dear.” Afther all the trouble I took with that chills manners she’s no more notion how to behave herself than a pig. You’ll have to wear General Sandstones uniform: its the ony one in the place, because he won’t lend it to the shows.
Mitchener | But Sandstones clothes won’t fit me.
Mrs. Farrell | Unmoved. Then you’ll have to fit them. Why shouldn’t they fitcha as well as they fitted General Blake at the Mansion House?
Mitchener | They didn’t fit him. He looked a frightful guy.
Mrs. Farrell | Well, you must do the best you can with them. You can’t exhibit your clothes and wear them too.
Mitchener | And the public thinks the lot of a commanding officer a happy one! Oh, if they could only see the seamy side of it. He returns to his table to resume work.
Mrs. Farrell | If they could only see the seamy side of General Sandstones uniform, where his flask rubs agen the buckle of his braces, they’ll tell him he ought to get a new one. Let alone the way he swears at me.
Mitchener | When a man has risked his life on eight battlefields, Mrs. Farrell, he has given sufficient proof of his self-control to be excused a little strong language.
Mrs. Farrell | Would you put up with bad language from me because I’ve risked my life eight times in childbed?
Mitchener | My dear Mrs. Farrell, you surely would not compare a risk of that harmless domestic kind to the fearful risks of the battlefield?
Mrs. Farrell | I wouldn’t compare risks run to bear living people into the world to risks run to blow them out of it. A mother’s risk is jooty: a soldier’s nothin but divilmint.
Mitchener | Nettled. Let me tell you, Mrs. Farrell, that if the men did not fight, the women would have to fight themselves. We spare you that, at all events.
Mrs. Farrell | You can’t help yourselves. If three-quarters of you was killed we could replace you with the help of the other quarter. If three-quarters of us was killed, how many people would there be in England in another generation? If it wasn’t for that, the man d put the fightin on us just as they put all the other dhrudgery. What would YOU do if we was all kilt? Would you go to bed and have twins?
Mitchener | Really, Mrs. Farrell, you must discuss these questions with a medical man. You make me blush, positively.
Mrs. Farrell | A good job too. If I could have made Farrell blush I wouldn’t have had to risk me life too often. You n your risks n your bravery n your self-control indeed! “Why don’t you conthrol yourself?” I sez to Farrell. “Its agen me religion,” he sez.
Mitchener | Plaintively. Mrs. Farrell, you’re a woman of very powerful mind. Im not qualified to argue these delicate matters with you. I ask you to spare me, and to be good enough to take these clothes to Mr. Balsquith when the ladies leave.
The Orderly comes in.
The Orderly | Lady Corinthia Fanshawe and Mrs. Banger wish to see you, sir. Mr. Balsquith told me to tell you.
Mrs. Farrell | They’ve come about the vote. I don’t know whether its them that want it or them that doesn’t want it: anyhow, they’re all alike when they get into a state about it. She goes out, having gathered Balsquith’s suffragette disguise from the desk.
Mitchener | Is Mr. Balsquith not with them?
The Orderly | No, Sir. Couldn’t stand Mrs. Banger, I expect. Fair caution she is. He chuckles. Couldn’t help larfin when I sor im op it.
Mitchener | How dare you indulge in this unseemly mirth in the presence of your commanding officer? Have you no sense of a soldier’s duty?
The Orderly | Sadly. Im afraid I shan’t ever get the ang of it, sir. You see my father has a tidy little barbers business down off Shoreditch; and I was brought up to be chatty and easy like with everybody. I tell you, when I drew the number in the conscription it gave my old mother the needle and it gev me the ump. I should take it very kind, sir, if you’d let me off the drill and let me shave you instead. You’d appreciate my qualities then: you would indeed sir. I shan’t never do myself justice at soljering, sir: I can’t bring myself to think of it as proper work for a man with an active mind, as you might say, sir. Arf of its only ousemaidin; and the other arf is dress-up and make-believe.
Mitchener | Stuff, Sir. Its the easiest life in the world. Once you learn your drill all you have to do is to hold your tongue and obey your orders.
The Orderly | But I do assure you, sir, arf the time they’re the wrong orders; and I get into trouble when I obey them. The sergeants orders is all right; but the officers don’t know what they’re talkin about. Why the orses knows better sometimes. “Fours” says Lieutenant Trevor at the gate of Bucknam Palace only this morning when we was on duty for a State visit to the Coal Trust. I was fourth man like in the first file; and when I started the orse eld back; and the sergeant was on to me straight. Threes, you bally fool, he whispers. And he was on to me again about it when we came back, and called me a fathead, he did. What am I to do, I says: the lieutenant’s orders was fours, I says. I’ll show you who’s lieutenant here, e says. In future you attend to my orders and not to iz, e says: what does he know about it? You didn’t give me any orders, I says. Couldn’t you see for yourself there wasn’t room for fours, e says: why can’t you THINK? General Mitchener tells me Im not to think but to obey orders, I says. Is Mitchener your sergeant or am I, e says in his bullyin way. You are, I says. Well, he says, you’ve got to do what your sergeant tells you: that’s discipline, he says. What am I to do for the General I says. You’re to let im talk, e says: that’s what es for.
Mitchener | Groaning. It is impossible for the human mind to conceive anything more dreadful than this. You’re a disgrace to the service.
The Orderly | Deeply wounded. The service is a disgrace to me. When my mother’s people pass me in the street with this uniform on, I ardly know which way to look. There never was a soldier in my family before.
Mitchener | There never was anything else in mine, sir.
The Orderly | My mother’s second cousin was one of the Parkinsons of Stepney. Almost in tears. What do you know of the feelings of a respectable family in the middle station of life? I can’t bear to be looked down on as a common soldier. Why can’t my father be let buy my discharge? You’ve done away with the soldier’s right to have his discharge bought for him by his relations. The country didn’t know you were going to do that or it would never have stood it. Is an Englishman to be made a mockery like this?
Mitchener | Silence. Attention. Right about face. March.
The Orderly | Retiring to the standing desk and bedewing it with passionate tears. Oh that I should have lived to be spoke to as if I was the lowest of the low. Me! that has shaved a City of London aldermen wiv me own hand.
Mitchener | Poltroon. Crybaby. Well, better disgrace yourself here than disgrace your country on the field of battle.
The Orderly | Angrily coming to the table. Who’s going to disgrace his country on the field of battle? Its not fightin I object to: its soljerin. Show me a German and I’ll have a go at him as fast as you or any man. But to ave me time wasted like this, an be stuck in a sentry box at a street corner for an ornament to be stared at; and to be told “right about face: march” if I speak as one man to another: that ain’t pluck: that ain’t fightin: that ain’t patriotism: its bein made a bloomin sheep of.
Mitchener | A sheep has many valuable military qualities. Emulate them: don’t disparage them.
The Orderly | Oh, wots the good of talkin to you? If I wasn’t a poor soldier I could punch your head for forty shillins for a month. But because you’re my commanding officer you deprive me of my right to a magistrate and make a compliment of giving me two years ard sted of shootin me. Why can’t you take your chance the same as any civilian does?
Mitchener | Rising majestically. I search the pages of history in vain for a parallel to such a speech made by a Private to a general. But for the coherence of your remarks I should conclude that you were drunk. As it is, you must be mad. You shall be placed under restraint at once. Call the guard.
The Orderly | Call your grandmother. If you take one man off the doors the place’ll be full of Suffragettes before you can wink.
Mitchener | Then arrest yourself; and off with you to the guardroom.
The Orderly | What am I to arrest myself for?
Mitchener | That’s nothing to you. You have your orders: obey them. Do you hear? Right about face. March.
The Orderly | How would you feel yourself if you was told to right-about-face and march as if you was a doormat?
Mitchener | I should feel as if my country had spoken through the voice of my officer. I should feel proud and honored to be able to serve my country by obeying its commands. No thought of self—no vulgar preoccupation with my own petty vanity could touch my mind at such a moment. To me my officer would not be a mere man: he would be for the moment—whatever his personal frailties—the incarnation of our national destiny.
The Orderly | What Im saying to you is the voice of old England a jolly sight more than all this rot that you get out of books. I’d rather be spoke to by a sergeant than by you. He tells me to go to hell when I challenges him to argue it out like a man. It ain’t polite; but its English. What you say ain’t anything at all. You don’t act on it yourself. You don’t believe in it. You’d punch my head if I tried it on you; and serve me right. And look here. Here’s another point for you to argue.
Mitchener | With a shriek of protest. No—
Mrs. Banger comes in, followed by Lady Corinthia Fanshawe. Mrs. Banger is a masculine woman of forty, with a powerful voice and great physical strength. Lady Corinthia, who is also over thirty, is beautiful and romantic.
Mrs. Banger | Throwing the door open decisively and marching straight to Michener. Pray how much longer is the Anti-Suffrage League to be kept waiting? She passes him contemptuously and sits down with impressive confidence in the chair next the fireplace. Lady Corinthia takes the chair on the opposite side of the table with equal aplomb.
Mitchener | Im extremely sorry. You really do not know what I have to put with. This imbecile, incompetent, unsoldierly disgrace to the uniform he should never have been allowed to put on, ought to have shown you in fifteen minutes ago.
The Orderly | All I said was—
Mitchener | Not another word. Attention. Right about face. March. The Orderly sits down doggedly. Get out of the room this instant, you fool, or I’ll kick you out.
The Orderly | Civilly. I don’t mind that, sir. Its human. Its English. Why couldn’t you have said it before? He goes out.
Mitchener | Take no notice I beg: these scenes are of daily occurrence now that we have compulsory service under the command of the halfpenny papers. Pray sit down.
Lady Corinthia and Mrs. Banger | Rising. Thank you. They sit down again.
Mitchener | Sitting down with a slight chuckle of satisfaction. And now, ladies, to what am I indebted?
Mrs. Banger | Let me introduce us. I am Rosa Carmina Banger—Mrs. Banger, organizing secretary of the Anti-Suffragette League. This is Lady Corinthia Fanshawe, the president of the League, known in musical circles—I am not myself musical—as the Richmond Park nightingale. A soprano. I am myself said to be almost a baritone; but I do not profess to understand these distinctions.
Mitchener | Murmuring politely. Most happy, Im sure.
Mrs. Banger | We have come to tell you plainly that the Anti-Suffragettes are going to fight.
Mitchener | Gallantly. Oh, pray leave that to the men, Mrs. Banger.
Lady Corinthia | We can no longer trust the men.
Mrs. Banger | They have shown neither the strength, the courage, nor the determination which are needed to combat women like the Suffragettes.
Lady Corinthia | Nature is too strong for the combatants.
Mrs. Banger | Physical struggles between persons of opposite sexes are unseemly.
Lady Corinthia | Demoralizing.
Mrs. Banger | Insincere.
Lady Corinthia | They are merely embraces in disguise.
Mrs. Banger | No such suspicion can attach to combats in which the antagonists are of the same sex.
Lady Corinthia | The Anti-Suffragettes have resolved to take the field.
Mrs. Banger | They will enforce the order of General Sandstone for the removal of all women from the two mile radius—that is, all women except themselves.
Mitchener | I am sorry to have to inform you, Madam, that the Government has given up that project, and that General Sandstone has resigned in consequence.
Mrs. Banger | That does not concern us in the least. We approve of the project and will see that it is carried out. We have spent a good deal of money arming ourselves; and we are not going to have that money thrown away through the pusillanimity of a Cabinet of males.
Mitchener | Arming yourselves! But, my dear ladies, under the latest proclamation women are strictly forbidden to carry chains, padlocks, tracts on the franchise, or weapons of any description.
Lady Corinthia | Producing an ivory-handled revolver and pointing it at his nose. You little know your countrywomen, General Mitchener.
Mitchener | Without flinching. Madam: it is my duty to take possession of that weapon in accordance with the proclamation. Be good enough to put it down.
Mrs. Banger | Producing an XVIII century horse pistol. Is it your duty to take possession of this also?
Mitchener | That, madam, is not a weapon; it is a curiosity. If you would be kind enough to place it in some museum instead of pointing it at my head, I should be obliged to you.
Mrs. Banger | This pistol, sir, was carried at Waterloo by my grandmother.
Mitchener | I presume you mean your grandfather.
Mrs. Banger | You presume unwarrantably.
Lady Corinthia | Mrs. Banger’s grandmother commanded a canteen at that celebrated battle.
Mrs. Banger | Who my grandfather was is a point that has never been quite clearly settled. I put my trust not in my ancestors, but in my good sword, which is at my lodgings.
Mitchener | Your sword!
Mrs. Banger | The sword with which I slew five Egyptians with my own hand at Kassassin, where I served as a trooper.
Mitchener | Lord bless me! But was your sex never discovered?
Mrs. Banger | It was never even suspected. I had a comrade—a gentleman ranker—whom they called Fanny. They never called ME Fanny.
Lady Corinthia | The suffragettes have turned the whole woman movement on to the wrong track. They ask for a vote.
Mrs. Banger | What use is a vote? Men have the vote.
Lady Corinthia | And men are slaves.
Mrs. Banger | What women need is the right to military service. Give me a well-mounted regiment of women with sabres, opposed to a regiment of men with votes. We shall see which will go down before the other. Rises. No: we have had enough of these gentle pretty creatures who merely talk and cross-examine ministers in police courts, and go to prison like sheep, and suffer and sacrifice themselves. This question must be solved by blood and iron, as was well said by Bismarck, whom I have reason to believe was a woman in disguise.
Mitchener | Bismarck a woman?
Mrs. Banger | All the really strong men of history have been disguised women.
Mitchener | Remonstrating. My dear lady!
Mrs. Banger | How can you tell? You never knew that the hero of the charge at Kassassin was a woman: yet she was: it was I, Rosa Carmina Banger. Would Napoleon have been so brutal to women, think you, had he been a man?
Mitchener | Oh, come, come! Really! Surely female rulers have often shown all the feminine weaknesses. Queen Elizabeth, for instance. Her vanity, her levity.
Mrs. Banger | Nobody who has studied the history of Queen Elizabeth can doubt for a moment that she was a disguised man.
Lady Corinthia | Admiring Mrs. Banger. Isn’t she splendid?
Mrs. Banger | Rising with a large gesture. This very afternoon I shall cast off this hampering skirt forever; mount my charger; and with my good sabre lead the Anti-Suffragettes to victory. She strides to the other side of the room, snorting.
Mitchener | But I can’t allow anything of the sort, madam. I shall stand no such ridiculous nonsense. Im perfectly determined to put my foot down.
Lady Corinthia | Don’t be hysterical, General.
Mitchener | Hysterical!
Mrs. Banger | Do you think we are to be stopped by these childish exhibitions of temper. They are useless; and your tears and entreaties—a man’s last resource—will avail you just as little. I sweep them away, just as I sweep your plans of campaign “made in Germany—”
Mitchener | Flying into a transport of rage. How dare you repeat that infamous slander? He rings the bell violently. If this is the alternative to votes for women, I shall advocate giving every woman in the country six votes. The Orderly comes in. Remove that woman. See that she leaves the building at once.
The Orderly forlornly contemplates the iron front presented by Mrs. Banger.
The Orderly | Propitiatorily. Would you av the feelin art to step out, madam.
Mrs. Banger | You are a soldier. Obey your orders. Put me out. If I got such an order, I should not hesitate.
The Orderly | To Mitchener. Would you mind lendin me a and, Guvner?
Lady Corinthia | Raising her revolver. I shall be obliged to shoot you if you stir, General.
Mrs. Banger | To the Orderly. When you are ordered to put a person out you should do it like this. She hurls him from the room. He is heard falling headlong downstairs and crashing through a glass door. I shall now wait on General Sandstone. If he shows any sign of weakness, he shall share that poor wretch’s fate. She goes out.
Lady Corinthia | Isn’t she magnificent?
Mitchener | Thank heaven she’s gone. And now, my dear lady, is it necessary to keep that loaded pistol to my nose all through our conversation?
Lady Corinthia | Its not loaded. Its heavy enough, goodness knows, without putting bullets in it.
Mitchener | Triumphantly snatching his revolver from the drawer. Then I am master of the situation. This is loaded. Ha, ha!
Lady Corinthia | But since we are not really going to shoot one another, what difference can it possibly make?
Mitchener | Putting his pistol down on the table. True. Quite true. I recognize there the practical good sense that has prevented you from falling into the snares of the Suffragettes.
Lady Corinthia | The Suffragettes, General, are the dupes of dowdies. A really attractive and clever woman—
Mitchener | Gallantly. Yourself, for instance.
Lady Corinthia | Snatching up his revolver. Another step and you are a dead man.
Mitchener | Amazed. My dear lady!
Lady Corinthia | I am not your dear lady. You are not the first man who has concluded that because I am devoted to music and can reach F flat with the greatest facility—Patti never got above E flat—I am marked out as the prey of every libertine. You think I am like the thousands of weak women whom you have ruined—
Mitchener | I solemnly protest—
Lady Corinthia | Oh, I know what you officers are. To you a woman’s honor is nothing, and the idle pleasure of the moment is everything.
Mitchener | This is perfectly ridiculous. I never ruined anyone in my life.
Lady Corinthia | Never! Are you in earnest?
Mitchener | Certainly I am in earnest. Most indignantly in earnest.
Lady Corinthia | Throwing down the pistol contemptuously. Then you have no temperament; you are not an artist. You have no soul for music.
Mitchener | I’ve subscribed to the regimental band all my life. I bought two sarrusophones for it out of my own pocket. When I sang Tosti’s Goodbye for Ever at Knightsbridge in 1880, the whole regiment wept. You are too young to remember that.
Lady Corinthia | Your advances are useless. I—
Mitchener | Confound it, madam, can you not receive an innocent compliment without suspecting me of dishonorable intentions?
Lady Corinthia | Love—real love—makes all intentions honorable. But YOU could never understand that.
Mitchener | I’ll not submit to the vulgar penny-novelette notion that an officer is less honorable than a civilian in his relations with women. While I live I’ll raise my voice—
Lady Corinthia | Tush!
Mitchener | What do you mean by tush?
Lady Corinthia | You can’t raise your voice above its natural compass. What sort of voice have you?
Mitchener | A tenor. What sort had you?
Lady Corinthia | Had? I have it still. I tell you I am the highest living soprano. Scornfully. What was your highest note, pray?
Mitchener | B flat—once—in 1879. I was drunk at the time.
Lady Corinthia | Gazing at him almost tenderly. Though you may not believe me, I find you are more interesting when you talk about music than when you are endeavoring to betray a woman who has trusted you by remaining alone with you in your apartment.
Mitchener | Springing up and fuming away to the fireplace. These repeated insults to a man of blameless life are as disgraceful to you as they are undeserved by me, Lady Corinthia. Such suspicions invite the conduct they impute. She raises the pistol. You need not be alarmed: I am only going to leave the room.
Lady Corinthia | Fish.
Mitchener | Fish! This is worse than tush. Why fish?
Lady Corinthia | Yes, fish: coldblooded fish.
Mitchener | Dash it all, madam, do you WANT me to make advances to you?
Lady Corinthia | I have not the slightest intention of yielding to them; but to make them would be a tribute to romance. What is life without romance?
Mitchener | Making a movement toward her. I tell you—
Lady Corinthia | Stop. No nearer. No vulgar sensuousness. If you must adore, adore at a distance.
Mitchener | This is worse than Mrs. Banger. I shall ask that estimable woman to come back.
Lady Corinthia | Poor Mrs. Banger! Do not for a moment suppose, General Mitchener, that Mrs. Banger represents my views on the suffrage question. Mrs. Banger is a man in petticoats. I am every inch a woman; but I find it convenient to work with her.
Mitchener | Do you find the combination comfortable?
Lady Corinthia | I do not wear combinations, General: with dignity they are unwomanly.
Mitchener | Throwing himself despairingly into the chair next the hearthrug. I shall go mad. I never for a moment dreamt of alluding to anything of the sort.
Lady Corinthia | There is no need to blush and become self-conscious at the mention of underclothing. You are extremely vulgar, General.
Mitchener | Lady Corinthia: you have my pistol. Will you have the goodness to blow my brains out. I should prefer it to any further effort to follow the gyrations of the weathercock you no doubt call your mind. If you refuse, then I warn you that you’ll not get another word out of me—not if we sit here until doomsday.
Lady Corinthia | I don’t want you to talk. I want you to listen. You do not yet understand my views on the question of the Suffrage. She rises to make a speech. I must preface my remarks by reminding you that the Suffragette movement is essentially a dowdy movement. The suffragettes are not all dowdies; but they are mainly supported by dowdies. Now I am not a dowdy. Oh, no compliments—
Mitchener | I did not utter a sound.
Lady Corinthia | Smiling. It is easy to read your thoughts. I am one of those women who are accustomed to rule the world through men. Man is ruled by beauty, by charm. The men who are not have no influence. The Salic Law, which forbade women to occupy a throne, is founded on the fact that when a woman is on the throne the country is ruled by men, and therefore ruled badly; whereas when a man is on the throne, the country is ruled by women, and therefore ruled well. The suffragettes would degrade women from being rulers to being voters, mere politicians, the drudges of the caucus and the polling booth. We should lose our influence completely under such a state of affairs. The New Zealand women have the vote. What is the result? No poet ever makes a New Zealand woman his heroine. One might as well be romantic about New Zealand mutton. Look at the suffragettes themselves. The only ones who are popular are the pretty ones, who flirt with mobs as ordinary women flirt with officers.
Mitchener | Then I understand you to hold that the country should be governed by the women after all.
Lady Corinthia | Not by all the women. By certain women. I had almost said by one woman. By the women who have charm—who have artistic talent—who wield a legitimate, a refining influence over the men. She sits down gracefully, smiling, and arranging her draperies with conscious elegance.
Mitchener | In short, madam, you think that if you give the vote to the man, you give the power to the women who can get round the man.
Lady Corinthia | That is not a very delicate way of putting it; but I suppose that is how you would express what I mean.
Mitchener | Perhaps you’ve never had any experience of garrison life. If you had, you’d have noticed that the sort of woman who is clever at getting round men is sometimes rather a bad lot.
Lady Corinthia | What do you mean by a bad lot?
Mitchener | I mean a woman who would play the very devil if the other women didn’t keep her in pretty strict order. I don’t approve of democracy, because its rot; and Im against giving the vote to women because Im not accustomed to it and therefore am able to see with an unprejudiced eye what infernal nonsense it is. But I tell you plainly, Lady Corinthia, that there is one game that I dislike more than either Democracy or Votes For Women: and that is the game of Antony and Cleopatra. If I must be ruled by women, let me have decent women and not—well, not the other sort.
Lady Corinthia | You have a coarse mind, General Mitchener.
Mitchener | So has Mrs. Banger. And by George! I prefer Mrs. Banger to you!
Lady Corinthia | Bounding to her feet. You prefer Mrs. Banger to me!!!
Mitchener | I do. You said yourself she was splendid.
Lady Corinthia | You are no true man. You are one of those unsexed creatures who have no joy in life, no sense of beauty, no high notes.
Mitchener | No doubt I am, Madam. As a matter of fact, I am not clever at discussing public questions, because, as an English gentleman, I was not brought up to use my brains. But occasionally, after a number of remarks which are perhaps sometimes rather idiotic, I get certain convictions. Thanks to you, I have now got a conviction that this woman question is not a question of lovely and accomplished females, but of dowdies. The average Englishwoman is a dowdy and never has half a chance of becoming anything else. She hasn’t any charm; and she has no high notes except when she’s giving her husband a piece of her mind, or calling down the street for one of the children.
Lady Corinthia | How disgusting!
Mitchener | Somebody must do the dowdy work! If we had to choose between pitching all the dowdies into the Thames and pitching all the lovely and accomplished women, the lovely ones would have to go.
Lady Corinthia | And if you had to do without Wagner’s music or do without your breakfast, you would do without Wagner. Pray does that make eggs and bacon more precious than music, or the butcher and baker better than the poet and philosopher? The scullery may be more necessary to our bare existence than the cathedral. Even humbler apartments might make the same claim. But which is the more essential to the higher life?
Mitchener | Your arguments are so devilishly ingenious that I feel convinced you got them out of some confounded book. Mine—such as they are—are my own. I imagine its something like this. There is an old saying that if you take care of the pence, the pounds will take care of themselves. Well, perhaps if we take care of the dowdies and the butchers and the bakers, the beauties and the bigwigs will take care of themselves. Rising and facing her determinedly. Anyhow, I don’t want to have things arranged for me by Wagner. Im not Wagner. How does he know where the shoe pinches me? How do you know where the shoe pinches your washerwoman?—you and your high F in alt. How are you to know when you haven’t made her comfortable unless she has a vote? Do you want her to come and break your windows?
Lady Corinthia | Am I to understand that General Mitchener is a democrat and a suffragette?
Mitchener | Yes: you have converted me—you and Mrs. Banger.
Lady Corinthia | Farewell, creature. Balsquith enters hurriedly. Mr. Balsquith: I am going to wait on General Sandstone. He at least is an officer and a gentleman. She sails out.
Balsquith | Mitchener: the game is up.
Mitchener | What do you mean?
Balsquith | The strain is too much for the Cabinet. The old Liberal and Unionist Free Traders declare that if they are defeated on their resolution to invite tenders from private contractors for carrying on the Army and Navy, they will go solid for votes for women as the only means of restoring the liberties of the country which we have destroyed by compulsory military service.
Mitchener | Infernal impudence?
Balsquith | The Labor party is taking the same line. They say the men got the Factory Acts by hiding behind the women’s petticoats, and that they will get votes for the army in the same way.
Mitchener | Balsquith: we must not yield to clamor. I have just told this lady that I am at last convinced—
Balsquith | Joyfully. That the suffragettes must be supported.
Mitchener | No: that the anti-suffragettes must be put down at all hazards.
Balsquith | Same thing.
Mitchener | No. For you now tell me that the Labor Party demands votes for women. That makes it impossible to give them, because it would be yielding to clamor. The one condition on which we can consent to grant anything in this country is that nobody shall presume to want it.
Balsquith | Earnestly. Mitchener: its no use. You can’t have the conveniences of Democracy without its occasional inconveniences.
Mitchener | What are its conveniences, I should like to know?
Balsquith | When you tell people that they are the real rulers and they can do what they like, nine times out of ten, they say, “All right, tell us what to do.” But it happens sometimes that they get an idea of their own; and then of course you’re landed.
Mitchener | Sh—
Balsquith | Desperately shouting him down. No: its no use telling me to shoot them down: Im not going to do it. After all, I don’t suppose votes for women will make much difference. It hasn’t in the other countries in which it has been tried.
Mitchener | I never supposed it would make much difference. What I can’t stand is giving in to that Pankhurst lot. Hang it all, Balsquith, it seems only yesterday that we put them in quod for a month. I said at the time that it ought to have been ten years. If my advice had been taken this wouldn’t have happened. Its a consolation to me that events are proving how thoroughly right I was.
The Orderly rushes in.
The Orderly | Look ere, sir: Mrs. Banger locked the door of General Sandstone’s room on the inside; and she’s sitting on his ead until he signs a proclamation for women to serve in the army.
Mitchener | Put your shoulder to the door and burst it open.
The Orderly | Its only in story books that doors burst open as easy as that. Besides, Im only too thankful to have a locked door between me and Mrs. B.; and so is all the rest of us.
Mitchener | Cowards. Balsquith: to the rescue! He dashes out.
Balsquith | Ambling calmly to the hearth. This is the business of the Sergeant at Arms rather than of the leader of the House. There’s no use in my tackling Mrs. Banger: she would only sit on my head too.
The Orderly | You take my tip, Mr. Balsquith. Give the women the vote and give the army civil rights; and av done with it.
Mitchener returns.
Mitchener | Balsquith: prepare to hear the worst.
Balsquith | Sandstone is no more?
Mitchener | On the contrary, he is particularly lively. He has softened Mrs. Banger by a proposal of marriage in which he appears to be perfectly in earnest. He says he has met his ideal at last, a really soldierly woman. She will sit on his head for the rest of his life; and the British Army is now to all intents and purposes commanded by Mrs. Banger. When I remonstrated with Sandstone she positively shouted “Right-about-face. March” at me in the most offensive tone. If she hadn’t been a woman I should have punched her head. I precious nearly punched Sandstone’s. The horrors of martial law administered by Mrs. Banger are too terrible to be faced. I demand civil rights for the army.
The Orderly | Chuckling. Wot oh, General! Wot oh!
Mitchener | Hold your tongue. He goes to the door and calls. Mrs. Farrell! Returning, and again addressing the Orderly. Civil rights don’t mean the right to be uncivil. Pleased with his own wit. Almost a pun. Ha ha!
Mrs. Farrell | What’s the matther now? She comes to the table.
Mitchener | To the Orderly. I have private business with Mrs. Farrell. Outside, you infernal blackguard.
The Orderly | Arguing, as usual. Well, I didn’t ask to—Mitchener seizes him by the nape; rushes him out; and slams the door.
Mitchener | Excuse the abruptness of this communication, Mrs. Farrell; but I know only one woman in the country whose practical ability and force of character can maintain her husband in competition with the husband of Mrs. Banger. I have the honor to propose for your hand.
Mrs. Farrell | Dye mean you want to marry me?
Mitchener | I do.
Mrs. Farrell | No thank you. I’d have to work for you just the same; only I shouldn’t get any wages for it.
Balsquith | That will be remedied when women get the vote. I’ve had to promise that.
Mitchener | Winningly. Mrs. Farrell: you have been charwoman here now ever since I took up my duties. Have you really never, in your more romantic moments, cast a favorable eye on my person?
Mrs. Farrell | I’ve been too busy casting an unfavorable eye on your cloze and on the litther you make with your papers.
Mitchener | Wounded. Am I to understand that you refuse me?
Mrs. Farrell | Just wait a bit. She takes Mitchener’s chair and rings up the telephone. Double three oh seven Elephant.
Mitchener | I trust you’re not ringing for the police, Mrs. Farrell. I assure you Im perfectly sane.
Mrs. Farrell | Into the telephone. Is that you, Eliza? She listens for the answer. Not out of bed yet! Go and pull her out by the heels, the lazy sthreel; and tell her her mother wants to speak to her very particularly about General Mitchener. To Mitchener. Don’t you be afeard: I know you’re sane enough when you’re not talkin about the Germans. Into the telephone. Is that you, Eliza? She listens for the answer. Dye remember me givin you a clout on the side of the head for tellin me that if I only knew how to play me cards I could marry any general on the staff instead o disgracin you be bein a charwoman? She listens for the answer. Well, I can have General Mitchener without playing any cards at all. What dye think I ought to say? She listens. Well, Im no chicken myself. To Mitchener. How old are you?
Mitchener | With an effort. Fifty-two.
Mrs. Farrell | Into the telephone. He says hes fifty-two. She listens; then, to Mitchener. She says you’re down in Who’s Who as sixty-one.
Mitchener | Damn Who’s Who.
Mrs. Farrell | Into the telephone. Anyhow I wouldn’t let that stand in the way. She listens. If I really ehat? She listens. I can’t hear you. If I really what? She listens. Who druv him? I never said a word to—Eh? She listens. Oh, love him. Arra don’t be a fool, child. To Mitchener. She wants to know do I really love you.Into the telephone. Its likely indeed I’d frighten the man off with any such nonsense, at my age. What? She listens. Well, that’s just what I was thinkin.
Mitchener | May I ask what you were thinking, Mrs. Farrell? This suspense is awful.
Mrs. Farrell | I was thinkin that perhaps the Duchess might like her daughter-in-law’s mother to be a General’s lady betther than to be a charwoman. Into the telephone. Waitle you’re married yourself, me fine lady: you’ll find out that every woman is a charwoman from the day she’s married. She listens. Then you think I might take him? She listens. Glang, you young scald: if I had you here I’d teach you manners. She listens. That’s enough now. Back wid you to bed; and be thankful Im not there to put me slipper across you. She rings off. The impudence! To Mitchener. Bless you, me childher, may you be happy, she says. To Balsquith, going to his side of the room. Give dear, old Mich me love, she says.
The Orderly opens the door, ushering in Lady Corinthia.
The Orderly | Lady Corinthia Fanshawe to speak to you, sir.
Lady Corinthia | General Mitchener: your designs on Mrs. Banger are defeated. She is engaged to General Sandstone. Do you still prefer her to me?
Mrs. Farrell | Hes out o the hunt. Hes engaged to me.
The Orderly overcome by this news reels from the door to the standing desk, and clutches the stool to save himself from collapsing.
Mitchener | And extremely proud of it, Lady Corinthia.
Lady Corinthia | Contemptuously. She suits you exactly. Coming to Balsquith. Mr. Balsquith: you at least, are not a Philistine.
Balsquith | No, Lady Corinthia; but Im a confirmed bachelor. I don’t want a wife; but I want an Egeria.
Mrs. Farrell | More shame for you.
Lady Corinthia | Silence, woman. The position and functions of a wife may suit your gross nature. An Egeria is exactly what I desire to be. To Balsquith. Can you play accompaniments?
Balsquith | Melodies only, I regret to say. With one finger. But my brother, who is a very obliging fellow, and not unlike me personally, is acquainted with three chords, with which he manages to accompany most of the comic songs of the day.
Lady Corinthia | I do not sing comic songs. Neither will you when I am your Egeria. Come. I give a musical at-home this afternoon. I will allow you to sit at my feet.
Balsquith | That is my ideal of romantic happiness. It commits me exactly as far as I desire to venture. Thank you.
The Orderly | Wot price me, General? Won’t you celebrate your engagement by doing something for me? Mayn’t I be promoted to be a sergeant.
Mitchener | You’re too utterly incompetent to discharge the duties of a sergeant. You are only fit to be a lieutenant. I shall recommend you for a commission.
The Orderly | Hooray! The Parkinsons of Stepney will be proud to have me call on them now. I’ll go and tell the sergeant what I think of him. Hooray! He rushes out.
Mrs. Farrell | Going to the door and calling after him. You might have the manners to shut the door idther you. She shuts it and comes between Mitchener and Lady Corinthia.
Mitchener | Poor wretch; the day after civil rights are conceded to the army he and Chubbs-Jenkinson will be found incapable of maintaining discipline. They will be sacked and replaced by really capable men. Mrs. Farrell: as we are engaged, and I am anxious to do the correct thing in every way, I am quite willing to kiss you if you wish it.
Mrs. Farrell | You’d only feel like a fool; and so would I.
Mitchener | You are really the most sensible woman. I’ve made an extremely wise choice.
Lady Corinthia | To Balsquith. You may kiss my hand, if you wish.
Balsquith | Cautiously. I think we had better not commit ourselves too far. If I might carry your parasol, that would quite satisfy me. Let us change a subject which threatens to become embarrassing. To Mitchener. The moral of the occasion for you, Mitchener, appears to be that you’ve got to give up treating soldiers as if they were schoolboys.
Mitchener | The moral for you, Balsquith, is that you’ve got to give up treating women as if they were angels. Ha ha!
Mrs. Farrell | Its a mercy you’ve found one another out at last. That’s enough now.

The Admirable Bashville

Or, Constancy Unrewarded

Being the Novel of Cashel Byron’s Profession Done Into a Stage Play in Three Acts, and in Blank Verse, with a Note on Modern Prizefighting

Preface

“The Admirable Bashville” is a product of the British law of copyright. As that law stands at present, the first person who patches up a stage version of a novel, however worthless and absurd that version may be, and has it read by himself and a few confederates to another confederate who has paid for admission in a hall licensed for theatrical performances, secures the stage rights of that novel, even as against the author himself; and the author must buy him out before he can touch his own work for the purposes of the stage.

A famous case in point is the drama of East Lynne, adapted from the late Mrs. Henry Wood’s novel of that name. It was enormously popular, and is still the surest refuge of touring companies in distress. Many authors feel that Mrs. Henry Wood was hardly used in not getting any of the money which was plentifully made in this way through her story. To my mind, since her literary copyright probably brought her a fair wage for the work of writing the book, her real grievance was, first, that her name and credit were attached to a play with which she had nothing to do, and which may quite possibly have been to her a detestable travesty and profanation of her story; and second, that the authors of that play had the legal power to prevent her from having any version of her own performed, if she had wished to make one.

There is only one way in which the author can protect himself; and that is by making a version of his own and going through the same legal farce with it. But the legal farce involves the hire of a hall and the payment of a fee of two guineas to the King’s Reader of Plays. When I wrote Cashel Byron’s Profession I had no guineas to spare, a common disability of young authors. What is equally common, I did not know the law. A reasonable man may guess a reasonable law, but no man can guess a foolish anomaly. Fortunately, by the time my book so suddenly revived in America I was aware of the danger, and in a position to protect myself by writing and performing “The Admirable Bashville.” The prudence of doing so was soon demonstrated; for rumors soon reached me of several American stage versions; and one of these has actually been played in New York, with the boxing scenes under the management (so it is stated) of the eminent pugilist Mr. James J. Corbett. The New York press, in a somewhat derisive vein, conveyed the impression that in this version Cashel Byron sought to interest the public rather as the last of the noble race of the Byrons of Dorsetshire than as his unromantic self; but in justice to a play which I never read, and an actor whom I never saw, and who honorably offered to treat me as if I had legal rights in the matter, I must not accept the newspaper evidence as conclusive.

As I write these words, I am promised by the King in his speech to Parliament a new Copyright Bill. I believe it embodies, in our British fashion, the recommendations of the book publishers as to the concerns of the authors, and the notions of the musical publishers as to the concerns of the playwrights. As author and playwright I am duly obliged to the Commission for saving me the trouble of speaking for myself, and to the witnesses for speaking for me. But unless Parliament takes the opportunity of giving the authors of all printed works of fiction, whether dramatic or narrative, both playright and copyright (as in America), such to be independent of any insertions or omissions of formulas about “all rights reserved” or the like, I am afraid the new Copyright Bill will leave me with exactly the opinion both of the copyright law and the wisdom of Parliament I at present entertain. As a good Socialist I do not at all object to the limitation of my right of property in my own works to a comparatively brief period, followed by complete Communism: in fact, I cannot see why the same salutary limitation should not be applied to all property rights whatsoever; but a system which enables any alert sharper to acquire property rights in my stories as against myself and the rest of the community would, it seems to me, justify a rebellion if authors were numerous and warlike enough to make one.

It may be asked why I have written “The Admirable Bashville” in blank verse. My answer is that I had but a week to write it in. Blank verse is so childishly easy and expeditious (hence, by the way, Shakespeare’s copious output), that by adopting it I was enabled to do within the week what would have cost me a month in prose.

Besides, I am fond of blank verse. Not nineteenth century blank verse, of course, nor indeed, with a very few exceptions, any post-Shakespearean blank verse. Nay, not Shakespearean blank verse itself later than the histories. When an author can write the prose dialogue of the first scene in As You Like It, or Hamlet’s colloquies with Rosencrantz and Guildenstern, there is really no excuse for The Seven Ages and “To be or not to be,” except the excuse of a haste that made great facility indispensable. I am quite sure that anyone who is to recover the charm of blank verse must frankly go back to its beginnings and start a literary pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood. I like the melodious singsong, the clear simple one-line and two-line sayings, and the occasional rhymed tags, like the half closes in an eighteenth century symphony, in Peele, Kyd, Greene, and the histories of Shakespeare. How anyone with music in him can turn from Henry VI, John, and the two Richards to such a mess of verse half developed into rhetorical prose as Cymbeline, is to me explicable only by the uncivil hypothesis that the artistic qualities in the Elizabethan drama do not exist for most of its critics; so that they hang on to its purely prosaic content, and hypnotize themselves into absurd exaggerations of the value of that content. Even poets fall under the spell. Ben Jonson described Marlowe’s line as “mighty”! As well put Michelangelo’s epitaph on the tombstone of Paolo Uccello. No wonder Jonson’s blank verse is the most horribly disagreeable product in literature, and indicates his most prosaic mood as surely as his shorter rhymed measures indicate his poetic mood. Marlowe never wrote a mighty line in his life: Cowper’s single phrase “Toll for the brave” drowns all his mightinesses as Great Tom drowns a military band. But Marlowe took that very pleasant-sounding rigmarole of Peele and Greene, and added to its sunny daylight the insane splendors of night, and the cheap tragedy of crime. Because he had only a common sort of brain, he was hopelessly beaten by Shakespeare; but he had a fine ear and a soaring spirit: in short, one does not forget “wanton Arethusa’s azure arms” and the like. But the pleasant-sounding rigmarole was the basis of the whole thing; and as long as that rigmarole was practised frankly for the sake of its pleasantness, it was readable and speakable. It lasted until Shakespeare did to it what Raphael did to Italian painting; that is, overcharged and burst it by making it the vehicle of a new order of thought, involving a mass of intellectual ferment and psychological research. The rigmarole could not stand the strain; and Shakespeare’s style ended in a chaos of half-shattered old forms, half-emancipated new ones, with occasional bursts of prose eloquence on the one hand, occasional delicious echoes of the rigmarole, mostly from Calibans and masque personages, on the other, with, alas! a great deal of filling up with formulary blank verse which had no purpose except to save the author’s time and thought.

When a great man destroys an art form in this way, its ruins make palaces for the clever would-be great. After Michelangelo and Raphael, Giulio Romano and the Carracci. After Marlowe and Shakespeare, Chapman and the Police News poet Webster. Webster’s specialty was blood: Chapman’s, balderdash. Many of us by this time find it difficult to believe that pre-Ruskinite art criticism used to prostrate itself before the works of Domenichino and Guido, and to patronize the modest little beginnings of those who came between Cimabue and Masaccio. But we have only to look at our own current criticism of Elizabethan drama to satisfy ourselves that in an art which has not yet found its Ruskin or its pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, the same folly is still academically propagated. It is possible, and even usual, for men professing to have ears and a sense of poetry to snub Peele and Greene and grovel before Fletcher and Webster—Fletcher! a facile blank verse penny-a-liner: Webster! a turgid paper cutthroat. The subject is one which I really cannot pursue without intemperance of language. The man who thinks The Duchess of Malfi better than David and Bethsabe is outside the pale, not merely of literature, but almost of humanity.

Yet some of the worst of these post-Shakespearean duffers, from Jonson to Heywood, suddenly became poets when they turned from the big drum of pseudo-Shakespearean drama to the pipe and tabor of the masque, exactly as Shakespeare himself recovered the old charm of the rigmarole when he turned from Prospero to Ariel and Caliban. Cyril Tourneur and Heywood could certainly have produced very pretty rigmarole plays if they had begun where Shakespeare began, instead of trying to begin where he left off. Jonson and Beaumont would very likely have done themselves credit on the same terms: Marston would have had at least a chance. Massinger was in his right place, such as it was; and one would not disturb the gentle Ford, who was never born to storm the footlights. Webster could have done no good anyhow or anywhere: the man was a fool. And Chapman would always have been a blathering unreadable pedant, like Landor, in spite of his classical amateurship and respectable strenuosity of character. But with these exceptions it may plausibly be held that if Marlowe and Shakespeare could have been kept out of their way, the rest would have done well enough on the lines of Peele and Greene. However, they thought otherwise; and now that their freethinking paganism, so dazzling to the pupils of Paley and the converts of Wesley, offers itself in vain to the disciples of Darwin and Nietzsche, there is an end of them. And a good riddance, too.

Accordingly, I have poetasted “The Admirable Bashville” in the rigmarole style. And lest the Webster worshippers should declare that there is not a single correct line in all my three acts, I have stolen or paraphrased a few from Marlowe and Shakespeare (not to mention Henry Carey); so that if any man dares quote me derisively, he shall do so in peril of inadvertently lighting on a purple patch from Hamlet or Faustus.

I have also endeavored in this little play to prove that I am not the heartless creature some of my critics take me for. I have strictly observed the established laws of stage popularity and probability. I have simplified the character of the heroine, and summed up her sweetness in the one sacred word: Love. I have given consistency to the heroism of Cashel. I have paid to Morality, in the final scene, the tribute of poetic justice. I have restored to Patriotism its usual place on the stage, and gracefully acknowledged The Throne as the fountain of social honor. I have paid particular attention to the construction of the play, which will be found equal in this respect to the best contemporary models.

And I trust the result will be found satisfactory.

Dramatis Personae

Lydia Carew

Cashel Byron

Bob Mellish

Lucian Webber

Bashville

Lord Worthington

Cetewayo

Paradise

The Master of the Revels

A Policeman

Adelaide Gisborne

Voice of a Newsboy

Spectators; Persions of Fashion; Zulu Chiefs; Constables; and Others

Act I

A glade in Wiltstoken Park.

Enter Lydia.
Lydia |

Ye leafy breasts and warm protecting wings
Of mother trees that hatch our tender souls,
And from the well of Nature in our hearts
Thaw the intolerable inch of ice
That bears the weight of all the stamping world.
Hear ye me sing to solitude that I,
Lydia Carew, the owner of these lands,
Albeit most rich, most learned, and most wise,
Am yet most lonely. What are riches worth
When wisdom with them comes to show the purse bearer
That life remains unpurchasable? Learning
Learns but one lesson: doubt! To excel all
Is, to be lonely. Oh, ye busy birds,
Engrossed with real needs, ye shameless trees
With arms outspread in welcome of the sun,
Your minds, bent singly to enlarge your lives,
Have given you wings and raised your delicate heads
High heavens above us crawlers.

A rook sets up a great cawing; and the other birds chatter loudly as a gust of wind sets the branches swaying. She makes as though she would show them her sleeves.

Lo, the leaves
That hide my drooping boughs! Mock me—poor maid!—
Deride with joyous comfortable chatter
These stolen feathers. Laugh at me, the clothed one.
Laugh at the mind fed on foul air and books.
Books! Art! And Culture! Oh, I shall go mad.
Give me a mate that never heard of these,
A sylvan god, tree born in heart and sap;
Or else, eternal maidhood be my hap.

Another gust of wind and bird-chatter. She sits on the mossy root of an oak and buries her face in her hands. Cashel Byron, in a white singlet and breeches, comes through the trees.
Cashel |

What’s this? Whom have we here? A woman!

Lydia |

Looking up.

Yes.

Cashel |

You have no business here. I have. Away!
Women distract me. Hence!

Lydia |

Bid you me hence?
I am upon mine own ground. Who are you?
I take you for a god, a sylvan god.
This place is mine: I share it with the birds,
The trees, the sylvan gods, the lovely company
Of haunted solitudes.

Cashel |

A sylvan god!
A goat-eared image! Do your statues speak?
Walk? heave the chest with breath? or like a feather
Lift you—like this?

He sets her on her feet.
Lydia |

Panting.

You take away my breath!
You’re strong. Your hands off, please. Thank you. Farewell.

Cashel |

Before you go: when shall we meet again?

Lydia |

Why should we meet again?

Cashel |

Who knows? We shall.
That much I know by instinct. What’s your name?

Lydia |

Lydia Carew.

Cashel |

Lydia’s a pretty name.
Where do you live?

Lydia |

I’ the castle.

Cashel |

Thunderstruck.

Do not say
You are the lady of this great domain.

Lydia |

I am.

Cashel |

Accursed luck! I took you for
The daughter of some farmer. Well, your pardon.
I came too close: I looked too deep. Farewell.

Lydia |

I pardon that. Now tell me who you are.

Cashel |

Ask me not whence I come, nor what I am.
You are the lady of the castle. I
Have but this hard and blackened hand to live by.

Lydia |

I have felt its strength and envied you. Your name?
I have told you mine.

Cashel |

My name is Cashel Byron.

Lydia |

I never heard the name; and yet you utter it
As men announce a celebrated name.
Forgive my ignorance.

Cashel |

I bless it, Lydia.
I have forgot your other name.

Lydia |

Carew.
Cashel’s a pretty name, too.

Mellish |

Calling through the wood.

Coo-ee! Byron!

Cashel |

A thousand curses! Oh, I beg you, go.
This is a man you must not meet.

Mellish |

Further off.

Coo-ee!

Lydia |

He’s losing us. What does he in my woods?

Cashel |

He is a part of what I am. What that is
You must not know. It would end all between us.
And yet there’s no dishonor in’t: your lawyer,
Who let your lodge to me, will vouch me honest.
I am ashamed to tell you what I am—
At least, as yet. Some day, perhaps.

Mellish |

Nearer.

Coo-ee!

Lydia |

His voice is nearer. Fare you well, my tenant.
When next your rent falls due, come to the castle.
Pay me in person. Sir: your most obedient. She curtsies and goes.

Cashel |

Lives in this castle! Owns this park! A lady
Marry a prizefighter! Impossible.
And yet the prizefighter must marry her.

Enter Mellish.

Ensanguined swine, whelped by a doggish dam,
Is this thy park, that thou, with voice obscene,
Fillst it with yodeled yells, and screamst my name
For all the world to know that Cashel Byron
Is training here for combat.

Mellish |

Swine you me?
I’ve caught you, have I? You have found a woman.
Let her show here again, I’ll set the dog on her.
I will. I say it. And my name’s Bob Mellish.

Cashel |

Change thy initial and be truly hight
Hellish. As for thy dog, why dost thou keep one
And bark thyself? Begone.

Mellish |

I’ll not begone.
You shall come back with me and do your duty—
Your duty to your backers, do you hear?
You have not punched the bag this blessed day.

Cashel |

The putrid bag engirdled by thy belt
Invites my fist.

Mellish |

Weeping.

Ingrate! O wretched lot!
Who would a trainer be? O Mellish, Mellish,
Trainer of heroes, builder-up of brawn,
Vicarious victor, thou createst champions
That quickly turn thy tyrants. But beware:
Without me thou art nothing. Disobey me,
And all thy boasted strength shall fall from thee.
With flaccid muscles and with failing breath
Facing the fist of thy more faithful foe,
I’ll see thee on the grass cursing the day
Thou didst forswear thy training.

Cashel |

Noisome quack
That canst not from thine own abhorrent visage
Take one carbuncle, thou contaminat’st
Even with thy presence my untainted blood.
Preach abstinence to rascals like thyself
Rotten with surfeiting. Leave me in peace.
This grove is sacred: thou profanest it.
Hence! I have business that concerns thee not.

Mellish |

Ay, with your woman. You will lose your fight.
Have you forgot your duty to your backers?
Oh, what a sacred thing your duty is!
What makes a man but duty? Where were we
Without our duty? Think of Nelson’s words:
England expects that every man—

Cashel |

Shall twaddle
About his duty. Mellish: at no hour
Can I regard thee wholly without loathing;
But when thou play’st the moralist, by Heaven,
My soul flies to my fist, my fist to thee;
And never did the Cyclops’ hammer fall
On Mars’s armor—but enough of that.
It does remind me of my mother.

Mellish |

Ah,
Byron, let it remind thee. Once I heard
An old song: it ran thus. He clears his throat. Ahem, Ahem!

Sings.

—They say there is no other
Can take the place of mother—

I am out o’ voice: forgive me; but remember:
Thy mother—were that sainted woman here—
Would say, Obey thy trainer.

Cashel |

Now, by Heaven,
Some fate is pushing thee upon thy doom.
Canst thou not hear thy sands as they run out?
They thunder like an avalanche. Old man:
Two things I hate, my duty and my mother.
Why dost thou urge them both upon me now?
Presume not on thine age and on thy nastiness.
Vanish, and promptly.

Mellish |

Can I leave thee here
Thus thinly clad, exposed to vernal dews?
Come back with me, my son, unto our lodge.

Cashel |

Within this breast a fire is newly lit
Whose glow shall sun the dew away, whose radiance
Shall make the orb of night hang in the heavens
Unnoticed, like a glowworm at high noon.

Mellish |

Ah me, ah me, where wilt thou spend the night?

Cashel |

Wiltstoken’s windows wandering beneath,
Wiltstoken’s holy bell hearkening,
Wiltstoken’s lady loving breathlessly.

Mellish |

The lady of the castle! Thou art mad.

Cashel |

’Tis thou art mad to trifle in my path.
Thwart me no more. Begone.

Mellish |

My boy, my son,
I’d give my heart’s blood for thy happiness.
Thwart thee, my son! Ah, no. I’ll go with thee.
I’ll brave the dews. I’ll sacrifice my sleep.
I am old—no matter: ne’er shall it be said
Mellish deserted thee.

Cashel |

You resolute gods
That will not spare this man, upon your knees
Take the disparity twixt his age and mine.
Now from the ring to the high judgment seat
I step at your behest. Bear you me witness
This is not Victory, but Execution.

He solemnly projects his fist with colossal force against the waistcoat of Mellish, who doubles up like a folded towel, and lies without sense or motion.

And now the night is beautiful again.

The castle clock strikes the hour in the distance.

Hark! Hark! Hark! Hark! Hark! Hark! Hark! Hark! Hark! Hark!
It strikes in poetry. ’Tis ten o’clock.
Lydia: to thee!

He steals off towards the castle. Mellish stirs and groans.

Act II

Scene I

London. A room in Lydia’s house.

Enter Lydia and Lucian.
Lydia |

Welcome, dear cousin, to my London house.
Of late you have been chary of your visits.

Lucian |

I have been greatly occupied of late.
The minister to whom I act as scribe
In Downing Street was born in Birmingham,
And, like a thoroughbred commercial statesman,
Splits his infinitives, which I, poor slave,
Must reunite, though all the time my heart
Yearns for my gentle coz’s company.

Lydia |

Lucian: there is some other reason. Think!
Since England was a nation every mood
Her scribes have prepositionally split;
But thine avoidance dates from yestermonth.

Lucian |

There is a man I like not haunts this house.

Lydia |

Thou speak’st of Cashel Byron?

Lucian |

Aye, of him.
Hast thou forgotten that eventful night
When as we gathered were at Hoskyn House
To hear a lecture by Herr Abendgasse,
He placed a single finger on my chest,
And I, ensorceled, would have sunk supine
Had not a chair received my falling form.

Lydia |

Pooh! That was but by way of illustration.

Lucian |

What right had he to illustrate his point
Upon my person? Was I his assistant
That he should try experiments on me
As Simpson did on his with chloroform?
Now, by the cannon balls of Galileo
He hath unmanned me: all my nerve is gone.
This very morning my official chief,
Tapping with friendly forefinger this button,
Levelled me like a thunderstricken elm
Flat upon the Colonial Office floor.

Lydia |

Fancies, coz.

Lucian |

Fancies! Fits! the chief said fits!
Delirium tremens! the chlorotic dance
Of Vitus! What could anyone have thought?
Your ruffian friend hath ruined me. By Heaven,
I tremble at a thumbnail. Give me drink.

Lydia |

What ho, without there! Bashville.

Bashville |

Without.

Coming, madam.

Enter Bashville.
Lydia |

My cousin ails, Bashville. Procure some wet. Exit Bashville.

Lucian |

Some wet!!! Where learnt you that atrocious word?
This is the language of a flower-girl.

Lydia |

True. It is horrible. Said I “Some wet”?
I meant, some drink. Why did I say “Some wet”?
Am I ensorceled too? “Some wet”! Fie! fie!
I feel as though some hateful thing had stained me.
Oh, Lucian, how could I have said “Some wet”?

Lucian |

The horrid conversation of this man
Hath numbed thy once unfailing sense of fitness.

Lydia |

Nay, he speaks very well: he’s literate:
Shakespeare he quotes unconsciously.

Lucian |

And yet
Anon he talks pure pothouse.

Enter Bashville.
Bashville |

Sir: your potion.

Lucian |

Thanks. He drinks. I am better.

A Newsboy |

Calling without.

Extra special Star!
Result of the great fight! Name of the winner!

Lydia |

Who calls so loud?

Bashville |

The papers, madam.

Lydia |

Why?
Hath ought momentous happened?

Bashville |

Madam: yes. He produces a newspaper.
All England for these thrilling paragraphs
A week has waited breathless.

Lydia |

Read them us.

Bashville |

Reading.

“At noon today, unknown to the police,
Within a thousand miles of Wormwood Scrubbs,
Th’ Australian Champion and his challenger,
The Flying Dutchman, formerly engaged
I’ the mercantile marine, fought to a finish.
Lord Worthington, the well-known sporting peer
Acted as referee.”

Lydia |

Lord Worthington!

Bashville |

“The bold Ned Skene revisited the ropes
To hold the bottle for his quondam novice;
Whilst in the seaman’s corner were assembled
Professor Palmer and the Chelsea Snob.
Mellish, whose epigastrium has been hurt,
’Tis said, by accident at Wiltstoken,
Looked none the worse in the Australian’s corner.
The Flying Dutchman wore the Union Jack:
His colors freely sold amid the crowd;
But Cashel’s well-known spot of white on blue—”

Lydia |

Whose, did you say?

Bashville |

Cashel’s, my lady.

Lydia |

Lucian:
Your hand—a chair—

Bashville |

Madam: you’re ill.

Lydia |

Proceed.
What you have read I do not understand;
Yet I will hear it through. Proceed.

Lucian |

Proceed.

Bashville |

“But Cashel’s well-known spot of white on blue
Was fairly rushed for. Time was called at twelve,
When, with a smile of confidence upon
His ocean-beaten mug—”

Lydia |

His mug?

Lucian |

Explaining.

His face.

Bashville |

Continuing.

“The Dutchman came undaunted to the scratch,
But found the champion there already. Both
Most heartily shook hands, amid the cheers
Of their encouraged backers. Two to one
Was offered on the Melbourne nonpareil;
And soon, so fit the Flying Dutchman seemed,
Found takers everywhere. No time was lost
In getting to the business of the day.
The Dutchman led at once, and seemed to land
On Byron’s dicebox; but the seaman’s reach,
Too short for execution at long shots,
Did not get fairly home upon the ivory;
And Byron had the best of the exchange.”

Lydia |

I do not understand. What were they doing?

Lucian |

Fighting with naked fists.

Lydia |

Oh, horrible!
I’ll hear no more. Or stay: how did it end?
Was Cashel hurt?

Lucian |

To Bashville.

Skip to the final round.

Bashville |

“Round Three: the rumors that had gone about
Of a breakdown in Byron’s recent training
Seemed quite confirmed. Upon the call of time
He rose, and, looking anything but cheerful,
Proclaimed with every breath Bellows to Mend.
At this point six to one was freely offered
Upon the Dutchman; and Lord Worthington
Plunged at this figure till he stood to lose
A fortune should the Dutchman, as seemed certain,
Take down the number of the Panley boy.
The Dutchman, glutton as we know he is,
Seemed this time likely to go hungry. Cashel
Was clearly groggy as he slipped the sailor,
Who, not to be denied, followed him up,
Forcing the fighting mid tremendous cheers.”

Lydia |

Oh stop—no more—or tell the worst at once.
I’ll be revenged. Bashville: call the police.
This brutal sailor shall be made to know
There’s law in England.

Lucian |

Do not interrupt him:
Mine ears are thirsting. Finish, man. What next?

Bashville |

“Forty to one, the Dutchman’s friends exclaimed.
Done, said Lord Worthington, who showed himself
A sportsman every inch. Barely the bet
Was booked, when, at the reeling champion’s jaw
The sailor, bent on winning out of hand,
Sent in his right. The issue seemed a cert,
When Cashel, ducking smartly to his left,
Cross-countered like a hundredweight of brick—”

Lucian |

Death and damnation!

Lydia |

Oh, what does it mean?

Bashville |

“The Dutchman went to grass, a beaten man.”

Lydia |

Hurrah! Hurrah! Hurrah! Oh, well done, Cashel!

Bashville |

“A scene of indescribable excitement
Ensued; for it was now quite evident
That Byron’s grogginess had all along
Been feigned to make the market for his backers.
We trust this sample of colonial smartness
Will not find imitators on this side.
The losers settled up like gentlemen;
But many felt that Byron showed bad taste
In taking old Ned Skene upon his back,
And, with Bob Mellish tucked beneath his oxter,
Sprinting a hundred yards to show the crowd
The perfect pink of his condition”—A knock.

Lydia |

Turning pale.

Bashville
Didst hear? A knock.

Bashville |

Madam: ’tis Byron’s knock.
Shall I admit him?

Lucian |

Reeking from the ring!
Oh, monstrous! Say you’re out.

Lydia |

Send him away.
I will not see the wretch. How dare he keep
Secrets from me? I’ll punish him. Pray say
I’m not at home. Bashville turns to go. Yet stay. I am afraid
He will not come again.

Lucian |

A consummation
Devoutly to be wished by any lady.
Pray, do you wish this man to come again?

Lydia |

No, Lucian. He hath used me very ill.
He should have told me. I will ne’er forgive him.
Say, Not at home.

Bashville |

Yes, madam. Exit.

Lydia |

Stay—

Lucian |

Stopping her.

No, Lydia:
You shall not countermand that proper order.
Oh, would you cast the treasure of your mind,
The thousands at your bank, and, above all,
Your unassailable social position
Before this soulless mass of beef and brawn?

Lydia |

Nay, coz: you’re prejudiced.

Cashel |

Without.

Liar and slave!

Lydia |

What words were those?

Lucian |

The man is drunk with slaughter.

Enter Bashville running: he shuts the door and locks it.
Bashville |

Save yourselves: at the staircase foot the champion
Sprawls on the mat, by trick of wrestler tripped;
But when he rises, woe betide us all!

Lydia |

Who bade you treat my visitor with violence?

Bashville |

He would not take my answer; thrust the door
Back in my face; gave me the lie i’ the throat;
Averred he felt your presence in his bones.
I said he should feel mine there too, and felled him;
Then fled to bar your door.

Lydia |

O lover’s instinct!
He felt my presence. Well, let him come in.
We must not fail in courage with a fighter.
Unlock the door.

Lucian |

Stop. Like all women, Lydia,
You have the courage of immunity.
To strike you were against his code of honor;
But me, above the belt, he may perform on
T’ th’ height of his profession. Also Bashville.

Bashville |

Think not of me, sir. Let him do his worst.
Oh, if the valor of my heart could weigh
The fatal difference twixt his weight and mine,
A second battle should he do this day:
Nay, though outmatched I be, let but my mistress
Give me the word: instant I’ll take him on
Here—now—at catchweight. Better bite the carpet
A man, than fly, a coward.

Lucian |

Bravely said:
I will assist you with the poker.

Lydia |

No:
I will not have him touched. Open the door.

Bashville |

Destruction knocks thereat. I smile, and open.

Bashville opens the door. Dead silence. Cashel enters, in tears. A solemn pause.
Cashel |

You know my secret?

Lydia |

Yes.

Cashel |

And thereupon
You bade your servant fling me from your door.

Lydia |

I bade my servant say I was not here.

Cashel |

To Bashville.

Why didst thou better thy instruction, man?
Hadst thou but said, “She bade me tell thee this,”
Thoudst burst my heart. I thank thee for thy mercy.

Lydia |

Oh, Lucian, didst thou call him “drunk with slaughter”?
Canst thou refrain from weeping at his woe?

Cashel |

To LUCIAN.

The unwritten law that shields the amateur
Against professional resentment, saves thee.
O coward, to traduce behind their backs
Defenceless prizefighters!

Lucian |

Thou dost avow
Thou art a prizefighter.

Cashel |

It was my glory.
I had hoped to offer to my lady there
My belts, my championships, my heaped-up stakes,
My undefeated record; but I knew
Behind their blaze a hateful secret lurked.

Lydia |

Another secret?

Lucian |

Is there worse to come?

Cashel |

Know ye not then my mother is an actress?

Lucian |

How horrible!

Lydia |

Nay, nay: how interesting!

Cashel |

A thousand victories cannot wipe out
That birthstain. Oh, my speech bewrayeth it:
My earliest lesson was the player’s speech
In Hamlet; and to this day I express myself
More like a mobled queen than like a man
Of flesh and blood. Well may your cousin sneer!
What’s Hecuba to him or he to Hecuba?

Lucian |

Injurious upstart: if by Hecuba
Thou pointest darkly at my lovely cousin,
Know that she is to me, and I to her,
What never canst thou be. I do defy thee;
And maugre all the odds thy skill doth give,
Outside I will await thee.

Lydia |

I forbid
Expressly any such duello. Bashville:
The door. Put Mr. Webber in a hansom,
And bid the driver hie to Downing Street.
No answer: ’tis my will.

Exeunt Lucian and Bashville.

And now, farewell.
You must not come again, unless indeed
You can some day look in my eyes and say:
Lydia: my occupation’s gone.

Cashel |

Ah, no:
It would remind you of my wretched mother.
O God, let me be natural a moment!
What other occupation can I try?
What would you have me be?

Lydia |

A gentleman.

Cashel |

A gentleman! I, Cashel Byron, stoop
To be the thing that bets on me! the fool
I flatter at so many coins a lesson!
The screaming creature who beside the ring
Gambles with basest wretches for my blood,
And pays with money that he never earned!
Let me die brokenhearted rather!

Lydia |

But
You need not be an idle gentleman.
I call you one of Nature’s gentlemen.

Cashel |

That’s the collection for the loser, Lydia.
I am not wont to need it. When your friends
Contest elections, and at foot o’ th’ poll
Rue their presumption, ’tis their wont to claim
A moral victory. In a sort they are
Nature’s M.P.’s. I am not yet so threadbare
As to accept these consolation stakes.

Lydia |

You are offended with me.

Cashel |

Yes, I am.
I can put up with much; but—“Nature’s gentleman”!
I thank your ladyship of Lyons, but
Must beg to be excused.

Lydia |

But surely, surely,
To be a prizefighter, and maul poor mariners
With naked knuckles, is no work for you.

Cashel |

Thou dost arraign the inattentive Fates
That weave my thread of life in ruder patterns
Than these that lie, antimacassarly,
Asprent thy drawing room. As well demand
Why I at birth chose to begin my life
A speechless babe, hairless, incontinent,
Hobbling upon all fours, a nurse’s nuisance?
Or why I do propose to lose my strength,
To blanch my hair, to let the gums recede
Far up my yellowing teeth, and finally
Lie down and moulder in a rotten grave?
Only one thing more foolish could have been,
And that was to be born, not man, but woman.
This was thy folly, why rebuk’st thou mine?

Lydia |

These are not things of choice.

Cashel |

And did I choose
My quick divining eye, my lightning hand,
My springing muscle and untiring heart?
Did I implant the instinct in the race
That found a use for these, and said to me,
Fight for us, and be fame and fortune thine?

Lydia |

But there are other callings in the world.

Cashel |

Go tell thy painters to turn stockbrokers,
Thy poet friends to stoop o’er merchants’ desks
And pen prose records of the gains of greed.
Tell bishops that religion is outworn,
And that the Pampa to the horsebreaker
Opes new careers. Bid the professor quit
His fraudulent pedantries, and do i’ the world
The thing he would teach others. Then return
To me and say: Cashel: they have obeyed;
And on that pyre of sacrifice I, too,
Will throw my championship.

Lydia |

But ’tis so cruel.

Cashel |

Is it so? I have hardly noticed that,
So cruel are all callings. Yet this hand,
That many a two days’ bruise hath ruthless given,
Hath kept no dungeon locked for twenty years,
Hath slain no sentient creature for my sport.
I am too squeamish for your dainty world,
That cowers behind the gallows and the lash,
The world that robs the poor, and with their spoil
Does what its tradesmen tell it. Oh, your ladies!
Sealskinned and egret-feathered; all defiance
To Nature; cowering if one say to them
“What will the servants think?” Your gentlemen!
Your tailor-tyrannized visitors of whom
Flutter of wing and singing in the wood
Make chickenbutchers. And your medicine men!
Groping for cures in the tormented entrails
Of friendly dogs. Pray have you asked all these
To change their occupations? Find you mine
So grimly crueller? I cannot breathe
An air so petty and so poisonous.

Lydia |

But find you not their manners very nice?

Cashel |

To me, perfection. Oh, they condescend
With a rare grace. Your duke, who condescends
Almost to the whole world, might for a Man
Pass in the eyes of those who never saw
The duke capped with a prince. See then, ye gods,
The duke turn footman, and his eager dame
Sink the great lady in the obsequious housemaid!
Oh, at such moments I could wish the Court
Had but one breadbasket, that with my fist
I could make all its windy vanity
Gasp itself out on the gravel. Fare you well.
I did not choose my calling; but at least
I can refrain from being a gentleman.

Lydia |

You say farewell to me without a pang.

Cashel |

My calling hath apprenticed me to pangs.
This is a rib-bender; but I can bear it.
It is a lonely thing to be a champion.

Lydia |

It is a lonelier thing to be a woman.

Cashel |

Be lonely then. Shall it be said of thee
That for his brawn thou misalliance mad’st
Wi’ the Prince of Ruffians? Never. Go thy ways;
Or, if thou hast nostalgia of the mud,
Wed some bedoggéd wretch that on the slot
Of gilded snobbery, ventre à terre,
Will hunt through life with eager nose on earth
And hang thee thick with diamonds. I am rich;
But all my gold was fought for with my hands.

Lydia |

What dost thou mean by rich?

Cashel |

There is a man,
Hight Paradise, vaunted unconquerable,
Hath dared to say he will be glad to hear from me.
I have replied that none can hear from me
Until a thousand solid pounds be staked.
His friends have confidently found the money.
Ere fall of leaf that money shall be mine;
And then I shall possess ten thousand pounds.
I had hoped to tempt thee with that monstrous sum.

Lydia |

Thou silly Cashel, ’tis but a week’s income.
I did propose to give thee three times that
For pocket money when we two were wed.

Cashel |

Give me my hat. I have been fooling here.
Now, by the Hebrew lawgiver, I thought
That only in America such revenues
Were decent deemed. Enough. My dream is dreamed.
Your gold weighs like a mountain on my chest.
Farewell.

Lydia |

The golden mountain shall be thine
The day thou quit’st thy horrible profession.

Cashel |

Tempt me not, woman. It is honor calls.
Slave to the Ring I rest until the face
Of Paradise be changed.

Enter Bashville.
Bashville |

Madam, your carriage,
Ordered by you at two. ’Tis now half-past.

Cashel |

Sdeath! is it half-past two? The king! the king!

Lydia |

The king! What mean you?

Cashel |

I must meet a monarch
This very afternoon at Islington.

Lydia |

At Islington! You must be mad.

Cashel |

A cab!
Go call a cab; and let a cab be called;
And let the man that calls it be thy footman.

Lydia |

You are not well. You shall not go alone.
My carriage waits. I must accompany you.
I go to find my hat. Exit.

Cashel |

Like Paracelsus,
Who went to find his soul. To Bashville. And now, young man,
How comes it that a fellow of your inches,
So deft a wrestler and so bold a spirit,
Can stoop to be a flunkey? Call on me
On your next evening out. I’ll make a man of you.
Surely you are ambitious and aspire—

Bashville |

To be a butler and draw corks; wherefore,
By Heaven, I will draw yours.

He hits Cashel on the nose, and runs out.
Cashel |

Thoughtfully putting the side of his forefinger to his nose, and studying the blood on it.

Too quick for me!
There’s money in this youth.

Re-enter Lydia, hatted and gloved.
Lydia |

O Heaven! you bleed.

Cashel |

Lend me a key or other frigid object,
That I may put it down my back, and staunch
The welling life stream.

Lydia |

Giving him her keys. Oh, what have you done?

Cashel |

Flush on the boko napped your footman’s left.

Lydia |

I do not understand.

Cashel |

True. Pardon me.
I have received a blow upon the nose
In sport from Bashville. Next, ablution; else
I shall be total gules. He hurries out.

Lydia |

How well he speaks!
There is a silver trumpet in his lips
That stirs me to the finger ends. His nose
Dropt lovely color: ’tis a perfect blood.
I would ’twere mingled with mine own!

Enter Bashville.

What now?

Bashville |

Madam, the coachman can no longer wait:
The horses will take cold.

Lydia |

I do beseech him
A moment’s grace. Oh, mockery of wealth!
The third class passenger unchidden rides
Whither and when he will: obsequious trams
Await him hourly: subterranean tubes
With tireless coursers whisk him through the town;
But we, the rich, are slaves to Houyhnhnms:
We wait upon their colds, and frowst all day
Indoors, if they but cough or spurn their hay.

Bashville |

Madam, an omnibus to Euston Road,
And thence t’ th’ Angel—

Enter Cashel.
Lydia |

Let us haste, my love:
The coachman is impatient.

Cashel |

Did he guess
He stays for Cashel Byron, he’d outwait
Pompei’s sentinel. Let us away.
This day of deeds, as yet but half begun,
Must ended be in merrie Islington.

Exeunt Lydia and Cashel.
Bashville |

Gods! how she hangs on’s arm! I am alone.
Now let me lift the cover from my soul.
O wasted humbleness! Deluded diffidence!
How often have I said, Lie down, poor footman:
She’ll never stoop to thee, rear as thou wilt
Thy powder to the sky. And now, by Heaven,
She stoops below me; condescends upon
This hero of the pothouse, whose exploits,
Writ in my character from my last place,
Would damn me into ostlerdom. And yet
There’s an eternal justice in it; for
By so much as the ne’er subduéd Indian
Excels the servile Negro, doth this ruffian
Precedence take of me. “Ich dien.” Damnation!
I serve. My motto should have been, “I scalp.”
And yet I do not bear the yoke for gold.
Because I love her I have blacked her boots;
Because I love her I have cleaned her knives,
Doing in this the office of a boy,
Whilst, like the celebrated maid that milks
And does the meanest chares, I’ve shared the passions
Of Cleopatra. It has been my pride
To give her place the greater altitude
By lowering mine, and of her dignity
To be so jealous that my cheek has flamed
Even at the thought of such a deep disgrace
As love for such a one as I would be
For such a one as she; and now! and now!
A prizefighter! O irony! O bathos!
To have made way for this! Oh, Bashville, Bashville:
Why hast thou thought so lowly of thyself,
So heavenly high of her? Let what will come,
My love must speak: ’twas my respect was dumb.

Scene II

The Agricultural Hall in Islington, crowded with spectators. In the arena a throne, with a boxing ring before it. A balcony above on the right, occupied by persons of fashion: among others, Lydia and Lord Worthington.

Flourish. Enter Lucian and Cetewayo, with Chiefs in attendance.
Cetewayo |

Is this the Hall of Husbandmen?

Lucian |

It is.

Cetewayo |

Are these anaemic dogs the English people?

Lucian |

Mislike us not for our complexions,
The pallid liveries of the pall of smoke
Belched by the mighty chimneys of our factories,
And by the million patent kitchen ranges
Of happy English homes.

Cetewayo |

When first I came
I deemed those chimneys the fuliginous altars
Of some infernal god. I now perceive
The English dare not look upon the sky.
They are moles and owls: they call upon the soot
To cover them.

Lucian |

You cannot understand
The greatness of this people, Cetewayo.
You are a savage, reasoning like a child.
Each pallid English face conceals a brain
Whose powers are proven in the works of Newton
And in the plays of the immortal Shakespeare.
There is not one of all the thousands here
But, if you placed him naked in the desert,
Would presently construct a steam engine,
And lay a cable t’ th’ Antipodes.

Cetewayo |

Have I been brought a million miles by sea
To learn how men can lie! Know, Father Webber,
Men become civilized through twin diseases,
Terror and Greed to wit: these two conjoined
Become the grisly parents of Invention.
Why does the trembling white with frantic toil
Of hand and brain produce the magic gun
That slays a mile off, whilst the manly Zulu
Dares look his foe i’ the face; fights foot to foot;
Lives in the present; drains the Here and Now;
Makes life a long reality, and death
A moment only! whilst your Englishman
Glares on his burning candle’s winding-sheets,
Counting the steps of his approaching doom,
And in the murky corners ever sees
Two horrid shadows, Death and Poverty:
In the which anguish an unnatural edge
Comes on his frighted brain, which straight devises
Strange frauds by which to filch unearnéd gold,
Mad crafts by which to slay unfacéd foes,
Until at last his agonized desire
Makes possibility its slave. And then—
Horrible climax! All-undoing spite!—
Th’ importunate clutching of the coward’s hand
From wearied Nature Devastation’s secrets
Doth wrest; when straight the brave black-livered man
Is blown explosively from off the globe;
And Death and Dread, with their white-livered slaves
O’er-run the earth, and through their chattering teeth
Stammer the words “Survival of the Fittest.”
Enough of this: I came not here to talk.
Thou say’st thou hast two white-faced ones who dare
Fight without guns, and spearless, to the death.
Let them be brought.

Lucian |

They fight not to the death,
But under strictest rules: as, for example,
Half of their persons shall not be attacked;
Nor shall they suffer blows when they fall down,
Nor stroke of foot at any time. And, further,
That frequent opportunities of rest
With succor and refreshment be secured them.

Cetewayo |

Ye gods, what cowards! Zululand, my Zululand:
Personified Pusillanimity
Hath ta’en thee from the bravest of the brave!

Lucian |

Lo, the rude savage whose untutored mind
Cannot perceive self-evidence, and doubts
That Brave and English mean the selfsame thing!

Cetewayo |

Well, well, produce these heroes. I surmise
They will be carried by their nurses, lest
Some barking dog or bumbling bee should scare them.

Cetewayo takes his state. Enter Paradise.
Lydia |

What hateful wretch is this whose mighty thews
Presage destruction to his adversaries?

Lord Worthington |

’Tis Paradise.

Lydia |

He of whom Cashel spoke?
A dreadful thought ices my heart. Oh, why
Did Cashel leave us at the door?

Enter Cashel.
Lord Worthington |

Behold!
The champion comes.

Lydia |

Oh, I could kiss him now,
Here, before all the world. His boxing things
Render him most attractive. But I fear
Yon villain’s fists may maul him.

Lord Worthington |

Have no fear.
Hark! the king speaks.

Cetewayo |

Ye sons of the white queen:
Tell me your names and deeds ere ye fall to.

Paradise |

Your royal highness, you beholds a bloke
What gets his living honest by his fists.
I may not have the polish of some toffs
As I could mention on; but up to now
No man has took my number down. I scale
Close on twelve stun; my age is twenty-three;
And at Bill Richardson’s Blue Anchor pub
Am to be heard of any day by such
As likes the job. I don’t know, governor,
As ennythink remains for me to say.

Cetewayo |

Six wives and thirty oxen shalt thou have
If on the sand thou leave thy foeman dead.
Methinks he looks full scornfully on thee.
To Cashel. Ha! dost thou not so?

Cashel |

Sir, I do beseech you
To name the bone, or limb, or special place
Where you would have me hit him with this fist.

Cetewayo |

Thou hast a noble brow; but much I fear
Thine adversary will disfigure it.

Cashel |

There’s a divinity that shapes our ends
Rough hew them how we will. Give me the gloves.

The Master of the Revels |

Paradise, a professor.
Cashel Byron,
Also professor. Time!

They spar.
Lydia |

Eternity
It seems to me until this fight be done.

Cashel |

Dread monarch: this is called the upper cut,
And this a hook-hit of mine own invention.
The hollow region where I plant this blow
Is called the mark. My left, you will observe,
I chiefly use for long shots: with my right
Aiming beside the angle of the jaw
And landing with a certain delicate screw
I without violence knock my foeman out.
Mark how he falls forward upon his face!
The rules allow ten seconds to get up;
And as the man is still quite silly, I
Might safely finish him; but my respect
For your most gracious majesty’s desire
To see some further triumphs of the science
Of self-defence postpones awhile his doom.

Paradise |

How can a bloke do hisself proper justice
With pillows on his fists?

He tears off his gloves and attacks Cashel with his bare knuckles.
The Crowd |

Unfair! The rules!

Cetewayo |

The joy of battle surges boiling up
And bids me join the melee. Isandhlana
And Victory!

He falls on the bystanders.
The Chiefs |

Victory and Isandhlana!

They run amok. General panic and stampede. The ring is swept away.

Lucian |

Forbear these most irregular proceedings.
Police! Police!

He engages Cetewayo with his umbrella. The balcony comes down with a crash. Screams from its occupants. Indescribable confusion.
Cashel |

Dragging Lydia from the struggling heap.

My love, my love, art hurt?

Lydia |

No, no; but save my sore o’ermatchéd cousin.

A Policeman |

Give us a lead, sir. Save the English flag.
Africa tramples on it.

Cashel |

Africa!
Not all the continents whose mighty shoulders
The dancing diamonds of the seas bedeck
Shall trample on the blue with spots of white.
Now, Lydia, mark thy lover.

He charges the Zulus.
Lydia |

Hercules
Cannot withstand him. See: the king is down;
The tallest chief is up, heels over head,
Tossed corklike o’er my Cashel’s sinewy back;
And his lieutenant all deflated gasps
For breath upon the sand. The others fly
In vain: his fist o’er magic distances
Like a chameleon’s tongue shoots to its mark;
And the last African upon his knees
Sues piteously for quarter. Rushing into Cashel’s arms. Oh, my hero:
Thou’st saved us all this day.

Cashel |

’Twas all for thee.

Cetewayo |

Trying to rise. Have I been struck by lightning?

Lucian |

Sir, your conduct
Can only be described as most ungentlemanly.

Policeman |

One of the prone is white.

Cashel |

’Tis Paradise.

Policeman |

He’s choking: he has something in his mouth.

Lydia |

To Cashel.

Oh Heaven! there is blood upon your hip.
You’re hurt.

Cashel |

The morsel in yon wretch’s mouth
Was bitten out of me.

Sensation. Lydia screams and swoons in Cashel’s arms.

Act III

Wiltstoken. A room in the Warren Lodge.

Lydia at her writing table.
Lydia |

O Past and Present, how ye do conflict
As here I sit writing my father’s life!
The autumn woodland woos me from without
With whispering of leaves and dainty airs
To leave this fruitless haunting of the past.
My father was a very learnéd man.
I sometimes think I shall oldmaided be
Ere I unlearn the things he taught to me.

Enter Policeman.
Policeman |

Asking your ladyship to pardon me
For this intrusion, might I be so bold
As ask a question of your people here
Concerning the Queen’s peace?

Lydia |

My people here
Are but a footman and a simple maid;
And both have craved a holiday to join
Some local festival. But, sir, your helmet
Proclaims the Metropolitan Police.

Policeman |

Madam, it does; and I may now inform you
That what you term a local festival
Is a most hideous outrage ’gainst the law,
Which we to quell from London have come down:
In short, a prizefight. My sole purpose here
Is to inquire whether your ladyship
Any bad characters this afternoon
Has noted in the neighborhood.

Lydia |

No, none, sir.
I had not let my maid go forth today
Thought I the roads unsafe.

Policeman |

Fear nothing, madam:
The force protects the fair. My mission here
Is to wreak ultion for the broken law.
I wish your ladyship good afternoon.

Lydia |

Good afternoon. Exit Policeman.
A prizefight! O my heart!
Cashel: hast thou deceived me? Can it be
Thou hast backslidden to the hateful calling
I asked thee to eschew?
O wretched maid,
Why didst thou flee from London to this place
To write thy father’s life, whenas in town
Thou might’st have kept a guardian eye on him—
What’s that? A flying footstep—

Enter Cashel.
Cashel |

Sanctuary!
The law is on my track. What! Lydia here!

Lydia |

Ay: Lydia here. Hast thou done murder, then,
That in so horrible a guise thou comest?

Cashel |

Murder! I would I had. Yon cannibal
Hath forty thousand lives; and I have ta’en
But thousands thirty-nine. I tell thee, Lydia,
On the impenetrable sarcolobe
That holds his seedling brain these fists have pounded
By Shrewsb’ry clock an hour. This bruiséd grass
And cakéd mud adhering to my form
I have acquired in rolling on the sod
Clinched in his grip. This scanty reefer coat
For decency snatched up as fast I fled
When the police arrived, belongs to Mellish.
’Tis all too short; hence my display of rib
And forearm mother-naked. Be not wroth
Because I seem to wink at you: by Heaven,
’Twas Paradise that plugged me in the eye
Which I perforce keep closing. Pity me,
My training wasted and my blows unpaid,
Sans stakes, sans victory, sans everything
I had hoped to win. Oh, I could sit me down
And weep for bitterness.

Lydia |

Thou wretch, begone.

Cashel |

Begone!

Lydia |

I say begone. Oh, tiger’s heart
Wrapped in a young man’s hide, canst thou not live
In love with Nature and at peace with Man?
Must thou, although thy hands were never made
To blacken others’ eyes, still batter at
The image of Divinity? I loathe thee.
Hence from my house and never see me more.

Cashel |

I go. The meanest lad on thy estate
Would not betray me thus. But ’tis no matter. He opens the door.
Ha! the police. I’m lost. He shuts the door again.
Now shalt thou see
My last fight fought. Exhausted as I am,
To capture me will cost the coppers dear.
Come one, come all!

Lydia |

Oh, hide thee, I implore:
I cannot see thee hunted down like this.
There is my room. Conceal thyself therein.
Quick, I command. He goes into the room.
With horror I foresee,
Lydia, that never lied, must lie for thee.

Enter Policeman, with Paradise and Mellish in custody, Bashville, constables, and others.
Policeman |

Keep back your bruiséd prisoner lest he shock
This wellbred lady’s nerves. Your pardon, ma’am;
But have you seen by chance the other one?
In this direction he was seen to run.

Lydia |

A man came here anon with bloody hands
And aspect that did turn my soul to snow.

Policeman |

’Twas he. What said he?

Lydia |

Begged for sanctuary.
I bade the man begone.

Policeman |

Most properly.
Saw you which way he went?

Lydia |

I cannot tell.

Paradise |

He seen me coming; and he done a bunk.

Policeman |

Peace, there. Excuse his damaged features, lady:
He’s Paradise; and this one’s Byron’s trainer,
Mellish.

Mellish |

Injurious copper, in thy teeth
I hurl the lie. I am no trainer, I.
My father, a respected missionary,
Apprenticed me at fourteen years of age
T’ the poetry writing. To these woods I came
With Nature to commune. My revery
Was by a sound of blows rudely dispelled.
Mindful of what my sainted parent taught,
I rushed to play the peacemaker, when lo!
These minions of the law laid hands on me.

Bashville |

A lovely woman, with distracted cries,
In most resplendent fashionable frock,
Approaches like a wounded antelope.

Enter Adelaide Gisborne.
Adelaide |

Where is my Cashel? Hath he been arrested?

Policeman |

I would I had thy Cashel by the collar:
He hath escaped me.

Adelaide |

Praises be forever!

Lydia |

Why dost thou call the missing man thy Cashel?

Adelaide |

He is mine only son.

All |

Thy son!

Adelaide |

My son.

Lydia |

I thought his mother hardly would have known him,
So crushed his countenance.

Adelaide |

A ribald peer,
Lord Worthington by name, this morning came
With honeyed words beseeching me to mount
His four-in-hand, and to the country hie
To see some English sport. Being by nature
Frank as a child, I fell into the snare,
But took so long to dress that the design
Failed of its full effect; for not until
The final round we reached the horrid scene.
Be silent all; for now I do approach
My tragedy’s catastrophe. Know, then,
That Heaven did bless me with an only son,
A boy devoted to his doting mother—

Policeman |

Hark! did you hear an oath from yonder room?

Adelaide |

Respect a brokenhearted mother’s grief,
And do not interrupt me in my scene.
Ten years ago my darling disappeared
(Ten dreary twelvemonths of continuous tears,
Tears that have left me prematurely aged;
For I am younger far than I appear).
Judge of my anguish when today I saw
Stripped to the waist, and fighting like a demon
With one who, whatsoe’er his humble virtues,
Was clearly not a gentleman, my son!

All |

O strange event! O passing tearful tale!

Adelaide |

I thank you from the bottom of my heart
For the reception you have given my woe;
And now I ask, where is my wretched son?
He must at once come home with me, and quit
A course of life that cannot be allowed.

Enter Cashel.
Cashel |

Policeman: I do yield me to the law.

Lydia |

Oh, no.

Adelaide |

My son!

Cashel |

My mother! Do not kiss me.
My visage is too sore.

Policeman |

The lady hid him.
This is a regular plant. You cannot be
Up to that sex. To Cashel. You come along with me.

Lydia |

Fear not, my Cashel: I will bail thee out.

Cashel |

Never. I do embrace my doom with joy.
With Paradise in Pentonville or Portland
I shall feel safe: there are no mothers there.

Adelaide |

Ungracious boy—

Cashel |

Constable: bear me hence.

Mellish |

Oh, let me sweetest reconcilement make
By calling to thy mind that moving song:—

Sings.

They say there is no other—

Cashel |

Forbear at once, or the next note of music
That falls upon thine ear shall clang in thunder
From the last trumpet.

Adelaide |

A disgraceful threat
To level at this virtuous old man.

Lydia |

Oh, Cashel, if thou scorn’st thy mother thus,
How wilt thou treat thy wife?

Cashel |

There spake my fate:
I knew you would say that. Oh, mothers, mothers,
Would you but let your wretched sons alone
Life were worth living! Had I any choice
In this importunate relationship?
None. And until that high auspicious day
When the millennium on an orphaned world
Shall dawn, and man upon his fellow look,
Reckless of consanguinity, my mother
And I within the selfsame hemisphere
Conjointly may not dwell.

Adelaide |

Ungentlemanly!

Cashel |

I am no gentleman. I am a criminal,
Redhanded, baseborn—

Adelaide |

Baseborn! Who dares say it?
Thou art the son and heir of Bingley Bumpkin
FitzAlgernon de Courcy Cashel Byron,
Sieur of Park Lane and Overlord of Dorset,
Who after three months’ wedded happiness
Rashly fordid himself with prussic acid,
Leaving a tearstained note to testify
That having sweetly honeymooned with me,
He now could say, O Death, where is thy sting?

Policeman |

Sir: had I known your quality, this cop
I had averted; but it is too late.
The law’s above us both.

Enter Lucian, with an Order in Council.
Lucian |

Not so, policeman.
I bear a message from The Throne itself
Of fullest amnesty for Byron’s past.
Nay, more: of Dorset deputy lieutenant
He is proclaimed. Further, it is decreed,
In memory of his glorious victory
Over our country’s foes at Islington,
The flag of England shall forever bear
On azure field twelve swanlike spots of white;
And by an exercise of feudal right
Too long disused in this anarchic age
Our sovereign doth confer on him the hand
Of Miss Carew, Wiltstoken’s wealthy heiress. General acclamation.

Policeman |

Was anything, sir, said about me?

Lucian |

Thy faithful services are not forgot:
In future call thyself Inspector Smith. Renewed acclamation.

Policeman |

I thank you, sir. I thank you, gentlemen.

Lucian |

My former opposition, valiant champion,
Was based on the supposed discrepancy
Betwixt your rank and Lydia’s. Here’s my hand.

Bashville |

And I do here unselfishly renounce
All my pretensions to my lady’s favor. Sensation.

Lydia |

What, Bashville! didst thou love me?

Bashville |

Madam: yes.
’Tis said: now let me leave immediately.

Lydia |

In taking, Bashville, this most tasteful course
You are but acting as a gentleman
In the like case would act. I fully grant
Your perfect right to make a declaration
Which flatters me and honors your ambition.
Prior attachment bids me firmly say
That whilst my Cashel lives, and polyandry
Rests foreign to the British social scheme,
Your love is hopeless; still, your services,
Made zealous by disinterested passion,
Would greatly add to my domestic comfort;
And if—

Cashel |

Excuse me. I have other views.
I’ve noted in this man such aptitude
For art and exercise in his defence
That I prognosticate for him a future
More glorious than my past. Henceforth I dub him
The Admirable Bashville, Byron’s Novice;
And to the utmost of my mended fortunes
Will back him ’gainst the world at ten stone six.

All |

Hail, Byron’s Novice, champion that shall be!

Bashville |

Must I renounce my lovely lady’s service,
And mar the face of man?

Cashel |

’Tis Fate’s decree.
For know, rash youth, that in this star crost world
Fate drives us all to find our chiefest good
In what we can, and not in what we would.

Policeman |

A post-horn—hark!

Cashel |

What noise of wheels is this?

Lord Worthington drives upon the scene in his four-in-hand, and descends.
Adelaide |

Perfidious peer!

Lord Worthington |

Sweet Adelaide—

Adelaide |

Forbear,
Audacious one: my name is Mrs. Byron.

Lord Worthington |

Oh, change that title for the sweeter one
Of Lady Worthington.

Cashel |

Unhappy man,
You know not what you do.

Lydia |

Nay, ’tis a match
Of most auspicious promise. Dear Lord Worthington,
You tear from us our mother-in-law—

Cashel |

Ha! True.

Lydia |

—but we will make the sacrifice. She blushes:
At least she very prettily produces
Blushing’s effect.

Adelaide |

My lord: I do accept you.

They embrace. Rejoicings.
Cashel |

Aside.

It wrings my heart to see my noble backer
Lay waste his future thus. The world’s a chessboard,
And we the merest pawns in fist of Fate.
Aloud. And now, my friends, gentle and simple both,
Our scene draws to a close. In lawful course
As Dorset’s deputy lieutenant I
Do pardon all concerned this afternoon
In the late gross and brutal exhibition
Of miscalled sport.

Lydia |

Throwing herself into his arms.

Your boats are burnt at last.

Cashel |

This is the face that burnt a thousand boats,
And ravished Cashel Byron from the ring.
But to conclude. Let William Paradise
Devote himself to science, and acquire,
By studying the player’s speech in Hamlet,
A more refined address. You, Robert Mellish,
To the Blue Anchor hostelry attend him;
Assuage his hurts, and bid Bill Richardson
Limit his access to the fatal tap.
Now mount we on my backer’s four-in-hand,
And to St. George’s Church, whose portico
Hanover Square shuts off from Conduit Street,
Repair we all. Strike up the wedding march;
And, Mellish, let thy melodies trill forth
Broad o’er the wold as fast we bowl along.
Give me the post-horn. Loose the flowing rein;
And up to London drive with might and main.

Exeunt.

Note on Modern Prizefighting

In 1882, when this book was written, prizefighting seemed to be dying out. Sparring matches with boxing gloves, under the Queensberry rules, kept pugilism faintly alive; but it was not popular, because the public, which cares only for the excitement of a strenuous fight, believed then that the boxing glove made sparring as harmless a contest of pure skill as a fencing match with buttoned foils. This delusion was supported by the limitation of the sparring match to boxing. In the prize-ring under the old rules a combatant might trip, hold, or throw his antagonist; so that each round finished either with a knockdown blow, which, except when it is really a liedown blow, is much commoner in fiction than it was in the ring, or with a visible body-to-body struggle ending in a fall. In a sparring match all that happens is that a man with a watch in his hand cries out “Time!” whereupon the two champions prosaically stop sparring and sit down for a minute’s rest and refreshment. The unaccustomed and inexpert spectator in those days did not appreciate the severity of the exertion or the risk of getting hurt: he underrated them as ignorantly as he would have overrated the more dramatically obvious terrors of a prizefight. Consequently the interest in the annual sparrings for the Queensberry Championships was confined to the few amateurs who had some critical knowledge of the game of boxing, and to the survivors of the generation for which the fight between Sayers and Heenan had been described in The Times as solemnly as the University Boat Race. In short, pugilism was out of fashion because the police had suppressed the only form of it which fascinated the public by its undissembled pugnacity.

All that was needed to rehabilitate it was the discovery that the glove fight is a more trying and dangerous form of contest than the old knuckle fight. Nobody knew that then: everybody knows it, or ought to know it, now. And, accordingly, pugilism is more prosperous today than it has ever been before.

How far this result was foreseen by the author of the Queensberry Rules, which superseded those of the old prize-ring, will probably never be known. There is no doubt that they served their immediate turn admirably. That turn was, the keeping alive of boxing in the teeth of the law against prizefighting. Magistrates believed, as the public believed, that when men’s knuckles were muffled in padded gloves; when they were forbidden to wrestle or hold one another; when the duration of a round was fixed by the clock, and the number of rounds limited to what seems (to those who have never tried) to be easily within the limits of ordinary endurance; and when the traditional interval for rest between the rounds was doubled, that then indeed violence must be checkmated, so that the worst the boxers could do was to “spar for points” before three gentlemanly members of the Stock Exchange, who would carefully note the said points on an examination paper at the ring side, awarding marks only for skill and elegance, and sternly discountenancing the claims of brute force. It may be that both the author of the rules and the “judges” who administered them in the earlier days really believed all this; for, as far as I know, the limit of an amateur pugilist’s romantic credulity has never yet been reached and probably never will. But if so, their good intentions were upset by the operation of a single new rule. Thus.

In the old prize-ring a round had no fixed duration. It was terminated by the fall of one of the combatants (in practice usually both of them), and was followed by an interval of half a minute for recuperation. The practical effect of this was that a combatant could always get a respite of half a minute whenever he wanted it by pretending to be knocked down: “finding the earth the safest place,” as the old phrase went. For this the Marquess of Queensberry substituted a rule that a round with the gloves should last a specified time, usually three or four minutes, and that a combatant who did not stand up to his opponent continuously during that time (ten seconds being allowed for rising in the event of a knockdown) lost the battle. That unobtrusively slipped-in ten seconds limit has produced the modern glove fight. Its practical effect is that a man dazed by a blow or a fall for, say, twelve seconds, which would not have mattered in an old-fashioned fight with its thirty seconds interval,[1] has under the Queensberry rules either to lose or else stagger to his feet in a helpless condition and be eagerly battered into insensibility by his opponent before he can recover his powers of self-defence. The notion that such a battery cannot be inflicted with boxing gloves is only entertained by people who have never used them or seen them used. I may say that I have myself received, in an accident, a blow in the face, involving two macadamized holes in it, more violent than the most formidable pugilist could have given me with his bare knuckles. This blow did not stun or disable me even momentarily. On the other hand, I have seen a man knocked quite silly by a tap from the most luxurious sort of boxing glove made, wielded by a quite unathletic literary man sparring for the first time in his life. The human jaw, like the human elbow, is provided, as every boxer knows, with a “funny bone”; and the pugilist who is lucky enough to jar that funny bone with a blow practically has his opponent at his mercy for at least ten seconds. Such a blow is called a “knockout.” The funny bone and the ten-seconds rule explain the development of Queensberry sparring into the modern knocking-out match or glove fight.

This development got its first impulse from the discovery by sparring competitors that the only way in which a boxer, however skilful, could make sure of a verdict in his favor, was by knocking his opponent out. This will be easily understood by anyone who remembers the pugilistic Bench of those days. The “judges” at the competitions were invariably ex-champions: that is, men who had themselves won former competitions. Now the judicial faculty, if it is not altogether a legal fiction, is at all events pretty rare even among men whose ordinary pursuits tend to cultivate it, and to train them in dispassionateness. Among pugilists it is quite certainly very often nonexistent. The average pugilist is a violent partisan, who seldom witnesses a hot encounter without getting much more excited than the combatants themselves. Further, he is usually filled with a local patriotism which makes him, if a Londoner, deem it a duty to disparage a provincial, and, if a provincial, to support a provincial at all hazards against a cockney. He has, besides, personal favorites on whose success he bets wildly. On great occasions like the annual competitions, he is less judicial and more convivial after dinner (when the finals are sparred) than before it. Being seldom a fine boxer, he often regards skill and style as a reflection on his own deficiencies, and applauds all verdicts given for “game” alone. When he is a technically good boxer, he is all the less likely to be a good critic, as Providence seldom lavishes two rare gifts on the same individual. Even if we take the sanguine and patriotic view that when you appoint such a man a judge, and thus stop his betting, you may depend on his sense of honor and responsibility to neutralize all the other disqualifications, they are sure to be exhibited most extremely by the audience before which he has to deliver his verdict. Now it takes a good deal of strength of mind to give an unpopular verdict; and this strength of mind is not necessarily associated with the bodily hardihood of the champion boxer. Consequently, when the strength of mind is not forthcoming, the audience becomes the judge, and the popular competitor gets the verdict. And the shortest way to the heart of a big audience is to stick to your man; stop his blows bravely with your nose and return them with interest; cover yourself and him with your own gore; and outlast him in a hearty punching match.

It was under these circumstances that the competitors for sparring championships concluded that they had better decide the bouts themselves by knocking their opponents out, and waste no time in cultivating a skill and style for which they got little credit, and which actually set some of the judges against them. The public instantly began to take an interest in the sport. And so, by a pretty rapid evolution, the dexterities which the boxing glove and the Queensberry rules were supposed to substitute for the old brutalities of Sayers and Heenan were really abolished by them.

Let me describe the process as I saw it myself. Twenty years ago a poet friend of mine, who, like all poets, delighted in combats, insisted on my sharing his interest in pugilism, and took me about to all the boxing competitions of the day. I was nothing loth; for, my own share of original sin apart, anyone with a sense of comedy must find the arts of self-defence delightful (for a time) through their pedantry, their quackery, and their action and reaction between amateur romantic illusion and professional eye to business.

The fencing world, as Molière well knew, is perhaps a more exquisite example of a fool’s paradise than the boxing world; but it is too restricted and expensive to allow play for popular character in a non-duelling country, as the boxing world (formerly called quite appropriately “the Fancy”) does. At all events, it was the boxing world that came under my notice; and as I was amused and sceptically observant, whilst the true amateurs about me were, for the most part, merely excited and duped, my evidence may have a certain value when the question comes up again for legislative consideration, as it assuredly will some day.

The first competitions I attended were at the beginning of the eighties, at Lillie Bridge, for the Queensberry championships. There were but few competitors, including a fair number of gentlemen; and the style of boxing aimed at was the “science” bequeathed from the old prize-ring by Ned Donnelly, a pupil of Nat Langham. Langham had once defeated Sayers, and thereby taught him the tactics by which he defeated Heenan. There was as yet no special technique of glove fighting: the traditions and influence of the old ring were unquestioned and supreme; and they distinctly made for brains, skill, quickness, and mobility, as against brute violence, not at all on moral grounds, but because experience had proved that giants did not succeed in the ring under the old rules, and that crafty middleweights did.

This did not last long. The spectators did not want to see skill defeating violence: they wanted to see violence drawing blood and pounding its way to a savage and exciting victory in the shortest possible time (the old prizefight usually dragged on for hours, and was ended by exhaustion rather than by victory). So did most of the judges. And the public and the judges naturally had their wish; for the competitors, as I have already explained, soon discovered that the only way to make sure of a favorable verdict was to “knock out” their adversary. All pretence of sparring “for points”: that is, for marks on an examination paper filled up by the judges, and representing nothing but impracticable academic pedantry in its last ditch, was dropped; and the competitions became frank fights, with abundance of blood drawn, and “knockouts” always imminent. Needless to add, the glove fight soon began to pay. The select and thinly attended spars on the turf at Lillie Bridge gave way to crowded exhibitions on the hard boards of St. James’s Hall. These were organized by the Boxing Association; and to them the provinces, notably Birmingham, sent up a new race of boxers whose sole aim was to knock their opponent insensible by a right-hand blow on the jaw, knowing well that no Birmingham man could depend on a verdict before a London audience for any less undeniable achievement.

The final step was taken by an American pugilist. He threw off the last shred of the old hypocrisy of the gloved hand by challenging the whole world to produce a man who could stand before him for a specified time without being knocked out. His brief but glorious career completely reestablished pugilism by giving a worldwide advertisement to the fact that the boxing glove spares nothing but the public conscience, and that as much ferocity, bloodshed, pain, and risk of serious injury or death can be enjoyed at a glove fight as at an old-fashioned prizefight, whilst the strain on the combatants is much greater. It is true that these horrors are greatly exaggerated by the popular imagination, and that if boxing were really as dangerous as bicycling, a good many of its heroes would give it up from simple fright; but this only means that there is a maximum of damage to the spectator by demoralization, combined with the minimum of deterrent risk to the poor scrapper in the ring.

Poor scrapper, though, is hardly the word for a modern fashionable American pugilist. To him the exploits of Cashel Byron will seem ludicrously obscure and low-lived. The contests in which he engages are like Handel Festivals: they take place in huge halls before enormous audiences, with cinematographs hard at work recording the scene for reproduction in London and elsewhere. The combatants divide thousands of dollars of gate-money between them: indeed, if an impecunious English curate were to go to America and challenge the premier pugilist, the spectacle of a match between the Church and the Ring would attract a colossal crowd; and the loser’s share of the gate would be a fortune to a curate—assuming that the curate would be the loser, which is by no means a foregone conclusion. At all events, it would be well worth a bruise or two. So my story of the Agricultural Hall, where William Paradise sparred for half a guinea, and Cashel Byron stood out for ten guineas, is no doubt read by the profession in America with amused contempt. In 1882 it was, like most of my conceptions, a daring anticipation of coming social developments, though today it seems as far out of date as Slender pulling Sackerson’s chain.

Of these latter-day commercial developments of glove fighting I know nothing beyond what I gather from the newspapers. The banging matches of the eighties, in which not one competitor in twenty either exhibited artistic skill, or, in his efforts to knock out his adversary, succeeded in anything but tiring and disappointing himself, were for the most part tedious beyond human endurance. When, after wading through Boxiana and the files of Bell’s Life at the British Museum, I had written Cashel Byron’s Profession, I found I had exhausted the comedy of the subject; and as a game of patience or solitaire was decidedly superior to an average spar for a championship in point of excitement, I went no more to the competitions. Since then six or seven generations of boxers have passed into peaceful pursuits; and I have no doubt that my experience is in some respects out of date. The National Sporting Club has arisen; and though I have never attended its reunions, I take its record of three pugilists slain as proving an enormous multiplication of contests, since such accidents are very rare, and in fact do not happen to reasonably healthy men. I am prepared to admit also that the disappearance of the old prize-ring technique must by this time have been compensated by the importation from America of a new glove-fighting technique; for even in a knocking-out match, brains will try conclusions with brawn, and finally establish a standard of skill; but I notice that in the leading contests in America luck seems to be on the side of brawn, and brain frequently finishes in a state of concussion, a loser after performing miracles of “science.” I use the word luck advisedly; for one of the fascinations of boxing to the gambler (who is the main pillar of the sporting world) is that it is a game of hardihood, pugnacity and skill, all at the mercy of chance. The knockout itself is a pure chance. I have seen two powerful laborers batter one another’s jaws with all their might for several rounds apparently without giving one another as much as a toothache. And I have seen a winning pugilist collapse at a trifling knock landed by a fluke at the fatal angle. I once asked an ancient prizefighter what a knockout was like when it did happen. He was a man of limited descriptive powers; so he simply pointed to the heavens and said, “Up in a balloon.” An amateur pugilist, with greater command of language, told me that “all the milk in his head suddenly boiled over.” I am aware that some modern glove fighters of the American school profess to have reduced the knockout to a science. But the results of the leading American combats conclusively discredit the pretension. When a boxer so superior to his opponent in skill as to be able practically to hit him where he pleases not only fails to knock him out, but finally gets knocked out himself, it is clear that the phenomenon is as complete a mystery pugilistically as it is physiologically, though every pugilist and every doctor may pretend to understand it. It is only fair to add that it has not been proved that any permanent injury to the brain results from it. In any case the brain, as English society is at present constituted, can hardly be considered a vital organ.

This, to the best of my knowledge, is the technical history of the modern revival of pugilism. It is only one more example of the fact that legislators, like other people, must learn their business by their own mistakes, and that the first attempts to suppress an evil by law generally intensify it. Prizefighting, though often connived at, was never legal. Even in its palmiest days prizefights were banished from certain counties by hostile magistrates, just as they have been driven from the United States and England to Belgium on certain occasions in our own time. But as the exercise of sparring, conducted by a couple of gentlemen with boxing gloves on, was regarded as part of a manly physical education, a convention grew up by which it became practically legal to make a citizen’s nose bleed by a punch from the gloved fist, and illegal to do the same thing with the naked knuckles. A code of glove-fighting rules was drawn up by a prominent patron of pugilism; and this code was practically legalized by the fact that even when a death resulted from a contest under these rules the accessories were not punished. No question was raised as to whether the principals were paid to fight for the amusement of the spectators, or whether a prize for the winner was provided in stakes, share of the gate, or a belt with the title of champion. These, the true criteria of prizefighting, were ignored; and the sole issue raised was whether the famous dictum of Dr. Watts, “Your little hands were never made, etc.,” had been duly considered by providing the said little hands with a larger hitting surface, a longer range, and four ounces extra weight.

In short, then, what has happened has been the virtual legalization of prizefighting under cover of the boxing glove. And this is exactly what public opinion desires. We do not like fighting; but we like looking on at fights: therefore we require a law which will punish the prizefighter if he hits us, and secure us the protection of the police whilst we sit in a comfortable hall and watch him hitting another prizefighter. And that is just the law we have got at present.

Thus Cashel Byron’s plea for a share of the legal toleration accorded to the vivisector has been virtually granted since he made it. The legalization of cruelty to domestic animals under cover of the anesthetic is only the extreme instance of the same social phenomenon as the legalization of prizefighting under cover of the boxing glove. The same passion explains the fascination of both practices; and in both, the professors—pugilists and physiologists alike—have to persuade the Home Office that their pursuits are painless and beneficial. But there is also between them the remarkable difference that the pugilist, who has to suffer as much as he inflicts, wants his work to be as painless and harmless as possible whilst persuading the public that it is thrillingly dangerous and destructive, whilst the vivisector wants to enjoy a total exemption from humane restrictions in his laboratory whilst persuading the public that pain is unknown there. Consequently the vivisector is not only crueller than the prizefighter, but, through the pressure of public opinion, a much more resolute and uncompromising liar. For this no one but a Pharisee will single him out for special blame. All public men lie, as a matter of good taste, on subjects which are considered serious (in England a serious occasion means simply an occasion on which nobody tells the truth); and however illogical or capricious the point of honor may be in man, it is too absurd to assume that the doctors who, from among innumerable methods of research, select that of tormenting animals hideously, will hesitate to come on a platform and tell a soothing fib to prevent the public from punishing them. No criminal is expected to plead guilty, or to refrain from pleading not guilty with all the plausibility at his command. In prizefighting such mendacity is not necessary: on the contrary, if a famous pugilist were to assure the public that a blow delivered with a boxing glove could do no injury and cause no pain, and the public believed him, the sport would instantly lose its following. It is the prizefighter’s interest to abolish the real cruelties of the ring and to exaggerate the imaginary cruelties of it. It is the vivisector’s interest to refine upon the cruelties of the laboratory, whilst persuading the public that his victims pass into a delicious euthanasia and leave behind them a row of bottles containing infallible cures for all the diseases. Just so, too, does the trainer of performing animals assure us that his dogs and cats and elephants and lions are taught their senseless feats by pure kindness.

The public, as Julius Caesar remarked nearly two thousand years ago, believes, on the whole, just what it wants to believe. The laboring masses do not believe the false excuses of the vivisector, because they know that the vivisector experiments on hospital patients; and the masses belong to the hospital patient class. The well-to-do people who do not go to hospitals, and who think they benefit by the experiments made there, believe the vivisectors’ excuses, and angrily abuse and denounce the anti-vivisectors. The people who “love animals,” who keep pets, and stick pins through butterflies, support the performing dog people, and are sure that kindness will teach a horse to waltz. And the people who enjoy a fight will persuade themselves that boxing gloves do not hurt, and that sparring is an exercise which teaches self-control and exercises all the muscles in the body more efficiently than any other.

My own view of prizefighting may be gathered from Cashel Byron’s Profession, and from the play written by me more than ten years later, entitled Mrs. Warren’s Profession. As long as society is so organized that the destitute athlete and the destitute beauty are forced to choose between underpaid drudgery as industrial producers, and comparative self-respect, plenty, and popularity as prizefighters and mercenary brides, licit or illicit, it is idle to affect virtuous indignation at their expense. The word prostitute should either not be used at all, or else applied impartially to all persons who do things for money that they would not do if they had any other assured means of livelihood. The evil caused by the prostitution of the Press and the Pulpit is so gigantic that the prostitution of the prize-ring, which at least makes no serious moral pretensions, is comparatively negligible by comparison. Let us not forget, however, that the throwing of a hard word such as prostitution does not help the persons thus vituperated out of their difficulty. If the soldier and gladiator fight for money, if men and women marry for money, if the journalist and novelist write for money, and the parson preaches for money, it must be remembered that it is an exceedingly difficult and doubtful thing for an individual to set up his own scruples or fancies (he cannot himself be sure which they are) against the demand of the community when it says, Do thus and thus, or starve. It was easy for Ruskin to lay down the rule of dying rather than doing unjustly; but death is a plain thing: justice a very obscure thing. How is an ordinary man to draw the line between right and wrong otherwise than by accepting public opinion on the subject; and what more conclusive expression of sincere public opinion can there be than market demand? Even when we repudiate that and fall back on our private judgment, the matter gathers doubt instead of clearness. The popular notion of morality and piety is to simply beg all the most important questions in life for other people; but when these questions come home to ourselves, we suddenly discover that the devil’s advocate has a stronger case than we thought: we remember that the way of righteousness or death was the way of the Inquisition; that hell is paved, not with bad intentions, but with good ones; that the deeper seers have suggested that the way to save your soul is perhaps to give it away, casting your spiritual bread on the waters, so to speak. No doubt, if you are a man of genius, a Ruskin or an Ibsen, you can divine your way and finally force your passage. If you have the conceit of fanaticism you can die a martyr like Charles I. If you are a criminal, or a gentleman of independent means, you can leave society out of the question and prey on it. But if you are an ordinary person you take your bread as it comes to you, doing whatever you can make most money by doing. And you are really showing yourself a disciplined citizen and acting with perfect social propriety in so doing. Society may be, and generally is, grossly wrong in its offer to you; and you may be, and generally are, grossly wrong in supporting the existing political structure; but this only means, to the successful modern prizefighter, that he must reform society before he can reform himself. A conclusion which I recommend to the consideration of those foolish misers of personal righteousness who think they can dispose of social problems by bidding reformers of society reform themselves first.

Practically, then, the question raised is whether fighting with gloves shall be brought, like cockfighting, bear-baiting, and gloveless fist fighting, explicitly under the ban of the law. I do not propose to argue that question out here. But of two things I am certain. First, that glove fighting is quite as fierce a sport as fist fighting. Second, that if an application were made to the Borough Council of which I am a member, to hire the Town Hall for a boxing competition, I should vote against the applicants.

This second point being evidently the practical one, I had better give my reason. Exhibition pugilism is essentially a branch of Art: that is to say, it acts and attracts by propagating feeling. The feeling it propagates is pugnacity. Sense of danger, dread of danger, impulse to batter and destroy what threatens and opposes, triumphant delight in succeeding: this is pugnacity, the great adversary of the social impulse to live and let live; to establish our rights by shouldering our share of the social burden; to face and examine danger instead of striking at it; to understand everything to the point of pardoning (and righting) everything; to conclude an amnesty with Nature wide enough to include even those we know the worst of: namely, ourselves. If two men quarrelled, and asked the Borough Council to lend them a room to fight it out in with their fists, on the ground that a few minutes’ hearty punching of one another’s heads would work off their bad blood and leave them better friends, each desiring, not victory, but satisfaction, I am not sure that I should not vote for compliance. But if a syndicate of showmen came and said, Here we have two men who have no quarrel, but who will, if you pay them, fight before your constituency and thereby make a great propaganda of pugnacity in it, sharing the profits with us and with you, I should indignantly oppose the proposition. And if the majority were against me, I should try to persuade them to at least impose the condition that the fight should be with naked fists under the old rules, so that the combatants should, like Sayers and Langham, depend on bunging up each other’s eyes rather than, like the modern knocker-out, giving one another concussion of the brain.

I may add, finally, that the present halting between the legal toleration and suppression of commercial pugilism is much worse than the extreme of either, because it takes away the healthy publicity and sense of responsibility which legality and respectability give, without suppressing the blackguardism which finds its opportunity in shady pursuits. I use the term commercial advisedly. Put a stop to boxing for money; and pugilism will give society no further trouble.

The Fascinating Foundling

A Disgrace to the Author

Dramatis Personae

Horace Brabazon

Mercer, an elderly clerk

Cardonius Boshington, the Lord Chancellor

Anastasia Vulliamy

The Fascinating Foundling

Morning. Office of the Lord Chancellor. Door on the right leading to his private room, near the fireplace. Door on the left leading to the public staircase.

Mercer, an elderly clerk, seated at work. Enter, to him, through the public door, Horace Brabazon, a smart and beautiful young man of nineteen, dressed in the extremity of fashion, with a walking stick.
Brabazon | I want to see the Lord Chancellor.
Mercer | Have you an appointment?
Brabazon | No.
Mercer | Then you can’t see the Lord Chancellor.
Brabazon | I tell you I must see him.
Mercer | I tell you you cant. Look here: do you think the Lord Chancellor’s a palmist or a hair doctor that people can rush in out of the street and see him whenever they want to?
Brabazon | That speech was meant to insult and humiliate me. I make it a rule to fight people who attempt to insult and humiliate me. Throwing away his stick. Put up your hands. He puts up his own.
Mercer | Here: you let me alone. You leave this office, d’ye hear; or I’ll have the police in on you.
Brabazon | You are face to face with your destiny; and your destiny is to fight me. Be quick: I’m going to begin. Don’t look pale: I scorn to take you by surprise. I shall lead off with my left on your right eye. Put them up.
Mercer | I ain’t going to fight you. Let me alone, will you? I said nothing to you.
Brabazon | Liar and slave. Fight, I tell you: fight.
Mercer | Oh, was there ever the like of this? Don’t make such a noise.
Brabazon | I’m making it on purpose. I want you to fight because it’ll make more noise than anything else. The Lord Chancellor will come to see what the noise is about if only it’s loud enough. Time! He spars.
Mercer | Retreating to the fireplace and snatching up the poker. Ah, would you? You come near me, and I’ll split your head open, I will.
Brabazon | Snatching up the tongs, and engaging him in a stage fight of the noisiest. Lay on, Macduff; and damned be he that first cries Hold! Enough!
The Lord Chancellor enters indignantly.
The Lord Chancellor | What’s this? Who is this gentleman?
Brabazon | The Lord Chancellor. Good. To Mercer. Hence, horrible shadow: unreal mockery, hence. My lord, I have called on professional business. In the matter of Brabazon, an infant.
The Lord Chancellor | If you are a solicitor, sir, you must be aware that this is not the proper way to approach the Court.
Brabazon | I approach you as the father of all the orphans in Chancery.
The Lord Chancellor | Sir—
Brabazon | Don’t fly out: I’ll explain everything. You remember the matter of Brabazon, an infant. Come, now! frankly as man to man you do remember the matter of Brabazon, an infant.
The Lord Chancellor | There is such a case, I believe.
Brabazon | Of course there is. Well, I’m the infant. I’m Brabazon. I’ll call thee Hamlet! King! father! Royal Dane: wilt thou not answer me? Prosaically. Now you see, don’t you?
The Lord Chancellor | You are young Horace Brabazon, are you?
Brabazon | I am, my lord. Such is life!
The Lord Chancellor | You are a ward of the Court; and you have systematically disobeyed every order made in your case.
Brabazon | The orders were unreasonable. Fatuous, in fact.
The Lord Chancellor | Sir—
Brabazon | Let me explain. One of the orders was that I was to go into the Church.
The Lord Chancellor | At your own desire.
Brabazon | Exactly. But I should not have been indulged. I was too young. How did I know what was good for me? I put it to you as one man to another: do I look like an archbishop?
The Lord Chancellor | Stuff, sir.
Brabazon | As you say, nothing could have been more idiotic. You ought to have known better. No: the Church is not in my line. Nature intended me for the stage. The Unreal Mockery here was practising Macduff with me when you came in. Now what I want to know is, can you get me an engagement. As your ward, I have a right to expect that of you. You must know lots of people who could give me a start. And there’s another thing: very important. I—Oh, by the way, won’t you sit down? Excuse me keeping you standing all this time. Macduff: a chair.
The Lord Chancellor | With ironic politeness. You are too good. He sits down.
Brabazon | Don’t mention it. Well, you know: I want some good home influence to steady me. You see you can’t steady me: you’re too much occupied here with your shop: besides, you may shake a loose leg yourself occasionally for all the public knows, eh? Even if you are virtuous, I should probably lead you astray. No: what I want is a wife. Not a young woman, you know. Someone old enough to be my mother: say thirty or so. I adore a mature woman. Not old enough to be your mother, you understand: old enough to be my mother. I attach some importance to that distinction; so be good enough to bear it in mind. One mustn’t overdo these notions.
The Lord Chancellor | Mr. Mercer, will you be good enough to make a careful note of this gentleman’s requirements: an engagement at a leading theatre to play Macbeth, and a wife of quiet habits and grave disposition. Anything else, Mr. Brabazon?
Brabazon | Nothing today, thank you. And now, I know better than to take up the time of a busy man. Happy to have made your acquaintance. So long! Ta, ta, Macduff.
He goes out.
The Lord Chancellor | What do you mean by letting this lunatic in, Mr. Mercer? I’m extremely annoyed.
Mercer | I didn’t let him in, my lord. He came in. I was keeping him from you at the risk of my life when you came in to ask what the noise was.
The Lord Chancellor | With emotion. My faithful Mercer.
Mercer | My honored master. They shake hands, weeping.
The Lord Chancellor | We were happy together until this man came between us.
Mercer | Let us try to forget him, my lord. Turns to his desk and sees Brabazon’s walking stick on the floor. My lord, he has left his walking stick behind. He will return for it. Let us fly. He picks it up and puts it on the desk.
The Lord Chancellor | Nonsense, Mercer: we have no aeroplane; and if we had we shouldn’t know how to use it. Hark! A visitor at the door. They both rush to it. The handle is turned. Tell him we have both gone out.
Mercer | Useless, my lord: he is a man of strong reasoning powers: he would conclude, on hearing our voices, that we were both within.
A Woman’s Voice | Is anybody there? Let me in. She rattles the door.
The Lord Chancellor | That is the voice of a young and probably beautiful woman.
Mercer | It is, my lord.
The Lord Chancellor | Then why the dickens don’t you open the door instead of striking melodramatic attitudes? How dare you keep the lady waiting? I’m very much annoyed.
Mercer | I’m sorry, my lord. He opens the door.
Anastasia Vulliamy enters.
Anastasia | To Mercer. Is this the Lord Chancellor’s?
Mercer | Yes.
Anastasia | Sir Cardonius Boshington’s?
Mercer | Yes, ma’am.
Anastasia | Are you the Lord Chancellor?
Mercer | No, ma’am. Leastways, not yet.
Anastasia | What are you?
Mercer | I’m the Lord Chancellor’s—
Anastasia | Secretary?
Mercer | Well, hardly that, ma’am. If you ask me, I should say I was a sort of what you might call a clerk-valet to his lordship.
Anastasia | Are you a gentleman?
Mercer | Staggered. Well, that’s a poser, Miss, really. I’m in a manner of speaking a gentleman.
Anastasia | In what manner of speaking are you a gentleman?
Mercer | Well, Miss, I’m a gentleman to my tobacconist. Every man is a gentleman to his tobacconist. The parliamentary candidate for Hornsey always addresses me as a gentleman. But then he ain’t particular: leastways, not at election times. You see, Miss, there are three classes of gentry in this country.
Anastasia | Only three?
Mercer | Only three, ma’am.
Anastasia | How do you tell one from the other?
Mercer | You tell by the railway porters, Miss. The real upper class gives them a shilling; the upper middle class sixpence; and the lower middle, tuppence. I give tuppence myself.
Anastasia | And which particular class of gentleman is it, pray, that gives a lady a chair?
Mercer | Oh, I’m sure I beg your pardon, Miss. He places a chair for her.
Anastasia | Thanks. And now will you be good enough to tell Sir Cardonius Boshington that Miss Anastasia Vulliamy wishes to see him?
Mercer | To the Lord Chancellor. Miss Anaesthesia Vulliamy, my lord, to see you.
Anastasia | Springing up. Do you mean to tell me that this old man in livery is the great Chancellor?
The Lord Chancellor | At your service, Miss Vulliamy.
Anastasia | Producing a newspaper. Quite impossible. I have here an article on Sir Cardonius, headed Our Great Chancellor; and the description does not correspond in the least. Reading. “No man of our time has succeeded in tempering the awe inspired by a commanding stature and majestic presence with a love and confidence which even the youngest and most timid ward of the Court feels at the sound of his kindly voice and the encouraging beam, twinkling with humor, of his tender grey eyes.” Do you mean to tell me that that’s you?
The Lord Chancellor | It is not for me to say how far the description is an accurate or a happy one, madam; but I believe I am the person intended by the writer.
Mercer | Producing another paper. Perhaps you’d recognize this better, Miss. Sir Cardonius and me is on opposite sides in politics.
Anastasia | Taking the paper and reading at the place he indicates. “How much longer will the nation allow this despicable pantaloon to occupy the woolsack—” What’s the woolsack?
Mercer | What the Lord Chancellor sits on in the House of Lords, Miss.
Anastasia | Continuing her reading. “whose contents only too strongly resemble those of his own head.” That’s a nasty one, you know: isn’t it? It means that your brains are woolly, doesn’t it?
The Lord Chancellor | Its meaning is entirely beneath my notice. I’m surprised, Mercer, to find you in possession of a scurrilous rag of this character. We may differ in our opinions; but if any paper taken in by me were to speak of you in such unbecoming terms, I should never open it again.
Mercer | Well, my lord; politics is politics; and after all, what is politics if it isn’t showing up the other side? When I pay a penny for a paper I’ve a right to get value for my money the same as any other man.
Anastasia | But I don’t understand. To the Chancellor. Are you a despicable pantaloon? The other paper says your name will be cherished by the warm hearts of the English people when Eldon and Sir Thomas More are forgotten. I thought that whatever is in the papers must be true. How do you explain being a great Chancellor and a despicable pantaloon at the same time?
The Lord Chancellor | I take it that the excellent journal from which you first quoted has put all considerations of party aside, and simply endeavored to place before you a dispassionate estimate of such modest services as I have been able to render to my country. The other paper gives you nothing but the vituperative ravings of an illiterate penny-a-liner blinded by party passion.
Mercer | You should never read more than one paper, Miss. It unsettles the mind, let alone the waste of a penny.
Anastasia | Well, it’s a great relief to me to hear that the Great Chancellor paper is the right one. To the Lord Chancellor. You think I may believe everything it says?
The Lord Chancellor | I trust I shall not disappoint any favorable opinion you may have founded on it.
Anastasia | It says here that though you are stern with the worthless and merciless to the impostor, yet your mature wisdom and unparalleled legal knowledge are freely at the service of all deserving persons, and that no distressed suitor has ever been turned empty away from your door.
The Lord Chancellor | That refers to my private house, madam. I don’t keep food here.
Mercer | I have a sandwich for my lunch, Miss. Sooner than send you empty away, I would give it to you, Miss, most joyfully.
Anastasia | I ask, not charity, but justice.
The Lord Chancellor | Madam: I must request you to speak like a lady and not like a procession of the unemployed. The House of Lords always gives charity and never gives justice.
Mercer | The House of Lords will find itself unemployed one of these days, if you ask me.
The Lord Chancellor | Silence, Mercer. Have the goodness to keep your Radicalism to yourself in the presence of this lady.
Anastasia | Why do you allow your clerk to be a Radical?
The Lord Chancellor | Well, madam, to make him a Conservative and an Imperialist I should have to raise his salary very considerably; and I prefer to save money and put up with a Radical.
Anastasia | You’ll excuse me asking you all these questions; but as I’ve decided, after what the paper says, that you are the man to advise me and be a father to me, it’s very important that you should be quite all right, isn’t it?
The Lord Chancellor | But it’s not my business to be a father to every young lady who walks into my office.
Anastasia | Not your business! Why, Whitaker’s Almanac says you get £5,000 a year. You don’t get that for nothing, I suppose. To Mercer. By the way, Whitaker doesn’t say how much you get.
Mercer | I get one-fifty.
Anastasia | One-fifty into £5,000 goes about thirty-three times. Why does he get thirty-three times as much as you? Is he thirty-three times as good?
Mercer | He thinks so.
The Lord Chancellor | I set up no such ridiculous pretension, Mercer.
Anastasia | To the Lord Chancellor. Perhaps you’re thirty-three times as sober. How much do you drink every day?
The Lord Chancellor | I am almost a teetotaller. A single bottle of burgundy is quite sufficient for me.
Anastasia | To Mercer. Then I suppose you drink thirty-three bottles of burgundy a day.
Mercer | Thirty-three bottles of burgundy a day on one-fifty a year! Not me. It hardly runs to beer on Sundays.
Anastasia | Well, there must be something awfully wrong about you, you know, if you get only the thirty-third of what he gets.
The Lord Chancellor | No, madam, Mercer is an excellent man in his proper place.
Anastasia | Then there must be something awfully right about you.
The Lord Chancellor | I hope so.
Anastasia | I don’t see the difference myself.
Mercer | He’s better fed.
Anastasia | Is he? I should have thought he was too red about the nose to be quite healthy. It’s the burgundy, I expect. However, I didn’t come here to talk about you two. Call it selfish if you will; but I came to talk about myself. The fact is, I’m an orphan. At least, I think I am.
The Lord Chancellor | Don’t you know?
Anastasia | No. I was brought up in what you might politely call a sort of public institution. They found me on the doorstep, you know. Might have happened to anybody, mightnt it?
Mercer | Scandalized. And you have the audacity to come here and talk up to us as if you was a lady. Be off with you; and be ashamed of yourself, you hussy.
The Lord Chancellor | Gently, Mercer, gently. It is not the poor girl’s fault.
Mercer | Not her fault! Why, she ain’t anybody’s daughter: she’s only an offspring.
Anastasia | Perhaps I’m his daughter, my lord.
Mercer | Oh, you wicked girl! Oh, you naughty story, you! Oh, that I should have lived to have this accusation brought against me: me! a respectable man!
Anastasia | I had a feeling the moment I saw you.
The Lord Chancellor | The voice of Nature! Oh, Mercer, Mercer!
Mercer | I’ll have the law of you for this, I will. Oh, say you don’t believe her, my lord. Don’t drive me mad. Say you don’t believe her.
The Lord Chancellor | I can’t disregard the voice of Nature, Mercer. The evidence against you is very black.
Mercer | Me the father of a common girl found on a workhouse doorstep!
Anastasia | Rising most indignantly. How dare you presume to say such a thing? A workhouse doorstep indeed! I was found on the doorstep of one of the very best houses in Park Lane.
The Lord Chancellor | Overwhelmed. My dear young lady, how can I apologize—
Mercer | Crushed. I’m sure I beg your pardon most humbly, Miss.
The Lord Chancellor | Forget the rudeness of my clerk: he knows no better. Resume your seat, I beg.
Mercer | If I had only known, Miss! Park Lane! I could bite my tongue out for my bad manners, I do assure you.
Anastasia | Say no more. Of course you could not know my social position.
Mercer | Don’t say that, Miss. You have Park Lane in every feature.
The Lord Chancellor | Effusively. In your manners.
Mercer | In your accent.
The Lord Chancellor | In your tone—
Mercer | Address—
The Lord Chancellor | A je ne sais quoi—
Mercer | A tout ensemble—
Anastasia | You speak French?
Mercer | Not a word, Miss; but at the sight of that hat of yours the French fairly burst out of me.
Anastasia | You are very good—
The Lord Chancellor | Oh, not at all.
Mercer | Don’t mention it.
Anastasia | Don’t begin again. I forgive you both. Now, attention! I’m a good-hearted but somewhat flighty girl; and I require some serious interest in life to steady me. As I had an ungovernable appetite, and was naturally rather inclined to be stout, I tried politics. For you, a man, politics meant the House of Lords. For me, a woman, politics meant Holloway Gaol and the hunger strike. I refused to take food until I was so frightfully hungry that when the Governor—who was a plump, chubby, tempting sort of man, you know—came into my cell and remonstrated with me, I attempted to devour him.
The Lord Chancellor | Pardon me. I thought you Suffragist lambs prided yourselves on acting always on principle. On what principle, may I ask, do you justify an attempt to devour an estimable public official?
Anastasia | On the Cat and Mouse principle, my lord. That is a part of the law of England.
Mercer | Never. Not when the woman is the cat.
The Lord Chancellor | May I ask, madam, what the unfortunate mouse did on this occasion?
Anastasia | He got quite angry, and said he wouldn’t have me in his prison another minute—not if I went down on my knees and begged him to let me stay. Of course I refused to go; but I had to let the poor man have his way at last, though it took ten wardresses to persuade me to do it. I left them simply in ribbons, poor things. Prison made a great change in me. Before I went in I felt a great want of something to love; but when I came out I felt nothing but a great want of something to eat. There were two public houses near the prison. One had a placard up “Sausage and Mashed,” the other “Sandwich and Small Lloyd George.” I visited both in succession, and had two goes of each delicacy. I then drove to the Holborn Restaurant and had a five shilling lunch, stopping at three Pearce and Plentys on the way to sustain exhausted nature. At the Holborn they refused to serve me with a second lunch; so I went on to the Carlton. Of my subsequent experiences at the Savoy, Pagani’s, Frascati’s, Gatti’s, five baked potato men, and a coffee stall, I shall say nothing. Suffice it that when at last the craving for food was stilled, the craving for love returned in all its original force. I felt I must have something to cherish, to sacrifice myself for. You no doubt hold that self-sacrifice is a woman’s chief amusement.
The Lord Chancellor | Certainly I do.
Anastasia | Any man would. Well, what was I to love? My friends recommended marriage: a man, in fact. But I hesitated to rush at once to so expensive and troublesome an extreme. I tried a pet dog; but when it had been stolen for the sixth time by the man I bought it from, I refused to pay any more rewards, and we were parted forever. I tried a cat; but its conduct was so disreputable that I really could not live in the same house with it. I adopted the orphan child of a crossing sweeper who was run over; but when its aunt learnt that I had no parents she would not permit it to stay. Glad as I must confess I was to get rid of the little beast, my starved heart still ached, my empty arms still longed to gather some beloved object to my breast.
The Lord Chancellor | If I can be of any service to you, madam—
Anastasia | You? You are married, are you not?
The Lord Chancellor | Well, er, yes I er—am married.
Mercer | Catching her eye. I’m sorry, miss; but so am I. Still, a divorce would be a matter of only eighty pound or so if we made it a fairly straight case.
Anastasia |

Never shall it be said that Anastasia Vulliamy built her happiness on the ruin of another woman’s home. There are younger and handsomer men than you, my lord: there are more genteel characters than Mercer. Neither of you, if I may be allowed the expression, is precisely what I should call a peach. And I want—oh, I want a peach. He must be a young peach. Not that I am to be seduced by the fleeting charms of a smooth cheek and a slim figure. But it’s a necessity of my position as a woman that I should marry someone whom I can bully, because if a woman can’t bully her husband, her husband generally bullies her.

You, my lord, you will, you can,
Find me a young and foolish man.
Into my arms: under my thumb
Let him come, let him come.

I fear I am almost dropping into poetry; but the tumult of my emotions carries me away. I implore you not to keep me waiting. My soul, my soul is thrilling as it never thrilled before. My arms, my arms are longing as they never longed before. My heart, my heart is beating as it never bet before. Every nerve in my body, every fibre in my heart—

Brabazon enters.
Brabazon | Excuse me: I left my stick, I think—
Anastasia | Throwing herself into his arms. He has come: he has come: the very thing I want.
Brabazon | Quite out of the question, my dear lady. Sir Cardonius will tell you that you are too young, too irresponsible, too impulsive to be anything more to me than an extremely agreeable object of contemplation, and a charming hostess. With that object may I venture to propose a marriage to you?
Anastasia | Silly! that is exactly what I am proposing to you.
Brabazon | Not marriage to the same person, I think. You, as I understand it, propose to marry me. I propose that you should marry one of my friends. You can then invite me to your house, and put on your best company manners for my benefit. He will have the privilege of paying for your hats, and enjoying your no-company manners.
Mercer | My lord: this man has a giant intellect.
The Lord Chancellor | It will avail him as little as if he were the biggest fool in creation. Young man: you are lost. I argued as you do. I tried to get out of it.
Mercer | I moved all the way from Gospel Oak to Islington to escape; but it was no use.
The Lord Chancellor | Beware how you anger her by showing any reluctance. Remember: “Hell hath no fury like a woman scorned.”
Mercer | What’s the good of that nowadays? When that was written a woman would take no for an answer. She won’t now.
Anastasia | You will begin walking out with me at once. You are only on approval, of course; but if you suit, you may consider next Friday three weeks named as the day.
Brabazon | But where does the merit come in for me? Where is the moral discipline? Where is the self-sacrifice? You are an agreeable person: to marry you would be an act of pure selfishness.
Anastasia | So you think now, dearest. You won’t think that a year hence. I’ll take care of that for my own boy.
Brabazon | Yes, but look here, you know. Have you got any money?
Anastasia | Not a rap.
Brabazon | And you expect to get a slave for nothing. What cheek!
Anastasia | I’m richer than you think, darling. It’s true that I’m a poor penniless orphan. Doesn’t that touch you?
Brabazon | Not in the least.
Anastasia | Thoughtless boy. Have you forgotten that the women who have money always belong to some family or other?
Brabazon | Well?
Anastasia | Well, a family means relations. You can’t call your house your own. The brothers borrow money. The sisters come and stay for months. The mother quarrels with your mother.
Mercer | Gospel truth, every word of it.
The Lord Chancellor | Undeniable. He sighs deeply.
Anastasia | I, my love, am not perfect. I am a weak woman: I have nothing to cling to but your love, nor any place to rest except your very becoming fancy waistcoat. But at least I’m a foundling.
Brabazon | Excited and hopeful. A foundling?
Anastasia | I haven’t a relation in the world.
Brabazon | Clasping her. Mine! mine!! Mine!!!

The Glimpse of Reality

A Tragedietta

Dramatis Personae

Character, a character

Scene: A scene.

The Glimpse of Reality

In the fifteenth century AD. Gloaming. An inn on the edge of an Italian lake. A stone cross with a pedestal of steps. A very old Friar sitting on the steps. The angelus rings. The Friar prays and crosses himself. A girl ferries a boat to the shore and comes up the bank to the cross.

The Girl | Father: were you sent here by a boy from—
The Friar | In a high, piping, but clear voice. I’m a very old man. Oh, very old. Old enough to be your great grandfather, my daughter. Oh, very very old.
The Girl | But were you sent here by a boy from—
The Friar | Oh yes, yes, yes, yes, yes. Quite a boy, he was. Very young. And I’m very old. Oh, very very old, dear daughter.
The Girl | Are you a holy man?
The Friar | Ecstatically. Oh, very holy. Very, very, very, very holy.
The Girl | But have you your wits still about you, father? Can you absolve me from a great sin?
The Friar | Oh yes, yes, yes. A very great sin. I’m very old; but I’ve my wits about me. I’m one hundred and thirteen years old, by the grace of Our Lady; but I still remember all my Latin; and I can bind and loose; and I’m very very wise; for I’m old and have left far behind me the world, the flesh, and the devil. You see I am blind, daughter; but when a boy told me that there was a duty for me to do here, I came without a guide, straight to this spot, led by St. Barbara. She led me to this stone, daughter. It’s a comfortable stone to me: she has blessed it for me.
The Girl | It’s a cross, father.
The Friar | Piping rapturously. Oh blessed, blessed, ever blessed be my holy patroness for leading me to this sacred spot. Is there any building near this, daughter? The boy mentioned an inn.
The Girl | There is an inn, father, not twenty yards away. It’s kept by my father, Squarcio.
The Friar | And is there a barn where a very very old man may sleep and have a handful of peas for his supper?
The Girl | There is bed and board both for holy men who will take the guilt of our sins from us. Swear to me on the cross that you are a very holy man.
The Friar | I’ll do better than that, daughter. I’ll prove my holiness to you by a miracle.
The Girl | A miracle!
The Friar | A most miraculous miracle. A wonderful miracle! When I was only eighteen years of age I was already famous for my devoutness. When the hand of the blessed Saint Barbara, which was chopped off in the days when the church was persecuted, was found at Viterbo, I was selected by the Pope himself to carry it to Rome for that blessed lady’s festival there; and since that my hand has never grown old. It remains young and warm and plump whilst the rest of my body is withered almost to dust, and my voice is cracked and become the whistling you now hear.
The Girl | Is that true? Let me see. He takes her hand in his. She kneels and kisses it fervently. Oh, it’s true. You are a saint. Heaven has sent you in answer to my prayer.
The Friar | As soft as your neck, is it not? He caresses her neck.
The Girl | It thrills me: it is wonderful.
The Friar | It thrills me also, daughter. That, too, is a miracle at my age.
The Girl | Father—
The Friar | Come closer, daughter. I’m very very old and very very very deaf: you must speak quite close to my ear if you speak low. She kneels with her breast against his arm and her chin on his shoulder. Good. Good. That’s better. Oh, I’m very very old.
The Girl | Father: I am about to commit a deadly sin.
The Friar | Do, my daughter. Do, do, do, do, do.
The Girl | Discouraged. Oh, you do not hear what I say.
The Friar | Not hear! Then come closer, daughter. Oh, much much closer. Put your arm round my shoulders, and speak in my ear. Do not be ashamed, my daughter: I’m only a sack of old bones. You can hear them rattle. He shakes his shoulders and makes the beads of his rosary rattle at the same time. Listen to the old man’s bones rattling. Oh, take the old old man to heaven, Blessed Barbara.
The Girl | Your wits are wandering. Listen to me. Are you listening?
The Friar | Yes yes yes yes yes yes yes. Remember: whether I hear or not, I can absolve. All the better for you perhaps if I do not hear the worst. He! He! He! Well well. When my wits wander, squeeze my young hand; and the blessed Barbara will restore my faculties. She squeezes his hand vigorously. That’s right. Tha-a-a-a-ats right. Now I remember what I am and who you are. Proceed, my child.
The Girl | Father, I am to be married this year to a young fisherman.
The Friar | The devil you are, my dear.
The Girl | Squeezing his hand. Oh listen, listen; you are wandering again.
The Friar | That’s right: hold my hand tightly. I understand, I understand. This young fisherman is neither very beautiful nor very brave; but he is honest and devoted to you; and there is something about him different to all the other young men.
The Girl | You know him, then!
The Friar | No no no no no. I’m too old to remember people. But Saint Barbara tells me everything.
The Girl | Then you know why we can’t marry yet.
The Friar | He is too poor. His mother will not let him unless his bride has a dowry—
The Girl | Interrupting him impetuously. Yes, yes: oh blessed be Saint Barbara for sending you to me! Thirty crowns—thirty crowns from a poor girl like me: it is wicked—monstrous. I must sin to earn it.
The Friar | That will not be your sin, but his mother’s.
The Girl | Oh, that is true: I never thought of that. But will she suffer for it?
The Friar | Thousands of years in purgatory for it, my daughter. The worse the sin, the longer she will suffer. So let her have it as hot as possible. The Girl recoils. Do not let go my hand: I’m wandering. She squeezes his hand. That’s right, darling. Sin is a very wicked thing, my daughter. Even a mother-in-law’s sin is very expensive; for your husband would stint you to pay for masses for her soul.
The Girl | That is true. You are very wise, father.
The Friar | Let it be a venial sin: an amiable sin. What sin were you thinking of, for instance?
The Girl | There is a young Count Ferruccio the Friar starts at the name, son of the tyrant of Parma—
The Friar | An excellent young man, daughter. You could not sin with a more excellent young man. But thirty crowns is too much to ask from him. He can’t afford it. He is a beggar: an outcast. He made love to Madonna Brigita, the sister of Cardinal Poldi, a Cardinal eighteen years of age, a nephew of the Holy Father. The Cardinal surprised Ferruccio with his sister; and Ferruccio’s temper got the better of him. He threw that holy young Cardinal out of the window and broke his arm.
The Girl | You know everything.
The Friar | Saint Barbara, my daughter, Saint Barbara. I know nothing. But where have you seen Ferruccio? Saint Barbara says that he never saw you in his life, and has not thirty crowns in the world.
The Girl | Oh, why does not Saint Barbara tell you that I am an honest girl who would not sell herself for a thousand crowns.
The Friar | Do not give way to pride, daughter. Pride is one of the seven deadly sins.
The Girl | I know that, father; and believe me, I’m humble and good. I swear to you by Our Lady that it is not Ferruccio’s love that I must take, but his life. The Friar, startled, turns powerfully on her. Do not be angry, dear father: do not cast me off. What is a poor girl to do? We are very poor, my father and I. And I am not to kill him. I am only to decoy him here; for he is a devil for women; and once he is in the inn, my father will do the rest.
The Friar | In a rich baritone voice. Will he, by thunder and lightning and the flood and all the saints, will he? He flings off his gown and beard, revealing himself as a handsome youth, a nobleman by his dress, as he springs up and rushes to the door of the inn, which he batters with a stone. Ho there, Squarcio, rascal, assassin, son of a pig: come out that I may break every bone in your carcass.
The Girl | You are a young man!
The Friar | Another miracle of Saint Barbara. Kicking the door. Come out, whelp: come out, rat. Come out and be killed. Come out and be beaten to a jelly. Come out, dog, swine, animal, mangy hound, lousy—Squarcio comes out, sword in hand. Do you know who I am, dog?
Squarcio | Impressed. No, your Excellency.
The Friar | I am Ferruccio, Count Ferruccio, the man you are to kill, the man your devil of a daughter is to decoy, the man who is now going to cut you into forty thousand pieces and throw you into the lake.
Squarcio | Keep your temper, Signor Count.
Ferruccio | I’ll not keep my temper. I’ve an uncontrollable temper. I get blinding splitting headaches if I do not relieve my temper by acts of violence. I’ll relieve it now by pounding you to jelly, assassin that you are.
Squarcio | Shrugging his shoulders. As you please, Signor Count. I may as well earn my money now as another time. He handles his sword.
Ferruccio | Ass: do you suppose I have trusted myself in this territory without precautions? My father has made a wager with your feudal lord here about me.
Squarcio | What wager, may it please your Excellency?
Ferruccio | What wager, blockhead! Why, that if I am assassinated, the murderer will not be brought to justice.
Squarcio | So that if I kill you—
Ferruccio | Your Baron will lose ten crowns unless you are broken on the wheel for it.
Squarcio | Only ten crowns, Excellency! Your father does not value your life very highly.
Ferruccio | Dolt. Can you not reason? If the sum were larger your Baron would win it by killing me himself and breaking somebody else on the wheel for it: you, most likely. Ten crowns is just enough to make him break you on the wheel if you kill me, but not enough to pay for all the masses that would have to be said for him if the guilt were his.
Squarcio | That is very clever, Excellency. Sheathing his sword. You shall not be slain: I will take care of that. If anything happens, it will be an accident.
Ferruccio | Body of Bacchus! I forgot that trick. I should have killed you when my blood was hot.
Squarcio | Will your Excellency please to step in? My best room and my best cooking are at your Excellency’s disposal.
Ferruccio | To the devil with your mangy kennel! You want to tell every traveller that Count Ferruccio slept in your best bed and was eaten by your army of fleas. Take yourself out of my sight when you have told me where the next inn is.
Squarcio | I’m sorry to thwart your Excellency; but I have not forgotten your father’s wager; and until you leave this territory I shall stick to you like your shadow.
Ferruccio | And why, pray?
Squarcio | Someone else might kill your Excellency; and, as you say, my illustrious Baron might break me on the wheel for your father’s ten crowns. I must protect your Excellency, whether your Excellency is willing or not.
Ferruccio | If you dare to annoy me, I’ll handle your bones so that there will be nothing left for the hangman to break. Now what do you say?
Squarcio | I say that your Excellency overrates your Excellency’s strength. You would have no more chance against me than a grasshopper. Ferruccio makes a demonstration. Oh, I know that your Excellency has been taught by fencers and wrestlers and the like; but I can take all you can give me without turning a hair, and settle the account when you are out of breath. That is why common men are dangerous, your Excellency: they are inured to toil and endurance. Besides, I know all the tricks.
The Girl | Do not attempt to quarrel with my father, Count. It must be as he says. It is his profession to kill. What could you do against him? If you want to beat somebody, you must beat me. She goes into the inn.
Squarcio | I advise you not to try that, Excellency. She also is very strong.
Ferruccio | Then I shall have a headache: that’s all. He throws himself ill-humoredly on a bench at the table outside the inn. Giulia returns with a tablecloth and begins preparing the table for a meal.
Squarcio | A good supper, Excellency, will prevent that. And Giulia will sing for you.
Ferruccio | Not while there’s a broomstick in the house to break her ugly head with. Do you suppose I’m going to listen to the howling of a she-wolf who wanted me to absolve her for getting me killed?
Squarcio | The poor must live as well as the rich, sir. Giulia is a good girl. He goes into the inn.
Ferruccio | Shouting after him. Must the rich die that the poor may live?
Giulia | The poor often die that the rich may live.
Ferruccio | What an honor for them! But it would have been no honor for me to die merely that you might marry your clod of a fisherman.
Giulia | You are spiteful, Signor.
Ferruccio | I am no troubadour, Giuliaccia, if that is what you mean.
Giulia | How did you know about my Sandro and his mother? How were you so wise when you pretended to be an old friar? you that are so childish now that you are yourself?
Ferruccio | I take it that either Saint Barbara inspired me, or else that you are a great fool.
Giulia | Saint Barbara will surely punish you for that wicked lie you told about her hand.
Ferruccio | The hand that thrilled you?
Giulia | That was blasphemy. You should not have done it. You made me feel as if I had had a taste of heaven; and then you poisoned it in my heart as a taste of hell. That was wicked and cruel. You nobles are cruel.
Ferruccio | Well! do you expect us to nurse your babies for you? Our work is to rule and to fight. Ruling is nothing but inflicting cruelties on wrongdoers: fighting is nothing but being cruel to one’s enemies. You poor people leave us all the cruel work, and then wonder that we are cruel. Where would you be if we left it undone? Outside the life I lead all to myself—the life of thought and poetry—I know only two pleasures: cruelty and lust. I desire revenge: I desire women. And both of them disappoint me when I get them.
Giulia | It would have been a good deed to kill you, I think.
Ferruccio | Killing is always sport, my Giuliaccia.
Sandro’s Voice | On the lake. Giulietta! Giulietta!
Ferruccio | Calling to him. Stop that noise. Your Giulietta is here with a young nobleman. Come up and amuse him. To Giulietta. What will you give me if I tempt him to defy his mother and marry you without a dowry?
Giulia | You are tempting me. A poor girl can give no more than she has. I should think you were a devil if you were not a noble, which is worse. She goes out to meet Sandro.
Ferruccio | Calling after her. The devil does evil for pure love of it: he does not ask a price: he offers it. Squarcio returns. Prepare supper for four, bandit.
Squarcio | Is your appetite so great in this heat, Signor?
Ferruccio | There will be four to supper. You, I, your daughter, and Sandro. Do not stint yourselves: I pay for all. Go and prepare more food.
Squarcio | Your order is already obeyed, Excellency.
Ferruccio | How?
Squarcio | I prepared for four, having you here to pay. The only difference your graciousness makes is that we shall have the honor to eat with you instead of after you.
Ferruccio | Dog of a bandit: you should have been born a nobleman.
Squarcio | I was born noble, Signor; but as we had no money to maintain our pretensions, I dropped them. He goes back into the inn.
Giulia returns with Sandro.
Giulia | This is the lad, Excellency. Sandro: this is his lordship Count Ferruccio.
Sandro | At your lordship’s service.
Ferruccio | Sit down, Sandro. You, Giulia, and Squarcio are my guests. They sit.
Giulia | I’ve told Sandro everything, Excellency.
Ferruccio | And what does Sandro say? Squarcio returns with a tray.
Giulia | He says that if you have ten crowns in your purse, and we kill you, we can give them to the Baron. It would be the same to him as if he got it from your illustrious father.
Squarcio | Stupid: the Count is cleverer than you think. No matter how much money you give the Baron he can always get ten crowns more by breaking me on the wheel if the Count is killed.
Giulia | That is true. Sandro did not think of that.
Sandro | With cheerful politeness. Oh! what a head I have! I am not clever, Excellency. At the same time you must know that I did not mean my Giulietta to tell you. I know my duty to your Excellency better than that.
Ferruccio | Come! You are dear people: charming people. Let us get to work at the supper. You shall be the mother of the family and give us our portions, Giulietta. They take their places. That’s right. Serve me last, Giulietta. Sandro is hungry.
Squarcio | To the girl. Come come! do you not see that his Excellency will touch nothing until we have had some first. He eats. See, Excellency! I have tasted everything. To tell you the truth, poisoning is an art I do not understand.
Ferruccio | Very few professional poisoners do, Squarcio. One of the best professionals in Rome poisoned my uncle and aunt. They are alive still. The poison cured my uncle’s gout, and only made my aunt thin, which was exactly what she desired, poor lady, as she was losing her figure terribly.
Squarcio | There is nothing like the sword, Excellency.
Sandro | Except the water, Father Squarcio. Trust a fisherman to know that. Nobody can tell that drowning was not an accident.
Ferruccio | What does Giulietta say?
Giulia | I should not kill a man if I hated him. You cannot torment a man when he is dead. Men kill because they think it is what they call a satisfaction. But that is only fancy.
Ferruccio | And if you loved him? Would you kill him then?
Giulia | Perhaps. If you love a man you are his slave: everything he says—everything he does—is a stab to your heart: every day is a long dread of losing him. Better kill him if there be no other escape.
Ferruccio | How well you have brought up your family, Squarcio! Some more omelette, Sandro?
Sandro | Very cheerfully. I thank your Excellency. He accepts and eats with an appetite.
Ferruccio | I pledge you all. To the sword and the fisherman’s net: to love and hate! He drinks: they drink with him.
Squarcio | To the sword!
Sandro | To the net, Excellency, with thanks for the honor.
Giulia | To love, Signor.
Ferruccio | To hate: the noble’s portion!
Squarcio | The meal has done you good, Excellency. How do you feel now?
Ferruccio | I feel that there is nothing but a bait of ten crowns between me and death, Squarcio.
Squarcio | It is enough, Excellency. And enough is always enough.
Sandro | Do not think of that, Excellency. It is only that we are poor folk, and have to consider how to make both ends meet as one may say. Looking at the dish. Excellency—?
Ferruccio | Finish it, Sandro. I’ve done.
Sandro | Father Squarcio?
Squarcio | Finish it, finish it.
Sandro | Giulietta?
Giulia | Surprised. Me? Oh no. Finish it, Sandro: it will only go to the pig.
Sandro | Then, with your Excellency’s permission—He helps himself.
Squarcio | Sing for his Excellency, my daughter.
Giulia turns to the door to fetch her mandoline.
Ferruccio | I shall jump into the lake Squarcio, if your cat begins to meowl.
Sandro | Always cheerful and reassuring. No, no, Excellency: Giulietta sings very sweetly: have no fear.
Ferruccio | I do not care for singing: at least not the singing of peasants. There is only one thing for which one woman will do as well as another, and that is lovemaking. Come, Father Squarcio: I will buy Giulietta from you: you can have her back for nothing when I am tired of her. How much?
Squarcio | In ready money, or in promises?
Ferruccio | Old fox. Ready money.
Squarcio | Fifty crowns, Excellency.
Ferruccio | Fifty crowns! Fifty crowns for that black-faced devil! I would not give fifty crowns for one of my mother’s ladies-in-waiting, Fifty pence, you must mean.
Squarcio | Doubtless your Excellency, being a younger son, is poor. Shall we say five and twenty crowns?
Ferruccio | I tell you she is not worth five.
Squarcio | Oh, if you come to what she is worth, Excellency, what are any of us worth? I take it that you are a gentleman, not a merchant.
Giulia | What are you worth, Signorino?
Ferruccio | I am accustomed to be asked for favors, Giuliaccia, not to be asked impertinent questions.
Giulia | What would you do if a strong man took you by the scruff of your neck, or his daughter thrust a knife in your throat, Signor?
Ferruccio | It would be many a year, my gentle Giuliaccia, before any baseborn man or woman would dare threaten a nobleman again. The whole village would be flayed alive.
Sandro | Oh no, Signor. These things often have a great air of being accidents. And the great families are well content that they should appear so. It is such a great trouble to flay a whole village alive. Here by the water, accidents are so common.
Squarcio | We of the nobility, Signor, are not strict enough. I learnt that when I took to breeding horses. The horses you breed from thoroughbreds are not all worth the trouble: most of them are screws. Well, the horsebreeder gets rid of his screws for what they will fetch: they go to labor like any peasant’s beast. But our nobility does not study its business so carefully. If you are a screw, and the son of a baron, you are brought up to think yourself a little god, though you are nothing, and cannot rule yourself, much less a province. And you presume, and presume, and presume—
Giulia | And insult, and insult, and insult.
Squarcio | Until one day you find yourself in a strange place with nothing to help you but your own hands and your own wits—
Giulia | And you perish—
Sandro | Accidentally—
Giulia | And your soul goes crying to your father for vengeance—
Squarcio | If indeed, my daughter, there be any soul left when the body is slain.
Ferruccio | Crossing himself hastily. Dog of a bandit: do you dare doubt the existence of God and the soul?
Squarcio | I think, Excellency, that the soul is so precious a gift that God will not give it to a man for nothing. He must earn it by being something and doing something. I should not like to kill a man with a good soul. I’ve had a dog that had, I’m persuaded, made itself something of a soul; and if anyone had murdered that dog, I would have slain him. But show me a man with no soul: one who has never done anything or been anything; and I will kill him for ten crowns with as little remorse as I would stick a pig.
Sandro | Unless he be a nobleman, of course—
Squarcio | In which case the price is fifty crowns.
Ferruccio | Soul or no soul?
Squarcio | When it comes to a matter of fifty crowns, Excellency, business is business. The man who pays me must square the account with the devil. It is for my employer to consider whether the action be a good one or no: it is for me to earn his money honestly. When I said I should not like to kill a man with a good soul, I meant killing on my own account: not professionally.
Ferruccio | Are you such a fool then as to spoil your own trade by sometimes killing people for nothing?
Squarcio | One kills a snake for nothing, Excellency. One kills a dog for nothing sometimes.
Sandro | Apologetically. Only a mad dog, Excellency, of course.
Squarcio | A pet dog, too. One that eats and eats and is useless, and makes an honest man’s house dirty. He rises. Come, Sandro, and help me to clean up. You, Giulia, stay and entertain his Excellency.
He and Sandro make a hammock of the cloth, in which they carry the wooden platters and fragments of the meal indoors. Ferruccio is left alone with Giulia. The gloaming deepens.
Ferruccio | Does your father do the house work with a great girl like you idling about? Squarcio is a fool, after all.
Giulia | No, Signor: he has left me here to prevent you from escaping.
Ferruccio | There is nothing to be gained by killing me, Giuliaccia.
Giulia | Perhaps; but I do not know. I saw Sandro make a sign to my father: that is why they went in. Sandro has something in his head.
Ferruccio | Brutally. Lice, no doubt.
Giulia | Unmoved. That would only make him scratch his head, Signor, not make signs with it to my father. You did wrong to throw the Cardinal out of the window.
Ferruccio | Indeed: and pray why?
Giulia | He will pay thirty crowns for your dead body. Then Sandro could marry me.
Ferruccio | And be broken on the wheel for it.
Giulia | It would look like an accident, Signor. Sandro is very clever; and he is so humble and cheerful and good-tempered that people do not suspect him as they suspect my father.
Ferruccio | Giulietta: if I reach Sacromonte in safety, I swear to send you thirty crowns by a sure messenger within ten days. Then you can marry your Sandro. How does that appeal to you?
Giulia | Your oath is not worth twenty pence, Signor.
Ferruccio | Do you think I will die here like a rat in a trap—His breath fails him.
Giulia | Rats have to wait in their traps for death, Signor. Why not you?
Ferruccio | I’ll fight.
Giulia | You are welcome, Signor. The blood flows freeest when it is hot.
Ferruccio | She devil! Listen to me, Giulietta—
Giulia | It is useless, Signor. Giulietta or Giuliaccia: it makes no difference. If they two in there kill you it will be no more to me—except for the money—than if my father trod on a snail.
Ferruccio | Oh, it is not possible that I, a nobleman, should die by such filthy hands.
Giulia | You have lived by them, Signor. I see no sign of any work on your own hands. We can bring death as well as life, we poor people, Signor.
Ferruccio | Mother of God, what shall I do?
Giulia | Pray, Signor.
Ferruccio | Pray! With the taste of death in my mouth? I can think of nothing.
Giulia | It is only that you have forgotten your beads, Signor. She picks up the Friar’s rosary. You remember the old man’s bones rattling. Here they are. She rattles them before him.
Ferruccio | That reminds me. I know of a painter in the north that can paint such beautiful saints that the heart goes out of one’s body to look at them. If I get out of this alive I’ll make him paint St. Barbara so that everyone can see that she is lovelier than St. Cecilia, who looks like my washerwoman’s mother in her Chapel in our cathedral. Can you give St. Cecilia a picture if she lets me be killed?
Giulia | No; but I can give her many prayers.
Ferruccio | Prayers cost nothing. She will prefer the picture unless she is a greater fool than I take her to be.
Giulia | She will thank the painter for it, not you, Signor. And I’ll tell her in my prayers to appear to the painter in a vision, and order him to paint her just as he sees her if she really wishes to be painted.
Ferruccio | You are devilishly ready with your answers. Tell me, Giulietta: is what your father told me true? Is your blood really noble?
Giulia | It is red, Signor, like the blood of the Christ in the picture in Church. I do not know if yours is different. I shall see when my father kills you.
Ferruccio | Do you know what I am thinking, Giulietta?
Giulia | No, Signor.
Ferruccio | I am thinking that if the good God would oblige me by taking my fool of an elder brother up to heaven, and his silly doll of a wife with him before she has time to give him a son, you would make a rare duchess for me. Come! Will you help me to outwit your father and Sandro if I marry you afterwards?
Giulia | No, Signor: I’ll help them to kill you.
Ferruccio | My back is to the wall, then?
Giulia | To the precipice, I think, Signor.
Ferruccio | No matter, so my face is to the danger. Did you notice, Giulia, a minute ago? I was frightened.
Giulia | Yes, Signor. I saw it in your face.
Ferruccio | The terror of terrors.
Giulia | The terror of death.
Ferruccio | No: death is nothing. I can face a stab just as I faced having my tooth pulled out at Faenza.
Giulia | Shuddering with sincere sympathy. Poor Signorino! That must have hurt horribly.
Ferruccio | What! You pity me for the tooth affair, and you did not pity me in that hideous agony of terror that is not the terror of death nor of anything else, but pure grim terror in itself.
Giulia | It was the terror of the soul, Signor. And I do not pity your soul: you have a wicked soul. But you have pretty teeth.
Ferruccio | The toothache lasted a week; but the agony of my soul was too dreadful to last five minutes: I should have died of it if it could have kept its grip of me. But you helped me out of it.
Giulia | I, Signor!
Ferruccio | Yes: you. If you had pitied me: if you had been less inexorable than death itself, I should have broken down and cried and begged for mercy. But now I have come up against something hard: something real: something that does not care for me. I see now the truth of my excellent uncle’s opinion that I was a spoilt cub. When I wanted anything I threatened men or ran crying to women; and they gave it to me. I dreamed and romanced: imagining things as I wanted them, not as they really are. There is nothing like a good look into the face of death: close up: right on you: for showing you how little you really believe and how little you really are. A priest said to me once, “In your last hour everything will fall away from you except your religion.” But I have lived through my last hour; and my religion was the first thing that fell away from me. When I was forced at last to believe in grim death I knew at last what belief was, and that I had never believed in anything before: I had only flattered myself with pretty stories, and sheltered myself behind Mumbo Jumbo, as a soldier will shelter himself from arrows behind a clump of thistles that only hide the shooters from him. When I believe in everything that is real as I believed for that moment in death, then I shall be a man at last. I have tasted the water of life from the cup of death; and it may be now that my real life began with this he holds up the rosary and will end with the triple crown or the heretic’s fire: I care not which. Springing to his feet. Come out, then, dog of a bandit, and fight a man who has found his soul. Squarcio appears at the door, sword in hand. Ferruccio leaps at him and strikes him full in the chest with his dagger. Squarcio puts back his left foot to brace himself against the shock. The dagger snaps as if it had struck a stone wall.
Giulia | Quick, Sandro.
Sandro, who has come stealing round the corner of the inn with a fishing net, casts it over Ferruccio, and draws it tight.
Squarcio | Your Excellency will excuse my shirt of mail. A good home blow, nevertheless, Excellency.
Sandro | Your Excellency will excuse my net: it is a little damp.
Ferruccio | Well, what now? Accidental drowning, I suppose.
Sandro | Eh, Excellency, it is such a pity to throw a good fish back into the water when once you have got him safe in your net. My Giulietta: hold the net for me.
Giulia | Taking the net and twisting it in her hands to draw it tighter round him. I have you very fast now, Signorino, like a little bird in a cage.
Ferruccio | You have my body, Giulia. My soul is free.
Giulia | Is it, Signor? I think Saint Barbara has got that in her net too. She has turned your jest into earnest.
Sandro | It is indeed true, sir, that those who come under the special protection of God and the Saints are always a little mad; and this makes us think it very unlucky to kill a madman. And since from what Father Squarcio and I overheard, it is clear that your Excellency, though a very wise and reasonable young gentleman in a general way, is somewhat cracked on the subject of the soul and so forth, we have resolved to see that no harm comes to your Excellency.
Ferruccio | As you please. My life is only a drop falling from the vanishing clouds to the everlasting sea, from finite to infinite, and itself part of the infinite.
Sandro | Impressed. Your Excellency speaks like a crazy but very holy book. Heaven forbid that we should raise a hand against you? But your Excellency will notice that this good action will cost us thirty crowns.
Ferruccio | Is it not worth it?
Sandro | Doubtless, doubtless. It will in fact save us the price of certain masses which we should otherwise have had said for the souls of certain persons who—ahem! Well, no matter. But we think it dangerous and unbecoming that a nobleman like your Excellency should travel without a retinue, and unarmed; for your dagger is unfortunately broken, Excellency. If you would therefore have the condescension to accept Father Squarcio as your man-at-arms—your servant in all but the name, to save his nobility—he will go with you to any town in which you will feel safe from His Eminence the Cardinal, and will leave it to your Excellency’s graciousness as to whether his magnanimous conduct will not then deserve some trifling present: say a wedding gift for my Giulietta.
Ferruccio | Good: the man I tried to slay will save me from being slain. Who would have thought Saint Barbara so full of irony!
Sandro | And if the offer your Excellency was good enough to make in respect of Giulietta still stands—
Squarcio | Rascal: have you then no soul?
Sandro | I am a poor man, Excellency: I cannot afford these luxuries of the rich.
Ferruccio | There is a certain painter will presently make a great picture of St. Barbara; and Giulia will be his model. He will pay her well. Giulia: release the bird. It is time for it to fly.
She takes the net from his shoulders.

The Music Cure

A Piece of Utter Nonsense

Dramatis Personae

Character, a character

Scene: A scene.

The Music Cure

Lord Reginald Fitzambry, a fashionably dressed, rather-pretty young man of 22, is prostrate on a sofa in a large hotel drawing room, crying convulsively. His doctor is trying to soothe him. The doctor is about a dozen years his senior; and his ways are the ways of a still youthful man who considers himself in smart society as well as professionally attendant on it. The drawing room has tall central doors, at present locked. If anyone could enter under these circumstances, he would find on his left a grand piano with the keyboard end towards him, and a smaller door beyond the piano. On his right would be the window, and, further on, the sofa on which the unhappy youth is wallowing, with, close by it, the doctor’s chair and a little table accommodating the doctor’s hat, a plate, a medicine bottle, a half emptied glass, and a bell call.

The Doctor | Come come! be a man. Now really this is silly. You mustn’t give way like this. I tell you nothing’s happened to you. Hang it all! it’s not the end of the world if you did buy a few shares—
Reginald | Interrupting him frantically. I never meant any harm in buying those shares. I am ready to give them up. Oh, I never meant any harm in buying those shares. I never meant any harm in buying those shares. Clutching the doctor imploringly. Won’t you believe me, Doctor? I never meant any harm in buying those shares. I never—
The Doctor | Extricating himself and replacing Reginald on the couch., not very gently. Of course you didnt. I know you didnt.
Reginald | I never—
The Doctor | Desperate. Don’t go on saying that over and over again or you will drive us all as distracted as you are yourself. This is nothing but nerves. Remember that you’re in a hotel. They’ll put you out if you make a row.
Reginald | Tearfully. But you don’t understand. Oh, why won’t anybody understand? I never—
The Doctor | Shouting him down. You never meant any harm in buying those shares. This is the four hundredth time you’ve said it.
Reginald | Wildly. Then why do you keep asking me the same questions over and over again? It’s not fair. I’ve told you I never meant any harm in—
The Doctor | Yes, yes, yes: I know, I know. You think you made a fool of yourself before that committee. Well, you didnt. You stood up to it for six days with the coolness of an iceberg and the cheerfulness of an idiot. Every member of it had a go at you; and everyone of them, including some of the cleverest cross-examiners in London, fell back baffled before your fatuous self-satisfaction, your impenetrable in- ability to see any reason why you shouldn’t have bought those shares.
Reginald | But why shouldn’tI have bought them? I made no secret of it. When the Prime Minister ragged me about it I offered to sell him the shares for what I gave for them.
The Doctor | Yes, after they had fallen six points. But never mind that. The point for you is that you are an under- secretary in the War Office. You knew that the army was going to be put on vegetarian diet, and that the British Maccaroni Trust shares would go up with a rush when this became public. And what did you do?
Reginald | I did what any fellow would have done. I bought all the shares I could afford.
The Doctor | You bought a great many more than you could afford.
Reginald | But why shouldn’tI? Explain it to me. I’m anxious to learn. I meant no harm. I see no harm. Why am I to be badgered because the beastly Opposition papers and all the Opposition rotters on that committee try to make party capital out of it by saying that it was disgraceful? It wasn’t disgraceful: it was simple common sense. I’m not a financier; but you can’t persuade me that if you happen to know that certain shares are going to rise you shouldn’t buy them. It would be flying in the face of Providence not to. And they wouldn’t see that. They pretended not to see it. They worried me, and kept asking me the same thing over and over again, and wrote blackguardly articles about me—
The Doctor | And you got the better of them all because you couldn’t see their point of view. But what beats me is why you broke down afterwards.
Reginald | Everyone was against me. I thought the committee a pack of fools; and I as good as told them so. But everyone took their part. The governor said I had disgraced the family name. My brothers said I ought to resign from my clubs. My mother said that all her hopes of marrying me to a rich woman were shattered. And I’d done nothing: absolutely nothing to what other chaps are doing every day.
The Doctor | Well, the long and short of it is that officials mustn’t gamble.
Reginald | But I wasn’t gambling. I knew. It isn’t gambling if you know that the shares will go up. It’s a cert.
The Doctor | Well, all I can tell you is that if you weren’t a son of the Duke of Dunmow, you’d have to resign; and—
Reginald | Breaking down. Oh, stop talking to me about if. Let me alone. I can’t bear it. I never meant any harm in buying those shares. I never meant any harm—
The Doctor | Sh-sh-sh-sh-sh! There: I shouldn’t have started the subject again. Take some of this valerian. He puts the glass to Reginald’s lips. That’s right. Now you’re better.
Reginald | Exhausted but calm. Why does valerian soothe me when it excites cats[??]? There’s a question to reflect on! You know, they ought to have made me a philosopher.
The Doctor | Philosophers are born, not made.
Reginald | Fine old chestnut, that. Everybody’s born, not made.
The Doctor | You’re getting almost clever. I don’t like it: voure not yourself today. I wish I could take your mind off your troubles. Suppose you try a little music.
Reginald | I can’t play. My fingers won’t obey me. And I can’t stand the sound of the piano. I sounded a note this morning: and it made me scream.
The Doctor | But why not get somebody to play to you?
Reginald | Whom could I get, even if I could bear it? You can’t play.
The Doctor | Well: I’m not the only person in the world.
Reginald | If you bring anyone else in here, I shall go mad. I’ll throw myself out of the window. I can’t bear the idea of music. I dread it, hate it, loathe it.
The Doctor | That’s very serious, you know.
Reginald | Why is it serious?
The Doctor | Well, what would become of you without your turn for music[??]? You have absolutely no capacity in any other direction.
Reginald | I’m in Parliament. And I’m an undersecretary.
The Doctor | That’s because your father is a Duke. If you were in a Republic you wouldn’t be trusted to clean boots, unless your father was a millionaire. No, Reginald the day you give up vamping accompaniments and playing the latest ragtimes by ear, you’re a lost man socially.
Reginald | Deprecating. Oh, I say!
The Doctor | Rising. However, perhaps it’s too soon for you to try the music-cure yet. It was your mother’s idea; but I’ll call and tell her to wait a day or two. I think she meant to send somebody to play. I must be off now. Look in again later. Meanwhile, sleep as much as you can. Or you might read a little.
Reginald | What can I read?
The Doctor | Try the Strand Magazine.
Reginald | But it’s so frightfully intellectual. It would overtax my brain.
The Doctor | Oh, well, I suppose it would. Well, sleep. Perhaps I’d better give you something to send you off. He produces a medicine case.
Reginald | What’s this[??]? Veronal[??]?
The Doctor | Don’t be alarmed. Only the old-fashioned remedy: opium. Take this Reginald takes a pill: that will do the trick, I expect. If you find after half an hour that it has only excited you, take another. I’ll leave one for you. He puts one on the plate, and pockets his medicine case.
Reginald | Better leave me a lot. I like pills.
The Doctor | Thank you: I’m not treating you with a view to a coroner’s inquest. You know, don’t you, that opium is a poison[??]?
Reginald | Yes, opium. But not pills.
The Doctor | Well, Heaven forbid that I, a doctor, should shake anybody’s faith in pills. But I shan’t leave you enough to kill you. He puts on his hat.
Reginald | You’ll tell them, won’t you, not to let anyone in. Really and truly I shall throw myself out of the window if any stranger comes in. I should go out of my mind.
The Doctor | None of us have very far to go to do that, my young friend. Ta ta, for the moment. He makes for the central doors.
Reginald | You can’t go out that way. I made my mother lock it and take away the key. I felt sure they’d let somebody in that way if she didnt. You’ll have to go the way you came.
The Doctor | Returning. Right. Now let me see you settle down before I go. I want you to be asleep before I leave the room.
Reginald | settles himself to sleep -with his face to the back of the sofa. The Doctor goes softly to the side door and goes out.
Reginald | Sitting up wildly and staring affrightedly at the piano. Doctor! Doctor Help!!!
The Doctor | Returning hastily. What is it?
Reginald | After another doubtful look at the piano. Nothing. He composes himself to sleep again.
The Doctor | Nothing! There must have been something or you wouldn’t have yelled like that. Pulling Reginald over so as to see his face. Here! what was it[??]?
Reginald | Well, it’s gone.
The Doctor | What’s gone?
Reginald | The crocodile.
The Doctor | The crocodile!
Reginald | Yes. It laughed at me, and was going to play the piano with its tail.
The Doctor | Opium in small doses doesn’t agree with you, my young friend. Taking the spare pill from the plate. I shall have to give you a second pill.
Reginald | But suppose two crocodiles come!
The Doctor | They won’t. If anything comes it will be something pretty this time. That’s how opium acts. Anyhow, you’ll be fast asleep in ten minutes. Here. Take it.
Reginald | After taking the pill. It was awfully silly of me. But you know I really saw the thing.
The Doctor | You needn’t trouble about what you see with your eyes shut. He turns to the door.
Reginald | Would you mind looking under the sofa to make sure the crocodile isn’t there?
The Doctor | Why not look yourself? that would be more convincing.
Reginald | I daren’t.
The Doctor | You duffer! He looks. All serene. No crocodile. Now go bye bye. He goes out.
Reginald again composes himself to sleep. Somebody unlocks the central doors. A lovely Lady enters with a bouquet in her hand, She looks about her; takes a letter from wherever she carries [??] letters; and starts on a voyage of discovery round the room, checking her observations by the contents of the letter. The piano seems specially satisfactory: she nods as she sees it. Reginald seems also to be quite expected. She does not speak to him. When she is quite satisfied that she is in the right room, she goes to the piano and tantalizes the expectant audience for about two minutes by putting down her flowers on the candle-stand; taking off her gloves and putting them with the flowers; taking off half a dozen diamond rings in the same way; sitting down to the keyboard and finding it too near to the piano, then too far, then too high, then too low: in short, exhausting all the tricks of the professional pianist before she at last strikes the keys and preludes brilliantly. At the sound, Reginald, with a scream, rolls from the sofa and writhes on the carpet in horrible contortions. She stops playing, amazed.
Reginald | Oh! Oh! Oh! The crocodiles! Stop! Ow! Oh! He looks at the piano and sees the Lady. Oh I say!
The Lady | What on earth do you mean by making that noise when I’m playing? Have you no sense? Have you no manners[??]?
Reginald | Sitting on the floor. I’m awfully sorry.
The Lady | Sorry! Why did you do it?
Reginald | I thought you were a crocodile.
The Lady | What a silly thing to say! Do I look like a crocodile?
Reginald | No.
The Lady | Do I play like a crocodile!
Reginald | Cautiously rising and approaching her. Well, you know, it’s so hard to know how a crocodile would play.
The Lady | Stuff! She resumes her playing.
Reginald | Please! He stops her by shutting the keyboard lid. Who let you in[??]?
The Lady | Rising threateningly. What is that to you, pray?
Reginald | Retreating timidly. It’s my room, you know.
The Lady | It’s nothing of the sort. It’s the Duchess of Dunmow’s room. I know it’s the right one, because she gave me the key; and it was the right key.
Reginald | But what did she do that for[??]? Who are you, if you don’t mind my asking?
The Lady | I do mind your asking. It’s no business of yours. However, you’d better know to whom you are speaking. I am Strega Thundridge. She pronounces it Strayga.
Reginald | What! The female Paderewski!
Strega | Pardon me. I believe Mr. Paderewski has been called the male Thundridge; but no gentleman would dream of repeating such offensive vulgarities. Will you be Good enough to return to your sofa, and hold your tongue, or else leave the room.
Reginald | But, you know, I am ill.
Strega | Then go to bed, and send for a doctor. She sits down again to the keyboard.
Reginald | Falling on his knees. You mustn’t play. You really mustn’t. I can’t stand it. I shall simply not be myself if you start playing.
Strega | Raising the lid. Then I shall start at once.
Reginald | Running to her on his knees and snatching at her hands. No, you shan’t. She rises indignantly. He holds on to her hands, but exclaims ecstatically: Oh, I say, what lovely hands you’ve got!
Strega | The idea! She hurls him to the carpet.
Reginald | On the floor staring at her. You are strong.
Strega | My strength has been developed by playing left hand octave passages—like this. She begins playing Liszt’s transcription of Schubert’s Erl König.
Reginald | Puts his fingers in his ears, but continues to stare at her.
Strega | Stopping. I really cannot play if you keep your ears stopped. It is an insult. Leave the room.
Reginald | But I tell you it’s my room.
Strega | Rising. Leave the room, or I will ring your bell and have you put out. She goes to the little table, and poises her fingers over the bell call.
Reginald | Rushing to her. No no: somebody will come if you ring; and I shall go distracted if a stranger comes in. With a touch of her left hand she sends him reeling. He appeals to her plaintively. Don’t you see that I am ill?
Strega | I see that you are mentally afflicted. But that doesn’t matter to me. The Duchess of Dunmow has engaged me to come to this room and play for two hours. I never break an engagement, especially a two hundred and fifty guinea one. She turns towards the piano.
Reginald | But didn’t she tell you anything about me?
Strega | Turning back to him. She said there would be a foolish young man in the room, but that I was not to mind him. She assured me you were not dangerous except to your- self Collaring him and holding him bent backwards over the piano. But I will have no nonsense about not listening. All the world listens when I play. Listen, or go.
Reginald | Helpless. But I shall have to sit on the stairs. I daren’t go into any of the rooms: I should meet people there.
Strega | You will meet plenty of people on the stairs, young man. They are sitting six on each stair, not counting those who are sitting astride the banisters on the chance of hearing me play.
Reginald | How dreadful! Tearfully. You’ve no right to bully me like this. I’m ill: I can’t bear it. I’ll throw myself out of the window.
Strega | Releasing him. Do. What an advertisement! It will be really kind of you. She goes back to the keyboard and sits down to play.
Reginald | Crossing to the window. You’ll be sorry you were so unfeeling when you see my mangled body. He opens the window; looks out; shuts it hastily, and retreats with a scream. There’s a crowd. I daren’t.
Strega | Pleased. Waiting to hear me play. She preludes softly.
Reginald | Ravished. Oh! I can stand that, you know.
Strega | Ironically, still preluding. Thank you.
Reginald | The fact is, I can play a bit myself.
Strega | Still preluding. An amateur, I presume.
Reginald | I have often been told I could make a living at it if I tried. But of course it wouldn’t do for a man in my position to lower himself by becoming a professional.
Strega | Abruptly ceasing to play. Tactful, that, I don’t think! And what do you play, may I ask?
Reginald | Oh, all the very best music.
Strega | For instance?
Reginald | I wish you belonged to me.
Strega | Rising outraged. You young blackguard! How dare you?
Reginald | You don’t understand: it’s the name of a tune. Let me play it for you. He sits down at the keyboard. I don’t think you believe I can play.
Strega | Pardon me. I have heard a horse play the harmonium at a music hall. I can believe anything.
Reginald | Aha! He plays. Do you like that?
Strega | What is it? Is it intended for music?
Reginald | Oh, you beautiful doll.
Strega | Take that! She knocks him sprawling over the keyboard.[??] Beautiful doll indeed!
Reginald | Oh, I say! Look here: that’s the name of the tune too. You seem quite ignorant of the best music. Don’t you know “Rum Turn Tiddle,” and “Alexander’s Rag Time Band,” and “Take me back to the Garden of Love,” and “Everybody likes our Mary?”
Strega | Young man: I have never even heard of these abominations. I am now going to educate you musically. I am going to play Chopin, and Brahms, and Bach, and Schumann, and—
Reginald | Horrified. You don’t mean classical music?
Strega | I do. He bolts through the central doors.
Strega | Disgusted. Pig! She sits down at the piano again.
Reginald | Rushing back into the room. I forgot the people on the stairs: crowds of them. Oh, what shall I do! Oh don’t, Don’t, DONT play classical music to me. Say you won’t. Please.
Strega | Looks at him enigmatically and softly plays a Liebeslieder Waltz.!!
Reginald | Oh, I say: that’s rather pretty.
Strega | Like it?
Reginald | Awfully. Oh, I say, you know: I really do wish you belonged to me. Strega suddenly plays a violent Chopin study. He goes into convulsions. Oh! Stop! Mercy! Help! Oh please, please!
Strega | Pausing with her hands raised over the keyboard, ready to pounce on the chords. Will you ever say that again[??]?
Reginald | Never. I beg your pardon.
Strega | Satisfied. Hm! She drops her hands in her lap.
Reginald | Wiping his brow. Oh, that was fearfully classical.
Strega | You want your back stiffened a little, my young friend. Besides, I really cannot earn two hundred and fifty guineas by playing soothing syrup to you. Now prepare for the worst. I’m going to make a man of you.
Reginald | How?
Strega | With Chopin’s Polonaise in A Flat. Now. Imagine yourself going into battle. He runs away as before. Goose!
Reginald | Returning as before. The crowd is worse than ever. Have you no pity?
Strega | Come here. Don’t imagine yourself going into battle. Imagine that you have just been in a battle; and that you have saved your country by deeds of splendid bravery; and that you are going to dance with beautiful women who are proud of you. Can you imagine that?
Reginald | Rathe-e-e-errr. That’s how I always do imagine myself.
Strega | Right. Now listen. She plays the first section of the Polonaise. Reginald flinches at first, but gradually braces himself; stiffens; struts; throws up his head and slaps his chest. That’s better. What a hero! After a difficult passage. Takes a bit of doing, that, dearest child. Coming to the chords which announce the middle section. Now for it.
Reginald | Unable to contain himself. Oh, this is too glorious. I must have a turn or I shall forget myself.
Strega | Can you play this? Nothing but this. She plays the octave passage in the bass.
Reginald | Just riddle tiddle, riddle tiddle, riddle tiddle, riddle tiddle? Nothing but that?
Strega | Very softly at first. Like the ticking of a watch. Then louder and louder, as you feel my soul swelling.
Reginald | I understand. Just give me those chords again to buck me up to it. She plays the chords again. He plays the octave passages; and they play the middle section as a duet. At the repeat he cries: Again! again!
Strega | It’s meant to be played again. Now.They repeat it. At the end of the section she pushes him off the bench on to the floor, and goes on with the Polonaise alone.
Reginald | Wonderful woman: I have a confession to make, a confidence to impart. Your playing draws it from me. Listen, Strega she plays a horrible discord I mean Miss Thundridge.
Strega | That’s better; but I prefer Wonderful Woman.
Reginald | You are a wonderful woman, you know. Adored one—would you mind my taking a little valerian? I’m so excited. He takes some. A—a—ah! Now I feel that I can speak. Listen to me, goddess. I am not happy. I hate my present existence. I loathe parliament. I am not fit for public affairs. I am condemned to live at home with five coarse and brutal sisters who care for nothing but Alpine climbing, and looping the loop on aeroplanes, and going on deputations, and fighting the police. Do you know what they call me?
Strega | Playing softly. What do they call you, dear?
Reginald | They call me a Clinger. Well, I confess it. I am a Clinger. I am not fit to be thrown unprotected upon the world. I want to be shielded. I want a strong arm to lean on, a dauntless heart to be gathered to and cherished, a breadwinner on whose income I can live without the sordid horrors of having to make money for myself. I am a poor little thing, I know, Strega; but I could make a home for you. I have great taste in carpets and pictures. I can cook like anything. I can play quite nicely after dinner. Though you mightnt think it, I can be quite stern and strongminded with servants. I get on splendidly with children; they never talk over my head as grownup people do. I have a real genius for home life. And I shouldn’t at all mind being tyrannized over a little: in fact, I like it. It saves me the trouble of having to think what to do. Oh, Strega, don’t you want a dear little domesticated husband who would have no concern but to please you, no thought outside our home, who would be unspotted and unsoiled by the rude cold world, who would never meddle in politics or annoy you by interfering with your profession? Is there any hope for me?
Strega | Coming away from the piano. My child: I am a hard, strong, independent, muscular woman. How can you, with your delicate soft nature, see anything to love in me? I should hurt you, shock you, perhaps—yes: let me confess.it—I have a violent temper, and might even, in a transport of rage, beat you.
Reginald | Oh do, do. Don’t laugh at this ridiculous confession; but ever since I was a child I have had only one secret longing, and that was to be mercilessly beaten by a splendid, strong, beautiful woman.
Strega | Solemnly. Reginald—I think your mother spoke of you as Reginald?—
Reginald | Rejjy.
Strega | I too have a confession to make. I too need some music to speak through. Will you be so good[??]?
Reginald | Angel. He rushes to the piano and plays sympathetically whilst she speaks.
Strega | I, too, have had my dream. It has consoled me through the weary hours when I practised scales for eight hours a day. It has pursued me through the applause of admiring thousands in Europe and America. It is a dream of a timid little heart fluttering against mine, of a gentle voice to welcome me home, of a silky moustache to kiss my weary fingers when I return from a Titanic struggle with Tchaikovsky’s Concerto in G major, of somebody utterly dependent on me, utterly devoted to me, utterly my own, living only to be cherished and worshipped by me.
Reginald | But you would be angry sometimes: terrible, splendid, ruthless, violent. You would throw down the thing you loved and trample on it as it clung to your feet.
Strega | Yes—oh, why do you force me to confess it?—I should beat it to a jelly, and then cast myself in transports of remorse on its quivering frame and smother it with passionate kisses.
Reginald | Transported. Let it be me, let it be me.
Strega | You dare face this terrible destiny?
Reginald | I embrace it. I adore you. I am wholly yours. Oh, let me cling, cling, cling.
Strega | Embracing him fiercely. Nothing shall tear you from my arms now.
Reginald | Nothing. I am provided for. Oh how happy this will make my mother!
Strega | Sweet: name the day.
He plays a wedding march. She plays the bass.

Endnotes

In a treatise on boxing by Captain Edgeworth Johnstone, just published, I read, “In the days of the prize-ring, fights lasted for hours; and the knockout blow was unknown.” This statement is a little too sweeping. The blow was known well enough. A veteran prizefighter once described to me his first experience of its curious effect on the senses. Only, as he had thirty seconds to recover in instead of ten, it did not end the battle. The thirty seconds made the knockout so unlikely that the old pugilists regarded it as a rare accident, not worth trying for. The glove fighter tries for nothing else. Nevertheless knockouts, and very dramatic ones too (Mace by King, for example), did occur in the prize-ring from time to time. Captain Edgeworth Johnstone’s treatise is noteworthy in comparison with the earlier Badminton handbook of sparring by Mr. E. B. Michell (one of the Queensberry champions) as throwing over the old teaching of prize-ring boxing with mufflers, and going in frankly for glove fighting, or, to put it classically, cestus boxing. ↩